<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-model href="../schema/wwp-store.rng"    type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><?xml-model href="../schema/wwp-store.isosch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?><!-- $Id: astell.marriage.xml 36665 2019-03-27 21:46:14Z aclark $ --><TEI xmlns="http://www.wwp.northeastern.edu/ns/textbase" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xml:lang="en">
  <teiHeader xml:id="TR00465.hdr">
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="main">Reflections Upon Marriage, 1706</title>
        <author>
          <persName ref="p:mastell.ojo" type="person-female">Astell, Mary</persName>
        </author>
        <sponsor>Brown University</sponsor>
        <sponsor>Northeastern University</sponsor>
        <funder>U.S. National Endowment for the Humanities</funder>
        <funder/>
      </titleStmt>
      <xi:include href="../common-boilerplate.xml" xpointer="element(WWPedition)"/>    
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Northeastern University Women Writers Project</publisher>
        <address>
          <addrLine>SL 213</addrLine>
          <addrLine>Northeastern University</addrLine>
          <addrLine>360 Huntington Avenue</addrLine>
          <addrLine>Boston, MA  02115-5005</addrLine>
          <addrLine>USA</addrLine>
          <addrLine>url:mailto:wwp@neu.edu</addrLine>
          <addrLine>url:http://www.wwp.northeastern.edu/</addrLine>
        </address>
        <idno type="WWP">TR00465</idno>
        <idno type="URL">http://www.wwp.northeastern.edu/texts/astell.marriage.html</idno>
        <xi:include href="../common-boilerplate.xml" xpointer="element(WWPavailability)"/>
        <date when="2002-01-30"/>
      </publicationStmt>
      <notesStmt>
        <note type="textual">
          <p>Pagination skips pages 81–82 so the printed page
		numbers are incorrect from page 80 on. However, the
		text is continuous. Also, page number 87 is
		misprinted as 78.</p>
        </note>
      </notesStmt>
      <sourceDesc n="OT00465">
        <biblStruct>
          <monogr>
            <author>
              <persName ref="p:mastell.ojo" type="titlePage">Mary Astell</persName>
              <persName ref="p:mastell.ojo" type="regularized">Astell, Mary</persName>
            </author>
            <title>Reflections upon marriage</title>
            <edition>Third edition</edition>
            <idno type="unknown">unknown</idno>
            <imprint>
              <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
              <publisher>
                <persName ref="p:rwilkin.tox" type="titlePage">R. Wilkin</persName>
                <persName ref="p:rwilkin.tox" type="regularized">Wilkin, R.</persName>
              </publisher>
              <date when="1706">1706</date>
            </imprint>
            <extent>
              <measure unit="page" quantity="118"/>
            </extent>
            <extent>
              <dimensions>
                <format>octavo</format>
              </dimensions>
            </extent>
          </monogr>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <xi:include href="../common-boilerplate.xml" xpointer="element(WWPprojectDescription)"/>
      <xi:include href="../common-boilerplate.xml" xpointer="element(WWPsamplingDeclaration)"/>
      <xi:include href="../common-boilerplate.xml" xpointer="element(WWPeditorialDeclaration)"/>
      <xi:include href="../common-boilerplate.xml" xpointer="element(WWPcharacterDeclaration)"/>
      <tagsDecl>
        <rendition xml:id="rend.ind1" selector="p">first-indent(1)</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="rend.it" selector="persName, foreign, name, placeName, mcr, emph, salute, quote">slant(italic)</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="rend.break" selector="">break(yes)</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="rend.nobreak" selector="">break(no)</rendition>
        <rendition xml:id="rend.alri" selector="mw">align(right)</rendition>
      </tagsDecl>
      <xi:include href="../common-boilerplate.xml" xpointer="element(WWPclassificationDeclaration)"/>
      <xi:include href="../common-boilerplate.xml" xpointer="element(WWPlistPrefixDefinitions)"/>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <catRef type="main" target="#G.non-fiction"/>
        <catRef type="other" target="#G.non-fiction.essay"/>
      </textClass>
      <xi:include href="../common-boilerplate.xml" xpointer="element(WWPcalendarDescription)"/>
      <xi:include href="../common-boilerplate.xml" xpointer="element(WWPlangUsage)"/>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change n="RCS-1.56" when="2010-07-16" who="p:jmelson.nep">added <att>type</att> to <gi>docRole</gi></change>
      <change n="RCS:1.52" when="2009-11-19" who="p:jmelson.nep">changed several name elements to persName</change>
      <change n="RCS:1.51" when="2009-09-15" who="p:npeterson.gwx">name key correction for Herod</change>
      <change n="RCS:1.50" when="2009-08-31" who="p:npeterson.gwx">name key fix</change>
      <change n="RCS:1.49" when="2009-08-27" who="p:jmelson.nep">name key fix</change>
      <change n="RCS:1.48" when="2009-08-27" who="p:jmelson.nep">name key fixes</change>
      <change n="RCS:1.47" when="2009-08-11" who="p:npeterson.gwx">added name key for Athaliah</change>
      <change n="RCS:1.46" when="2009-06-10" who="p:jmelson.nep">changed name key for Josiah</change>
      <change n="RCS:1.45" when="2009-04-07" who="p:npeterson.gwx">new name keys</change>
      <change n="RCS:1.44" when="2009-04-06" who="p:jmelson.nep">Updated name key for the Duchess of Mazarine to reflect deletion of original record in names authority database</change>
      <change n="RCS:1.43" when="2009-02-12" who="p:npeterson.gwx">additional name keys</change>
      <change n="RCS:1.42" when="2008-12-20" who="p:npeterson.gwx">finished initial personography. Ambiguities and gaps will be posted to the wiki.</change>
      <change n="RCS:1.41" when="2008-12-19" who="p:npeterson.gwx">personography through line 828</change>
      <change n="RCS:1.40" when="2008-10-14" who="p:lmanders.vko">checked for placeName in persName:  not sure about Duke and Dutchess Mazarine</change>
      <change n="RCS:1.39" when="2008-10-10" who="p:npeterson.gwx">improvement</change>
      <change n="RCS:1.38" when="2008-10-02" who="p:npeterson.gwx">improvement</change>
      <change n="RCS:1.31" when="2001-12-18" who="p:zmizuho.zgk">Checking round correx entry. Supravalidated. Moved on-deck.</change>
      <change n="RCS:1.30" when="2001-06-12" who="p:zmizuho.zgk">Correx entry. Supravalidated. Printed.</change>
      <change n="RCS:1.25" when="1999-11-02" who="p:jrussom.zxg">Replaced line-end hard hyphens with soft hyphens</change>
      <change n="RCS:1.18" when="1999-08-26" who="p:pcaton.xzc">Deleted the DIV for the supposed 'frontispiece' (because it is a bookplate); 
	  added number and r/v values to the pi signatures; corrected encoding of the titlepage border; validated against DTD 1.2.2.</change>
      <change n="RCS:1.17" when="1999-08-25" who="p:jflanders.lfw">Entered corrections from checking round, fixed errata list; supravalidated, ran SPAM, casefix, and other cleanup routines.</change>
      <change when="1999-08-17" who="p:ldohanian.bik">Completed first round of corrections from first proofing of text.</change>
      <change when="1999-08-14" who="p:ldohanian.bik">Successful supravalidation using emacs with psgml 
         on Unix with version 1.2.2 of wwp-store DTD.</change>
      <change when="1999-08-14" who="p:ldohanian.bik">Julia found missing pages and I completed capture using emacs with psgml 
         on Unix with version 1.2.2 of wwp-store DTD.</change>
      <change when="1999-02-12" who="p:ldohanian.bik">Began capture using emacs with psgml on Unix with
	  version 2.0 of wwp-store DTD.</change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text xml:id="TR00465">
    <hyperDiv>
</hyperDiv>
    <front>
      <titleBlock>
        <pb n="i"/>
        <milestone n="π1r" unit="sig"/>
        <mw type="border-ornamental" rend="place(fullPageSurround)"/>
        <titlePart rend="align(center)case(allcaps)post(#rule)" type="main">Reflections
	  	<lb/>upon
	  	<lb/>Marriage.</titlePart>
        <gap desc="handwriting" reason="omitted"/>
        <titlePart rend="post(#rule)" type="desc">The Third Edition.</titlePart>
        <titlePart rend="post(#rule)" type="desc">To which is Added
	  	<lb/><hi rend="case(smallcaps)">A Preface</hi>, in Anſwer to ſome
	  <lb rend="indent(+1)"/>Objections.</titlePart>
        <epigraph>
          <quote source="b:IT50001">
            <p rend="first-indent(-1)post(#rule)">If a Virgin Marry, ſhe hath not ſinned; neverthe­
	  	<lb/>leſs ſuch ſhall have trouble.
            </p>
            <p rend="first-indent(-1)">The Wife is bound by the Law ſo long as her Huſ­
            	<lb/>band liveth, but if her Husband be dead ſhe
	  	<lb/>is at liberty to be Married to whom ſhe will,
	  	<lb/>only in the Lord. But ſhe is happier if ſhe
	  	<lb/>ſo abide after my Judgment.
            </p>           
          </quote>
        	<bibl source="b:IT50001">
        		<regMe>1 Cor. 7. 28,
        		<lb/>39, 40.</regMe>
        	</bibl>
        </epigraph>
        <docImprint rend="align(center)"><pubPlace rend="case(allcaps)">London:</pubPlace>
	  <lb/>Printed for <docRole type="publisher"><persName ref="p:rwilkin.tox">R. Wilkin</persName></docRole>, at the <placeName>King's Head</placeName>
	  <lb/>in <placeName>St. <hi rend="slant(italic)">Paul</hi>'s Church-Yard</placeName>, <docDate when="1706">1706</docDate>.</docImprint>
      </titleBlock>
      <pb n="ii"/>
      <milestone n="π1v" unit="sig"/>
      <pb n="iii"/>
      <milestone n="π2r" unit="sig"/>
      <div type="prefatory">
        <head rend="align(center)case(allcaps)">The 
	  	<lb/>Preface.</head>
        <p rend="slant(italic)first-indent(0)"><hi rend="class(#DIC)">T</hi><hi rend="case(allcaps)">h</hi>eſe
	  Reflections being made in the Country,
	<lb/>where the Book that occaſion'd them came
	<lb/>but late to Hand, the <mcr rend="slant(upright)">Reader</mcr> is deſir'd to
	<lb/>excuſe their Unſeaſonableneſs as well as other Faults;
	<lb/>and to believe that they have no other Deſign than to
	  <lb/>Correct ſome Abuſes, which <ref xml:id="er1" type="error" target="#ec1">are</ref> not the leſs becauſe
	<lb/>Power and Preſcription ſeem to Authorize them. If any
	<lb/>is ſo needleſly curious as to enquire from what Hand
	<lb/>they come, they may pleaſe to know, that it is not good
	<lb/>Manners to ask, ſince the Title-Page does not tell
	<lb/>them: We are all of us ſufficiently Vain, and with­
	<lb/>out doubt the Celebrated Name of <mcr rend="slant(upright)">Author</mcr>, which moſt
	<lb/>are ſo fond of, had not been avoided but for very good
	<lb/>Reaſons: To name but one; <mcr rend="slant(upright)">Who will care to pull
	<lb/>upon themſelves an Hornet's Neſt?</mcr> 'Tis a very
	<lb/>great Fault to regard rather who it is that Speaks,
	<lb/>than what is Spoken; and either to ſubmit to Authority,
	<lb/>when we ſhould only yield to Reaſon; or if Reaſon
	<lb/>preſs too hard, to think to ward it off by Perſonal
	<lb/>Objections and Reflections. Bold Truths may paſs
	<lb/>while the Speaker is <mcr rend="slant(upright)">Incognito</mcr>, but are not endur'd when
	<lb/>he is known; few Minds being ſtrong enough to bear
	<lb/>what contradicts their Principles and Practices with­
	<lb/>out Recriminating when they can. And tho' to tell
	<lb/>the Truth be the moſt Friendly Office, yet whoſoever is
	<lb/>ſo hardy as to venture at it, ſhall be counted an Enemy
	<lb/>for ſo doing.</p>
      </div>
      <div rend="slant(italic)" type="prefatory">
        <pb n="iv"/>
        <milestone n="π2v" unit="sig"/>
        <head rend="align(center)">Thus far the old Advertiſement, when the Re­
	<lb/>flections firſt appear'd, <date when="1700" rend="slant(italic)">A.D. 1700</date>.</head>
        <p><lb/>But the <mcr rend="slant(upright)">Reflector</mcr>, who hopes 
            <mcr rend="slant(upright)">Reflector</mcr> is not bad
	<lb/>Engliſh, now <mcr rend="slant(upright)">Governor</mcr> is happily of the Feminine
	<lb/>Gender, had as good or better have ſaid nothing; For
	<lb/>People by being forbid, are only excited to a more cu­
	<lb/>rious Enquiry. A certain <ref xml:id="er2" type="error" target="#ec2">Ingenious</ref> Gentleman (as
	<lb/>ſhe is inform'd) had the Good-Nature to own theſe
	<lb/>Reflections, ſo far as to affirm that he had the
	<lb/>Original <mcr rend="slant(upright)">M. S.</mcr> in his Cloſet, a Proof ſhe is not able
	<lb/>to produce; and ſo to make himſelf reſponſible for all
	<lb/>their Faults, for which ſhe returns him all due Acknow­
	<lb/>ledgment. However, the Generality being of Opinion,
	<lb/>that a Man would have had more Prudence and Man­
	<lb/>ners than to have Publiſh'd ſuch unſeaſonable Truths,
	<lb/>or to have betray'd the <foreign rend="slant(upright)" xml:lang="la">Arcana
            Imperii</foreign> of his Sex,
	<lb/>ſhe humbly confeſſes, that the Contrivance and Execu­
	<lb/>tion of this Deſign, which is unfortunately accus'd of
	<lb/>being ſo deſtructive to the Government, of the Men I
	<lb/>mean, is entirely her own. She neither advis'd with
	<lb/>Friends, nor turn'd over Antient or Modern Authors,
	<lb/>nor prudently ſubmitted to the Correction of ſuch as are,
	<lb/>or ſuch as <emph rend="slant(upright)">think</emph> they are good Judges, but with an
	<lb/><mcr rend="slant(upright)">Engliſh</mcr> Spirit and Genius, ſet out upon the
	    Forlorn
	<lb/>Hope, meaning no hurt to any body, nor deſigning any
	<lb/>thing but the Publick Good, and to retrieve, if poſ­
	<lb/>ſible, the Native Liberty, the Rights and Privileges
	<lb/>of the Subject.</p>
        <p>Far be it from her to ſtir up Sedition of any ſort,
	<lb/>none can abhor it more; and ſhe heartily wiſhes that
	<lb/>our Maſters wou'd pay their Civil and Eccleſiaſtical
	<lb/>Governors the ſame Submiſſion, which they themſelves
	<lb/>exact from their Domeſtic Subjects. Nor can ſhe ima­
	  <mw type="catch">gine</mw>

<pb n="v"/>
<milestone n="A1r" unit="sig"/>
	<lb/><choice><sic>ima</sic><corr/></choice>gine how ſhe any way undermines the Maſculine
	<lb/>Empire, or blows the Trumpet of Rebellion to the Moiety
	<lb/>of Mankind. Is it by exhorting Women, not to ex­
	<lb/>pect to have their own Will in any thing, but to be en­
	<lb/>tirely Submiſſive, when once they have made choice of
	<lb/>a Lord and Maſter, tho' he happen not to be ſo Wiſe,
	<lb/>ſo Kind, or even ſo Juſt a Governor as was expected?
	<lb/>She did not indeed adviſe them to think his Folly Wiſdom,
	<lb/>nor his Brutality that Love and Worſhip he promiſed
	<lb/>in his Matrimonial Oath, for this required a Flight
	<lb/>of Wit and Senſe much above her poor Ability, and
	<lb/>proper only to Maſculine Underſtandings. However ſhe
	<lb/>did not in any manner prompt them to Reſiſt, or to
	<lb/>Abdicate the Perjur'd Spouſe, tho' the Laws of <mcr rend="slant(upright)case(allcaps)">God</mcr>
	<lb/>and the Land make ſpecial Proviſion for it, in a
	<lb/>caſe wherein, as is to be fear'd, few Men can truly
	<lb/>plead Not Guilty.</p>
        <p>'Tis true, thro' Want of Learning, and of that Su­
	<lb/>perior Genius which Men as Men lay claim to, ſhe
	<lb/>was ignorant of the <mcr rend="slant(upright)">Natural Inferiority</mcr> of our Sex,
	<lb/>which our Maſters lay down as a Self-Evident and
	<lb/>Fundamental Truth. She ſaw nothing in the Reaſon of
	<lb/>Things, to make this either a Principle or a Conclu­
	<lb/>ſion, but much to the contrary; it being Sedition at
	<lb/>leaſt, if not Treaſon to aſſert it in this Reign. For if by
	<lb/>the Natural Superiority of their Sex, they mean that
	<lb/><mcr rend="slant(upright)">every</mcr> Man is by Nature ſuperior to 
	    <mcr rend="slant(upright)">every</mcr> Woman,
	<lb/>which is the obvious meaning, and that which muſt
	<lb/>be ſtuck to if they would ſpeak Senſe, it wou'd be a Sin
	<lb/>in <mcr rend="slant(upright)">any</mcr> Woman to have Dominion over 
            <mcr rend="slant(upright)">any</mcr> Man, and
	<lb/>the greateſt Queen ought not to command but to obey her
	<lb/>Footman, becauſe no Municipal Laws can ſuperſede
	<lb/>or change the Law of Nature; ſo that if the Dominion
	<lb/>of the Men be ſuch, the <mcr rend="slant(upright)">Salique Law</mcr>, as
	    unjuſt as <mcr rend="slant(upright)">En­
	<lb/>gliſh Men</mcr> have ever thought it, ought to take place
	  <mw rend="align(center)slant(upright)" type="sig">A</mw>
	  <mw rend="break(no)" type="catch">over</mw>

<pb n="vi"/>
<milestone n="A1v" unit="sig"/>
	<lb/>over all the Earth, and the moſt glorious Reigns in
	<lb/>the <name rend="slant(upright)">Engliſh</name>, <name rend="slant(upright)">Daniſh</name>, 
            <name rend="slant(upright)">Caſtilian</name>, and other Annals,
	<lb/>were wicked Violations of the Law of Nature!</p>
        <p>If they mean that <mcr rend="slant(upright)">ſome</mcr> Men are ſuperior to
           <mcr rend="slant(upright)">ſome</mcr>
	<lb/>Women, this is no great Diſcovery; had they turn'd
	<lb/>the Tables they might have ſeen that <emph rend="slant(upright)">ſome</emph> Women
	<lb/>are Superior to <emph rend="slant(upright)">ſome</emph> Men. Or had they been pleaſed to
	<lb/>remember their Oaths of Allegiance and Supremacy,
	<lb/>they might have known that <emph rend="slant(upright)">One</emph> Woman is ſu­
	<lb/>perior to <emph rend="slant(upright)">All</emph> the Men in theſe Nations, or elſe they
	<lb/>have ſworn to very little purpoſe. And it muſt not
	<lb/>be ſuppos'd, that their Reaſon and Religion wou'd
	<lb/>ſuffer them to take Oaths, contrary to the Law of Na­
	<lb/>ture and Reaſon of things.</p>
        <p>By all which it appears, that our Reflector's Igno­
	<lb/>rance is very pitiable, it may be her Misfortune but not
	<lb/>her Crime, eſpecially ſince ſhe is willing to be better in­
	<lb/>form'd, and hopes ſhe ſhall never be ſo obſtinate as to
	<lb/>ſhut her Eyes againſt the Light of Truth, which is not to
	<lb/>be charg'd with Novelty, how late ſoever we may be
	<lb/>bleſs'd with the Diſcovery. Nor can Error, be it as
	<lb/>Antient as it may, ever plead Preſcription againſt
	<lb/>Truth. And ſince the only way to remove all Doubts,
	<lb/>to anſwer all Objections, and to give the Mind entire
	<lb/>Satisfaction, is not by <mcr rend="slant(upright)">Affirming</mcr>, but by
	    <mcr rend="slant(upright)">Proving</mcr>, ſo
	<lb/>that every one may ſee with their <mcr rend="slant(upright)">own</mcr> Eyes, and
	<lb/>Judge according to the beſt of their <mcr rend="slant(upright)">own</mcr>
	    Underſtand­
	<lb/>ings, She hopes it is no Preſumption to inſiſt on this
	<lb/>Natural Right of Judging for her ſelf, and the rather,
	<lb/>becauſe by quitting it, we give up all the Means of 
	<lb/>Rational Conviction. Allow us then as many Glaſſes as
	<lb/>you pleſe to help our Sight, and as many good Argu­
	<lb/>ments as you can afford to Convince our Underſtand­
	<lb/>ings: But don't exact of us we beſeech you, to affirm
	<lb/>that we ſee ſuch things as are only the Diſcovery of
	  <mw type="catch">Men</mw>

<pb n="vii"/>
<milestone n="A2r" unit="sig"/>
	<lb/>Men who have quicker Senſes; or that we underſtand
	<lb/>and Know what we have by Hear-ſay only; for to be ſo
	<lb/>exceſſively Complaiſant, is neither to ſee nor to under­
	<lb/>ſtand.</p>
        <p>That the Cuſtom of the World has put Women, general­
	<lb/>ly ſpeaking, into a State of Subjection, is not deny'd; but
	<lb/>the Right can no more be prov'd from the Fact, than
	<lb/>the Predominancy of Vice can juſtifie it. A certain
	<lb/>great Man has endeavour'd to prove by Reaſons not
	<lb/>contemptible, that in the Original State of things the
	<lb/>Woman was the Superior, and that her Subjection to
	<lb/>the Man is an Effect of the Fall, and the Puniſhment
	<lb/>of her Sin. And that Ingenious Theoriſt <persName ref="p:wwhiston.ycp">Mr. <hi rend="slant(upright)">Whiſton</hi></persName>
	<lb/>aſſerts, That before the Fall there was a greater equal­
	<lb/>lity between the two Sexes. However this be, 'tis cer­
	<lb/>tainly no Arrogance in a Woman to conclude, that ſhe
	<lb/>was made for the Service of <mcr rend="slant(upright)case(allcaps)">God</mcr>, and that this is her
	<lb/>End. Becauſe <mcr rend="slant(upright)case(allcaps)">God</mcr> made all Things for Himſelf, and
	<lb/>a Rational Mind is too noble a Being to be Made for
	<lb/>the Sake and Service of any Creature. The Service ſhe
	<lb/>at any time becomes oblig'd to pay to a Man, is only a
	<lb/>Buſineſs by the Bye. Juſt as it may be any Man's Bu­
	<lb/>ſineſs and Duty to keep Hogs; he was not Made for this,
	<lb/>but if he hires himſelf out to ſuch an Employment, he
	<lb/>ought conſcientiouſly to perform it. Nor can any thing
	<lb/>be concluded to the contrary from <persName ref="p:paul.pbe">St. 
            <hi rend="slant(upright)">Paul</hi>'s</persName> Argu­
	  <lb/>ment, <bibl source="b:IT50001"><regMe>1 Cor. II.</regMe></bibl> For he argues only for Decency
	<lb/>and Order, according to the preſent Cuſtom and State
	<lb/>of things. Taking his Words ſtrictly and literally, they
	<lb/>prove too much, in that <mcr rend="slant(upright)">Praying and Prophecying in
	<lb/>the Church</mcr> are allow'd the Women, provided they do
	<lb/>it with their Head Cover'd, as well as the Men; and
	<lb/>no inequality can be inferr'd from hence, neither from
        	<lb/>the Gradation the Apoſtle there uſes, that <quote source="b:IT50001" rend="slant(upright)">the Head of
	<lb/>every Man is <persName ref="p:jchrist.hjn" rend="slant(upright)">Chriſt</persName>, 
            and that the Head of the Wo­
	  <mw rend="align(center)" type="sig">A2</mw>
	  <mw rend="break(no)" type="catch">man</mw>

<pb n="viii"/>
<milestone n="A2v" unit="sig"/>
	<lb/>man is the Man, and the Head of <persName ref="p:jchrist.hjn" rend="slant(upright)">Chriſt</persName> 
            is <hi rend="case(allcaps)">God</hi></quote>;
	<lb/>It being evident from the Form of Baptiſm, that
	<lb/>there is no natural Inferiority among the Divine
	<lb/>Perſons, but that they are in all things Coequal. The
	<lb/>Apoſtle indeed adds, that <mcr rend="slant(upright)">the Man is the Glory of
	<lb/>God, and the Woman the Glory of the Man</mcr>, &amp;c.
	<lb/>But what does he infer from hence? he ſays not a word
	<lb/>of Inequality, or natural Inferiority, but concludes, that
	<lb/>a Woman ought to Cover her head, and a Man
	<lb/>ought not to cover his, and <mcr rend="slant(upright)">that even Nature it ſelf,
	<lb/>teaches</mcr> us, that <mcr rend="slant(upright)">if a Man have long hair it is a
	<lb/>ſhame unto him</mcr>. Whatever the Apoſtle's Argument
	<lb/>proves in this place, nothing can be plainer, than
	<lb/>that there is much more ſaid againſt the preſent
	<lb/>Faſhion of Men's wearing long Hair, than for that
	<lb/>Supremacy they lay claim to. For by all that ap­
	<lb/>pears in the Text, it is not ſo much a Law of Nature,
	<lb/>that Women ſhou'd Obey Men, as that Men ſhou'd
	<lb/>not wear long Hair. Now how can a Chriſtian Na­
	<lb/>tion allow Faſhions contrary to the Law of Nature,
	<lb/>forbidden by an Apoſtle, and declared by him to be a
	<lb/>ſhame to <ref xml:id="er3" type="error" target="#ec3">Man</ref>? Or if Cuſtom may make an alteration
	<lb/>in one Caſe it may in another, but what then becomes
	<lb/>of the Nature and Reaſon of things? Beſides, the
	<lb/>Concluſion the Apoſtle draws from his Argument con­
	<lb/>cerning Women, <mcr rend="slant(upright)">viz</mcr>. that they <mcr rend="slant(upright)">ſhou'd have power on
	<lb/>their heads becauſe of the Angels</mcr>, is ſo very obſcure
	<lb/>a Text, That the Ingenious Paraphraſt who pleads ſo
	<lb/>much for the <mcr rend="slant(upright)">Natural Subjection</mcr> of Women, Ingenu­
	<lb/>ouſly confeſſes, that he does not underſtand it. Proba­
	  <lb/>bly it refers to ſome Cuſtom among the <name rend="slant(upright)">Corinthians</name>,
	<lb/>which being well known to them the Apoſtle only hints at
	<lb/>it, but which we are ignorant of, and therefore apt to
	<lb/>miſtake him. 'Tis like that the Falſe Apoſtle whom
	<lb/><persName ref="p:paul.pbe">St. <hi rend="slant(upright)">Paul</hi></persName> writes againſt, had 
  <mcr rend="slant(upright)">led Captive</mcr> ſome of their
	  <mw rend="slant(italic)" type="catch">Rich</mw>

<pb n="ix"/>
<milestone n="A3r" unit="sig"/>
	<lb/>Rich and Powerful but <mcr rend="slant(upright)">ſilly Women</mcr>, who having as
	<lb/>mean an Opinion of the Reaſon <mcr rend="case(allcaps)">God</mcr> had given them, as
	<lb/>any Deceiver cou'd deſire, did not, like the noble minded
	<lb/><mcr rend="slant(upright)"><name rend="slant(upright)">Bereans</name>, ſearch the Scriptures whether thoſe things
	<lb/>were ſo</mcr>, but lazily took up with having Men's Per­
	<lb/>ſons in admiration, and follow'd their Leaders Blind­
	<lb/>fold, the certain Rout to Deſtruction. And it is alſo
	<lb/>probable, that the ſame cunning Seducer imploy'd theſe
	<lb/>Women to carry on his own Deſigns, and putting them
	<lb/>upon what he might not think fit to appear in himſelf,
	<lb/>made them guilty of Indecent Behaviour in the Church
	<lb/>of <placeName rend="slant(upright)">Corinth</placeName>. And therefore 
	    <persName ref="p:paul.pbe">St. <hi rend="slant(upright)">Paul</hi></persName> thought it neceſ­
	<lb/>ſary to reprove them ſo ſeverly in order to humble
	<lb/>them, but this being done, he takes care in the Con­
	<lb/>cluſion to ſet the matter on a right Foot, placing the
	<lb/>two Sexes on a Level, to Keep Men as much as might
	<lb/>be, from taking thoſe advantages which People who
	<lb/>have ſtrength in their hands, are apt to aſſume over
	<lb/>thoſe who can't contend with them. For, ſays he, <mcr rend="slant(upright)">Ne­
	<lb/>vertheleſs</mcr>, or notwithſtanding the former Argument,
	<lb/><mcr rend="slant(upright)">the Man is not without the Woman, nor the Wo­
	    <lb/>man without the Man, but all things of <hi rend="slant(upright)case(allcaps)">God</hi></mcr>.
	<lb/>The Relation between the two Sexes is mutual, and the
	<lb/>Dependance Reciprocal, both of them Depending intirely
	<lb/>upon <mcr rend="case(allcaps)">God</mcr>, and upon Him only; which one wou'd
	<lb/>think is no great Argument of the natural Inferiority
	<lb/>of either Sex.</p>
        <p>Our <mcr rend="slant(upright)">Reflector</mcr> is of Opinion that Diſputes of this
	<lb/>kind, extending to Human Nature in general, and not
	<lb/>peculiar to thoſe to whom the Word of <mcr rend="case(allcaps)">God</mcr> has been
	<lb/>reveal'd, ought to be decided by natural Reaſon only.
	<lb/>And that the Holy Scriptures ſhou'd not be Intereſſed
	<lb/>in the preſent Controverſy, in which it determines no­
	<lb/>thing, any more than it does between the <mcr rend="slant(upright)">Copernican</mcr>
	<lb/>and <mcr rend="slant(upright)">Ptolomean</mcr> Syſtems. The Deſign of thoſe Holy
	  <mw type="catch">Books</mw>

<pb n="x"/>
<milestone n="A3v" unit="sig"/>
	<lb/>Books being to make us excellent Moraliſts and Perfect
	<lb/><name rend="slant(upright)">Chriſtians</name>, not great Philoſophers. And being writ for
	<lb/>the Vulgar as well as for the Learned, they are ac­
	<lb/>commodated to the common way of Speech and the
	<lb/>Uſage of the World; in which we have but a ſhort
	<lb/>Probation, ſo that it matters not much what part we
	<lb/>Act, whether of Governing or Obeying, provided we
	<lb/>perform it well with reſpect to the World to come.</p>
        <p>One does not wonder indeed, that when an Adverſary
	<lb/>is drove to a Nonplus and Reaſon declares againſt him,
	<lb/>he flies to Authority, eſpecially to Divine, which is infal­
	<lb/>lible, and therefore ought not to be diſputed. But Scripture
	<lb/>is not always on their ſide who make parade of it, and
	<lb/>thro' their skill in Languages and the Tricks of the
	<lb/>Schools, wreſt it from its genuine ſenſe to their own
	<lb/>Inventions. And ſuppoſing, not granting, that it were
	<lb/>apparently to the <ref xml:id="er4" type="error" target="#ec4">Woman's</ref> Diſadvantage, no fair and
	<lb/>generous Adverſary but wou'd be aſham'd  to urge this
	<lb/>advantage. Becauſe Women without their own Fault,
	<lb/>are kept in Ignorance of the Original, wanting Lan­
	<lb/>guages and other helps to Criticiſe on the Sacred Text,
	<lb/>of which they know no more, than Men are pleas'd to
	<lb/>impart in their Tranſlations. In ſhort, they ſhew their
	<lb/>deſire to maintain their Hypotheſes, but by no means
	<lb/>their Reverence to the Sacred Oracles who engage them in
	<lb/>ſuch Diſputes. And therefore the blame be theirs, who
	<lb/>have unneceſſarily introduc'd them in the preſent Subject,
	<lb/>and who by ſaying that the <mcr rend="slant(upright)">Reflections</mcr> were not agreea­
	<lb/>ble to Scripture, oblige the Reflector to ſhew that thoſe
	<lb/>who affirm it muſt either miſtake her Meaning, or the
	<lb/>Senſe of Holy Scripture, or both, if they think what
	<lb/>they ſay, and do not find fault merely becauſe they re­
	<lb/>ſolve to do ſo. For had ſhe ever writ any thing con­
	<lb/>trary to thoſe ſacred Truths, ſhe wou'd be the firſt in
	<lb/>pronouncing its Condemnation.</p>
        <pb n="xi"/>
        <milestone n="A4r" unit="sig"/>
        <p>But what ſays the Holy Scripture? It ſpeaks of
	<lb/>Women as in a State of Subjection, and ſo it does of
	<lb/>the <name rend="slant(upright)">Jews</name> and <name rend="slant(upright)">Chriſtians</name> when under the Dominion of
	<lb/>the <name rend="slant(upright)">Chaldeans</name> and <name rend="slant(upright)">Romans</name>, requiring of the one as
	<lb/>well as of the other a quiet ſubmiſſion to them under
	<lb/>whoſe Power they liv'd. But will any one ſay that theſe
	<lb/>had a <mcr rend="slant(upright)">Natural Superiority</mcr> and Right to Dominion?
	<lb/>that they had a ſuperior Underſtanding, or any Pre­
	<lb/>eminence, except what their greater Strength acquir'd?
	<lb/>Or that the other were ſubjected to their Adverſaries
	<lb/>for any other Reaſon but the Puniſhment of their ſins,
	<lb/>and in order to their Reformation? Or for the Exer­
	<lb/>ciſe of their Vertue, and becauſe the Order of the
	<lb/>World and the Good of Society requir'd it?</p>
        <p>If Mankind had never ſinn'd, Reaſon wou'd always
	<lb/>have been obey'd, there wou'd have been no ſtruggle
	<lb/>for Dominion, and Brutal Power wou'd not have pre­
	<lb/>vail'd. But in the laps'd State of Mankind, and now
	<lb/>that Men will not be guided by their Reaſon but by
	<lb/>their Appetites, and do not what they <mcr rend="slant(upright)">ought</mcr> but what
	<lb/>they <mcr rend="slant(upright)">can</mcr>, the Reaſon, or that which ſtands for it, the
	<lb/>Will and Pleaſure of the Governor is to be the Rea­
	<lb/>ſon of thoſe who will not be guided by their own, and
	<lb/>muſt take place for Order's ſake, altho' it ſhou'd not be
	<lb/>conformable to right Reaſon. Nor can there be any
	<lb/>Society great or little, from Empires down to private
	<lb/>Families, without a laſt Reſort, to determine the Af­
	<lb/>fairs of that Society by an irreſiſtible Sentence. Now
	<lb/>unleſs this Supremacy be fix'd ſomewhere, there will be
	<lb/>a perpetual Contention about it, ſuch is the love of
	<lb/>Dominion, and let the Reaſon of things be what it may,
	<lb/>thoſe who have leaſt Force, or Cunning to ſupply it,
	<lb/>will have the Diſadvantage. So that ſince Women are 
	<lb/>acknowledg'd to have leaſt Bodily ſtrength, their being
	<lb/>commanded to obey is in pure kindneſs to them, and
	  <mw type="catch">for</mw>

<pb n="xii"/>
<milestone n="A4v" unit="sig"/>
	<lb/>for their Quiet and Security, as well as for the Exer­
	<lb/>ciſe of their Vertue. But does it follow that Domeſtic
	<lb/>Governors have more Senſe than their Subjects, any
	<lb/>more than that other Governors have? We do not
	<lb/>find that any Man thinks the worſe of his own Under­
	<lb/>ſtanding becauſe another has ſuperior Power; or con­
	<lb/>cludes himſelf leſs capable of a Poſt of Honour and
	<lb/>Authority, becauſe he is not Prefer'd to it. How much
	<lb/>time wou'd lie on Men's hands, how empty wou'd the
	<lb/>Places of Concourſe be, and how ſilent moſt Companies,
	<lb/>did Men forbear to Cenſure their Governors, that is
	<lb/>in effect to think themſelves Wiſer. Indeed Govern­
	<lb/>ment wou'd be much more deſirable than it is, did it
	<lb/>inveſt the Poſſeſſor with a ſuperior Underſtanding as
	<lb/>well as Power. And if mere Power gives a Right to
	<lb/>Rule, there can be no ſuch thing as Uſurpation; but a
	<lb/>Highway-Man ſo long as he has ſtrength to force, has
	<lb/>alſo a Right to require our Obedience.</p>
        <p>Again, if Abſolute Sovereignty be not neceſſary in a
	<lb/>State, how comes it to be ſo in a Family? or if in a
	<lb/>Family why not in a State; ſince no Reaſon can be al­
	<lb/>ledg'd for the one that will not hold more ſtrongly for 
	<lb/>the other? If the Authority of the Husband ſo far as
	<lb/>it extends, is ſacred and inalienable, why not of the
	<lb/>Prince? The Domeſtic Sovereign is without Diſpute
	<lb/>Elected, and the Stipulations and Contract are mutual,
	<lb/>is it not then partial in Men to the laſt degree, to
	<lb/>contend for, and practiſe that Arbitrary Dominion in
	<lb/>their Families, which they abhor and exclaim againſt
	<lb/>in the State? For if Arbitrary Power is evil in it ſelf,
	<lb/>and an improper Method of Governing Rational and
	<lb/>Free Agents, it ought not to be Practis'd any where;
	<lb/>Nor is it leſs, but rather more miſchievous in Fami­
	<lb/>lies than in Kingdoms, by how much 100000 Tyrants
	<lb/>are worſe than one. What tho' a Husband can't de­
	  <mw type="catch">prive</mw>

<pb n="xiii"/>
<milestone n="a1r" unit="sig"/>
	<lb/>prive a Wife of Life without being reſponsible to the
	<lb/>Law, he may however do what is much more grievous
	<lb/>to a generous Mind, render Life miſerable, for which
	<lb/>ſhe has no Redreſs, ſcarce Pity which is afforded to
	<lb/>every other Complainant. It being thought a Wife's
	<lb/>Duty to ſuffer every thing without Complaint. If all
	<lb/><mcr rend="slant(upright)">Men are born free</mcr>, how is it that all Women are
	<lb/>born Slaves? as they muſt be if the being ſubjected to
	<lb/>the <mcr rend="slant(upright)">inconſtant, uncertain, unknown, arbitrary Will</mcr>
	<lb/>of Men, be the <mcr rend="slant(upright)">perfect Condition of Slavery?</mcr> and
	<lb/>if the Eſſence of Freedom conſiſts, as our Maſters
	<lb/>ſay it does, in having a ſtanding <mcr rend="slant(upright)">Rule to live by?</mcr>
	<lb/>And why is Slavery ſo much condemn'd and ſtrove a­
	<lb/>gainſt in one Caſe, and ſo highly applauded, and held
	<lb/>ſo neceſſary and ſo ſacred in another?</p>
        <p>'Tis true that <mcr rend="slant(upright)case(allcaps)">God</mcr> told 
	    <persName ref="p:eve.znk" rend="slant(upright)">Eve</persName> after the Fall that
	<lb/><mcr rend="slant(upright)">her Husband ſhou'd Rule over her:</mcr> And ſo it is
	<lb/>that he told <persName ref="p:esau.sfb" rend="slant(upright)">Eſau</persName> by the mouth
	    of <persName ref="p:isaack.yeq" rend="slant(upright)">Iſaac</persName> his Father,
	<lb/>that he ſhou'd <mcr rend="slant(upright)">ſerve</mcr> his 
            <mcr rend="slant(upright)">younger Brother</mcr>, and ſhou'd
	<lb/>in time, and when he was ſtrong enough to do it, <mcr rend="slant(upright)">break
	<lb/>the Yoke from off his Neck</mcr>. Now why one Text
	<lb/>ſhou'd be a Command any more than the other, and not
	<lb/>both of them be Predictions only; or why the former
	<lb/>ſhou'd prove <persName ref="p:adam.vdi" rend="slant(upright)">Adam's</persName> 
            natural Right to Rule, and
	<lb/>much leſs every Man's, any more than the latter is a
	<lb/>Proof of <persName ref="p:jacob.yew" rend="slant(upright)">Jacob's</persName> Right to Rule, and
	    of <persName ref="p:esau.sfb" rend="slant(upright)">Eſau's</persName> to Rebel,
	<lb/>one is yet to learn? The Text in both Caſes foretel­
	<lb/>ling what wou'd be; <ref xml:id="er5" type="error" target="#ec5">but</ref> neither of them determining
	<lb/>what ought to be.</p>
        <p>But the Scripture commands <mcr rend="slant(upright)">Wives</mcr> to <mcr rend="slant(upright)">ſubmit
	<lb/>themſelves to their own Husbands</mcr>. True; for which
	<lb/><persName ref="p:paul.pbe">St. <hi rend="slant(upright)">Paul</hi></persName> gives a Myſtical Reaſon 
        	<bibl source="b:IT50032"><regMe>(Eph 5.22, &amp;c)</regMe></bibl>
	  <lb/>and <persName ref="p:peter.nex">St. <hi rend="slant(upright)">Peter</hi></persName> a Prudential and Charitable one 
            <bibl source="b:IT50006"><regMe>(1 St. 
	<lb/>Pet. 3.)</regMe></bibl> but neither of them derive that Subjection
	<lb/>from the Law of Nature. Nay <persName ref="p:paul.pbe">St. <hi rend="slant(upright)">Paul</hi></persName>, as if he fore­
	  <mw rend="align(center)" type="sig">a</mw>
	  <mw rend="break(no)" type="catch">ſaw</mw>

<pb n="xiv"/>
<milestone n="a1v" unit="sig"/>
	<lb/>ſaw and meant to prevent this Plea, giving directions
        <lb/>for their Conduct to Women in general, <bibl source="b:IT50009"><regMe><hi rend="slant(upright)">1 Tim. 2,</hi></regMe></bibl> 
	<lb/>when he comes to ſpeak of <mcr rend="slant(upright)">Subjection</mcr>, he changes his
	<lb/>Phraſe from <mcr rend="slant(upright)">Women</mcr> which denotes the whole Sex, to
	<lb/><mcr rend="slant(upright)">Woman</mcr> which in the <rs type="title" ref="b:IT55558">New Teſtament</rs> is appropriated
	<lb/>to a Wife.</p>
        <p>As for his not ſuffering Women to ſpeak in the
	<lb/>Church, no ſober Perſon that I know of pretends to it.
	<lb/>That Learned Paraphraſt indeed, who lays ſo much
	  <lb/>ſtreſs on the <mcr rend="slant(upright)">Natural Subjection</mcr>, provided this Pre­
	<lb/>rogative be ſecur'd, is willing to give up the other.
	<lb/>For he endeavours to prove that Inſpir'd Women as well
	<lb/>as Men us'd to ſpeak in the Church, and that 
            <persName ref="p:paul.pbe">St. <hi rend="slant(upright)">Paul</hi></persName>
	<lb/>does not forbid it, but only takes care that the Women
	<lb/>ſhou'd ſignifie their Subjection by wearing a Veil. But
	<lb/>the Apoſtle is his own beſt Expoſitor, let us therefore
	<lb/>compare his Precepts with his Practice, for he was all
	<lb/>of a piece, and did not contradict himſelf. Now by
	<lb/>this Compariſon we find, that tho' he forbids Women to
	<lb/>teach in the Church, and this for ſeveral Prudential
	<lb/>Reaſons, like thoſe he introduces with an <mcr rend="slant(upright)">I give my
	<lb/>Opinion, and now ſpeak I not the Lord</mcr>, and not
	<lb/>becauſe of any Law of Nature, or Poſitive Divine Pre­
	<lb/>cept, for that the words <mcr rend="slant(upright)">they are Commanded</mcr>
        	<lb/><bibl rend="slant(upright)" source="b:IT50001"><regMe>(1 Cor. 14. 24.)</regMe></bibl> 
	    are not in the Original, appears
	<lb/>from the <mcr rend="slant(upright)">Italic</mcr> Character, yet he did not found this
	<lb/>Prohibition on any ſuppos'd want of Underſtanding in
	<lb/>Woman, or of ability to Teach; neither does he con­
	<lb/>fine them at all times to <mcr rend="slant(upright)">learn in ſilence</mcr>. For the
	<lb/>Eloquent <persName ref="p:apollos.brv" rend="slant(upright)">Apollos</persName> who was himſelf a Teacher, 
            was in­
	<lb/>ſtructed by <persName ref="p:priscilla.cvv" rend="slant(upright)">Priſcilla</persName> as well
	    as by her Husband <persName ref="p:aquila.ukn" rend="slant(upright)">Aquila</persName>,
	<lb/>and was improv'd by them both in the Chriſtian Faith.
	<lb/>Nor does <persName ref="p:paul.pbe">St. <hi rend="slant(upright)">Paul</hi></persName> 
            blame her for this, or ſuppoſe that
	<lb/>ſhe <mcr rend="slant(upright)">Uſurp'd Authority over</mcr> that great
	    <mcr rend="slant(upright)">Man</mcr>, ſo far
	<lb/>from this, that as ſhe is always honourably mention'd
	  <mw type="catch">in</mw>

<pb n="xv"/>
<milestone n="a2r" unit="sig"/>
	<lb/>in Holy Scripture, ſo our Apoſtle in his Salutations,
	<lb/><bibl rend="slant(upright)" source="b:IT50074"><regMe>Rom 16.</regMe></bibl> places her in the Front, even before her
	<lb/>Husband, giving to her as well as to him, the Noble
	<lb/>Title of <mcr rend="slant(upright)">his Helper in 
            <persName ref="p:jchrist.hjn" rend="slant(upright)">Chriſt Jeſus</persName></mcr>, and of one
	    <mcr rend="slant(upright)">to
	    <lb/>whom all the Churches of the <name rend="slant(upright)">Gentiles</name></mcr> had great
	<lb/>Obligations.</p>
        <p>But it will be ſaid perhaps, that in <bibl source="b:IT50009"><regMe>1 Tim. 2. 13,</regMe></bibl>
	<lb/>&amp;c. <persName ref="p:paul.pbe">St. <hi rend="slant(upright)">Paul</hi></persName> argues for the Woman's 
            ſubjection from
	<lb/>the Reaſon of things. To this I anſwer, that it muſt be
	<lb/>confeſs'd that this (according to the vulgar Interpretati­
	<lb/>on) is a very obſcure place, and I ſhou'd be glad to ſee a
	<lb/>Natural, and not a Forc'd Interpretation given of it by
	<lb/>thoſe who take it Literally. Whereas if it be taken Al­
	<lb/>legorically, with reſpect to the Myſtical Union between
	<lb/>Chriſt and his Church, to which <persName ref="p:paul.pbe">St. <hi rend="slant(upright)">Paul</hi></persName> 
            frequently ac­
	<lb/>commodates the Matrimonial Relation, the difficulties
	<lb/>vaniſh. For the Earthly <persName ref="p:adam.vdi" rend="slant(upright)">Adam's</persName>
	    being <mcr rend="slant(upright)">Form'd</mcr> before
	<lb/><persName ref="p:eve.znk" rend="slant(upright)">Eve</persName>, ſeems as little to prove her 
            Natural Subjection to
	<lb/>him, as the Living Creatures, Fiſhes, Birds and Beaſts
	<lb/>being Form'd before them both, proves that Mankind
	<lb/>muſt be ſubject to theſe Animals. Nor can the Apo­
	<lb/>ſtle mean that <persName ref="p:eve.znk" rend="slant(upright)">Eve</persName> only ſinned; 
            or that ſhe only was
	<lb/><mcr rend="slant(upright)">Deceiv'd</mcr>, for if <persName ref="p:adam.vdi" rend="slant(upright)">Adam</persName> ſinn'd wilfully and knowingly,
	<lb/>he became the greater Tranſgreſſor. But it is very
	<lb/>true that the <persName ref="p:jchrist.hjn">Second <hi rend="slant(upright)">Adam</hi></persName>, the Man 
            <persName ref="p:jchrist.hjn">Chriſt Jeſus</persName>,
	<lb/><mcr rend="slant(upright)">was firſt form'd</mcr>, and then his Spouſe the Church. He
	<lb/>was not in any reſpect <mcr rend="slant(upright)">Deceiv'd</mcr>, nor does ſhe pretend
	<lb/>to Infallibility. And from this <persName ref="p:jchrist.hjn">ſecond <hi rend="slant(upright)">Adam</hi></persName>, pro­
	<lb/>mis'd to <persName ref="p:eve.znk" rend="slant(upright)">Eve</persName> in the Day of our 
            firſt Parent's Tranſ­
	<lb/>greſſion, and from Him only, do all their Race, Men as well
	<lb/>as Women, derive their Hopes of Salvation. Nor is it
	<lb/>promis'd to either Sex on any other Terms beſides Per­
	<lb/>ſeverance in <mcr rend="slant(upright)">Faith, Charity, Holineſs and Sobriety</mcr>.</p>
        <p>If the Learned will not admit of this Interpreta­
	<lb/>tion, I know not how to contend with them. For Senſe
	  <mw rend="align(center)" type="sig">a2</mw>
	  <mw rend="break(no)" type="catch">is</mw>

<pb n="xvi"/>
<milestone n="a2v" unit="sig"/>
	<lb/>is a Portion that <mcr rend="slant(upright)">God</mcr> Himſelf has been pleas'd to di­
	<lb/>ſtribute to both Sexes with an Impartial Hand, but
	<lb/>Learning is what Men have engroſs'd to themſevles,
	<lb/>and one can't but admire their great Improvements!
	<lb/>For after doubting whether there was ſuch a thing as
	<lb/>Truth, and after many hundred years Diſputes about
	<lb/>it, in the laſt Century an extraordinary Genius aroſe,
	<lb/>(whom yet ſome are pleas'd to call a Viſionary) en­
	<lb/>quir'd after it, and laid down the beſt Method of
	<lb/>finding it. Not to the general liking of the Men of
	<lb/>Letters, perhaps, becauſe it was wrote in a vulgar
	<lb/>Language, and was ſo natural and eaſy as to debaſe
	<lb/>Truth to Common Underſtandings, ſhewing to plainly
	<lb/>that Learning and true Knowledge are two very dif­
        	<lb/>ferent things. <said rend="bestow((pre(“))(lb))"><quote source="b:IT07945" rend="pre(“)">For it often happens (ſays that Author)
 	<lb/>that Women and Children acknowledge the Falſhood of
 	<lb/>thoſe Prejudices we contend with, becauſe they do not
 	<lb/>dare to judge without examination, and they bring all the
 	<lb/>attention they are capable of to what they reade. Whereas
 	<lb/>on the contrary, the Learned continue wedded to their own 
 	<lb/>Opinions, becauſe they will not take the trouble of exa­
 	<lb/>mining what is contrary to their receiv'd Doctrines.</quote></said></p>
        <p>Sciences indeed have been invented and taught
	<lb/>long ago, and, as Men grew better advis'd, new
	<lb/>Modell'd. So that it is become a conſiderable piece of
	<lb/>Learning to give an account of the Riſe and Progreſs of
	<lb/>the Sciences, and of the various Opinions of Men 
	<lb/>concerning them. But Certainty and Demonſration
	<lb/>are much pretended to in this preſent Age, and being
	<lb/>obtain'd in many things, 'tis hop'd Men will never
	<lb/>Diſpute them away in that which is of greateſt Impor­
	<lb/>tance, the Way of Salvation. And becauſe there is not
	<lb/>any thing more certain than what is delivered in the
	<lb/>oracles of <mcr rend="slant(upright)case(allcaps)">God</mcr>, 
            we come now to conſider what they
	<lb/>offer in favour of our Sex.</p>
        <mw type="catch">Let</mw>
        <pb n="xvii"/>
        <milestone n="a3r" unit="sig"/>
        <p>Let it be premis'd, (according to the Reaſoning of a
	<lb/>very Ingenious Perſon in a like Caſe) that One Text
	<lb/>for us, is more to be regarded than many againſt us.
	<lb/>Becauſe that <mcr rend="slant(upright)">One</mcr> being different from what Cuſtom has
	<lb/>eſtabliſh'd, ought to be taken with Philoſophical Strict­
	<lb/>neſs; whereas the <mcr rend="slant(upright)">Many</mcr> being expreſſ'd
            according to
	<lb/>the vulgar Mode Of Speech, ought to have no greater ſtreſs
	<lb/>laid on them, than that evident Condeſcenſion will
	<lb/>bear. One place then were ſufficient, but we have
	<lb/>many Inſtances wherein Holy Scripture conſiders Wo­
	<lb/>men very differently from what they appear in the com­
	<lb/>mon Prejudices of Mankind.</p>
        <p>The World will hardly allow a Woman to ſay any
	<lb/>thing well, unleſs as ſhe borrows it from Men, or is aſ­
	<lb/>ſiſted by them: But <mcr rend="slant(upright)case(allcaps)">God</mcr> 
            Himſelf allows that the
	<lb/>Daughters of <mcr rend="slant(upright)"><persName ref="p:zelopheha.qfi" rend="slant(upright)">Zelophehad</persName> 
            ſpake right</mcr>, and paſſes
	<lb/>their Requeſt into a Law. Conſidering how much the
	<lb/>Tyranny ſhall I ſay, or the ſuperior Force of Men,
	<lb/>keeps Women from Acting in the World, or doing any
	<lb/>thing conſiderable, and remembring withal the conciſe­
	<lb/>neſs of the Sacred Story, no ſmall part of it is beſtow'd in
	<lb/>tranſmitting the Hiſtory of Women famous in their 
	<lb/>Generations: Two of the Canonical Books bearing the
	<lb/>Names of thoſe great Women whoſe Vertues and Actions
	<lb/>are there recorded. <persName ref="p:ruth.qkj" rend="slant(upright)">Ruth</persName> being call'd from
	    among the
	<lb/><name rend="slant(upright)">Gentiles</name> to be an Anceſtor of the
	     Meſſiah, and <persName ref="p:esther.qba" rend="slant(upright)">Eſther</persName>
	<lb/>being rais'd up by <mcr rend="slant(upright)case(allcaps)">God</mcr> to be the great Inſtrument
	<lb/>of the Deliverance and Proſperity of the Jewiſh 
            Church.</p>
        <p>The Character of <persName ref="p:isaack.yeq" rend="slant(upright)">Iſaac</persName>, 
           tho' one of the moſt blameleſs
	<lb/>Men taken notice of in the <rs type="title" ref="b:IT55557">Old Teſtament</rs>, muſt give
	<lb/>place to <persName ref="p:rebecca.rew" rend="slant(upright)">Rebecca's</persName>, whoſe
	    Affections are more Reaſo­
	<lb/>nably plac'd then his, her Favourite Son being the
	<lb/>ſame who was <mcr rend="slant(upright)"><hi rend="case(allcaps)">God</hi>'s</mcr> 
            Favourite. Nor was the Bleſſing
	<lb/>beſtow'd according to his but to her Deſire; ſo that if
	    <mw type="catch">you</mw>

<pb n="xviii"/>
<milestone n="a3v" unit="sig"/>
	<lb/>you will not allow, that her Command to <persName ref="p:jacob.yew" rend="slant(upright)">Jacob</persName> 
            ſu­
	<lb/>perſeded <persName ref="p:isaack.yeq" rend="slant(upright)">Iſaac's</persName> to 
            <persName ref="p:esau.sfb" rend="slant(upright)">Eſau</persName>, his deſire to give the Bleſ­
	<lb/>ſing to this Son, being evidently an effect of his Par­
	<lb/>tiality: You muſt at leaſt grant that ſhe paid greater
	<lb/>deference to the Divine Revelation, and for this Rea­
	<lb/>ſon at leaſt, had a Right to oppoſe her Husband's De­
	<lb/>ſign; which it ſeems <persName ref="p:isaack.yeq" rend="slant(upright)">Iſaac</persName> 
            was ſenſible of, when upon
	<lb/>his Diſappointment he <mcr rend="slant(upright)">trembled ſo exceedingly</mcr>. And
	<lb/>ſo much notice is taken even of <persName ref="p:rebecca.rew" rend="slant(upright)">Rebecca's</persName> 
            Nurſe, that
	<lb/>we have an account where ſhe Died and where ſhe was
	<lb/>Buried.</p>
        <p><mcr rend="slant(upright)case(allcaps)">God</mcr> is pleas'd to record it among 	  
            His Favours to
	<lb/>the Ingrateful <name rend="slant(upright)">Jews</name>, that He ſent before them His
	<lb/>Servants <persName ref="p:moses.znq" rend="slant(upright)">Moſes</persName>, <persName ref="p:aaron.neo" rend="slant(upright)">Aaron</persName>, and 
            <persName ref="p:miriam.inh" rend="slant(upright)case(allcaps)">Miriam</persName>; who was
	<lb/>alſo a Propheteſs, and Inſtructed the Women how to bear
	<lb/>their part with <persName ref="p:moses.znq" rend="slant(upright)">Moſes</persName> in his Triumphal Hymn. Is
	<lb/>ſhe to be blam'd for her Ambition? and is not the
	<lb/>High Prieſt <persName ref="p:aaron.neo" rend="slant(upright)">Aaron</persName> 
            alſo? who has his ſhare in the
	<lb/>Reproof as well as in the Crime; nor cou'd ſhe have
	<lb/>mov'd Sedition if ſhe had not been a conſiderable Per­
	<lb/>ſon, which appears alſo by the Reſpect the People paid
	<lb/>her, in deferring their Journey till ſhe was ready.</p>
        <p>Where ſhall we find a nobler piece of Poetry than
	<lb/><persName ref="p:deborah.ina" rend="slant(upright)">Deborah's</persName> Song? or a better and greater Ruler than
	<lb/>that Renowned Woman whoſe Government ſo much ex­
	<lb/>cell'd that of the former Judges? And tho' ſhe had a
	<lb/>Husband, ſhe her ſelf Judg'd <persName rend="slant(upright)" ref="p:jacob.yew">Iſrael</persName> and conſequently
	<lb/>was his Sovereign, of whom we know no more than the
	<lb/>Name. Which Inſtance, as I humbly ſuppoſe, over­
	<lb/>throws the pretence of <mcr rend="slant(upright)">Natural Inferiority</mcr>. For it is
	<lb/>not the bare Relation of a Fact, by which none ought to
	<lb/>be concluded, unleſs it is conformable to a Rule, and
	<lb/>to the Reaſon of things: But <persName ref="p:deborah.ina" rend="slant(upright)">Deborah's</persName> Government
	<lb/>was confer'd on her by <mcr rend="slant(upright)case(allcaps)">God</mcr> 
            Himſelf. Conſequently
	<lb/>the Sovereignty of a Woman is not contrary to the
	  <mw type="catch">Law</mw>

<pb n="xix"/>
<milestone n="a4r" unit="sig"/>
	<lb/>Law of Nature; for the law of Nature is the Law of
	<lb/><mcr rend="slant(upright)case(allcaps)">God</mcr>, who cannot contradict
	    Himſelf; and yet it was
	<lb/><mcr rend="slant(upright)case(allcaps)">God</mcr> who Inſpir'd and Approv'd 
            that great Woman,
	<lb/>raiſing her up to Judge and to Deliver His People <placeName rend="slant(upright)">Iſ­
	<lb/>rael</placeName>.</p>
        <p>Not to inſiſt on the Courage of that valiant Woman
	<lb/>who deliver'd <placeName rend="slant(upright)">Thebez</placeName> 
            by ſlaying the Aſſailant; nor upon
	<lb/>the preference which <mcr rend="slant(upright)case(allcaps)">God</mcr> thought fit to
	    give to <persName ref="p:samson.nkr" rend="slant(upright)">Samp­
	<lb/>ſon's</persName> Mother, in ſending the Angel to her, and not to
	<lb/>her Husband, whoſe vulgar Fear ſhe ſo prudently an­
	<lb/>ſwer'd, as plainly ſhews her ſuperior Underſtanding:
	<lb/>To paſs over <persName ref="p:abigail.neu" rend="slant(upright)">Abigail's</persName> wiſe
	    Conduct, whereby ſhe pre­
	<lb/>ſerv'd her Family and deſerv'd <persName ref="p:david.yei" rend="slant(upright)">David's</persName> 
            acknowledg­
	<lb/>ments, for reſtraining him from doing a Raſh and un­
	<lb/>juſtifiable Action; the Holy Penman giving her the
	<lb/>Character of a <mcr rend="slant(upright)">Woman of good Underſtanding,</mcr>
	<lb/>whilſt her Husband has that of a Churliſh and Fooliſh
	<lb/>Perſon, and a Son of <persName ref="p:belial.vfr" rend="slant(upright)">Belial</persName>: To ſay
	  nothing of the
	<lb/>wiſe <mcr rend="slant(upright)">Woman</mcr> (as the Text calls her) of
            <placeName rend="slant(upright)">Tekoah</placeName>;
	<lb/>or of her of <persName ref="p:abel.nep" rend="slant(upright)">Abel</persName> who has the
	    ſame Epithet, and who
	<lb/>by her Prudence deliver'd the City and appeas'd a
	<lb/>dangerous Rebellion: Nor of the Queen of 
            <ref xml:id="er6" type="error" target="#ec6"><persName ref="p:qsheba.hyf" rend="slant(upright)">Sheba's</persName></ref>,
	<lb/>whoſe Journey to hear the Wiſdom of <persName ref="p:solomon.yer" rend="slant(upright)">Solomon</persName>, 
            ſhews
	<lb/>her own good Judgment and great ſhare in that excel­
	<lb/>lent Endowment. <persName ref="p:solomon.yer" rend="slant(upright)">Solomon</persName> 
            does not think himſelf too
	<lb/>Wiſe to be Inſtructed by his Mother, nor too great
	<lb/>to Record her Leſſons, which if he had follow'd he
	<lb/>might have ſpar'd the trouble of Repentance, and been
	<lb/>deliver'd from a great deal of that Vanity he ſo deeply
	<lb/>Regrets.</p>
        <p>What Reaſon can be aſſign'd why the Mothers of the
	<lb/>Kings of <persName ref="p:judah.mdz" rend="slant(upright)">Judah</persName>, 
            are ſo frequently noted in thoſe very
	<lb/>ſhort accounts that are given of their Reigns, but the
	<lb/>great Reſpect paid them, or perhaps their Influence on
	<lb/>the Government, and ſhare in the Adminiſtration?
	  <mw type="catch">This</mw>

<pb n="xx"/>
<milestone n="a4v" unit="sig"/>
	<lb/>This is not improbable, ſince the wicked 
            <persName ref="p:athaliah.qzk" rend="slant(upright)">Athaliah</persName> had
	<lb/>power to carry on her Intrigues ſo far as to get poſſeſſion
	<lb/>of the Throne, and to keep it for ſome Years. Neither
	<lb/>was there any neceſſity for <persName ref="p:asa.lxx" rend="slant(upright)">Aſa's</persName> 
            removing his Mother
	<lb/>(or Grandmother) from being Queen, if this were
	<lb/>merely Titular, and did not carry Power and Autho­
	<lb/>rity along with it. And we find what Influence <persName ref="p:jezebel.kje" rend="slant(upright)">Jeza­
	<lb/>bel</persName> had in <placeName rend="slant(upright)">Iſrael</placeName>, 
            indeed to her Husband's and her
	<lb/>own Deſtruction.</p>
        <p>It was a <mcr rend="slant(upright)">Widow-Woman</mcr> whom <mcr rend="case(allcaps)">God</mcr> made choice
	<lb/>of to ſuſtain his Prophet <persName ref="p:eliah.cku" rend="slant(upright)">Elijah</persName> at 
	  <placeName rend="slant(upright)">Zarephah</placeName>. And
	<lb/>the Hiſtory of the <name rend="slant(upright)">Shunamite</name> is a 
            noble Inſtance of the
	<lb/>Account that is made of Women in Holy Scripture.
	<lb/>For whether it was not the Cuſtom in 
            <placeName rend="slant(upright)">Shunem</placeName> for the
	<lb/>Husband to Dictate, or whether her's was conſcious
	<lb/>of her ſuperior Vertue, or whatever was the Reaſon,
	<lb/>we find it is ſhe who Governs, dwelling with great
	<lb/>Honour and Satisfaction <mcr rend="slant(upright)">among her own People</mcr>.
	<lb/>Which Happineſs ſhe underſtood ſo well, and was ſo
	<lb/>far from a troubleſome Ambition, that ſhe deſires no
	<lb/>Recommendation to <mcr rend="slant(upright)">the King 
            or Captain of the Hoſt</mcr>
	<lb/>when the Prophet offer'd it, being already greater than
        	<lb/>they cou'd make her. The Text calls her a <quote source="b:IT50014" rend="slant(upright)">Great
	<lb/>Woman,</quote> whilſt her Husband is hardly taken notice of,
	<lb/>and this no otherwiſe than as performing the Office of a
	<lb/>Bailiff. It is <emph rend="slant(upright)">her</emph> Piety and Hoſpitality that are Re­
	<lb/>corded, <emph rend="slant(upright)">She</emph> invites the Prophet to 
            <emph rend="slant(upright)">her Houſe</emph>; who
	<lb/>Converſes with and is entertain'd by <emph rend="slant(upright)">her</emph>. She gives
	<lb/>her Husband no account of <emph rend="slant(upright)">her</emph> Affairs any further
	<lb/>than to tell him <emph rend="slant(upright)">her</emph> Deſigns that he may ſee them
	<lb/>Executed. And when he deſires to know the reaſon of
        	<lb/>her Conduct, all the Anſwer ſhe affords is, <quote source="b:IT50014" rend="slant(upright)">Well,</quote> or
        	<lb/>as the Margin has it from the <name rend="slant(upright)">Hebrew</name>, <quote source="b:IT50014" rend="slant(upright)">Peace</quote>. Nor
	<lb/>can this be thought aſſuming, ſince it is no more than
	<lb/>what the Prophet encourages, for all his Addreſſes are
	  <mw type="catch">to</mw>
	  
<pb n="xxi"/>
<milestone unit="sig" n="b1r"/>
	<lb/>to her, he takes no Notice of her Husband. His be­
	<lb/>nefits are confer'd on <emph rend="slant(upright)">her</emph>, 
	  'tis ſhe and <emph rend="slant(upright)">her Houſhold</emph>
	<lb/>whom he warns of a Famine, and 'tis <emph rend="slant(upright)">ſhe</emph> who appeals
	<lb/>to the King for the Reſtitution of <emph rend="slant(upright)">her Houſe</emph> and
	<lb/><mcr rend="slant(upright)">Land</mcr>. I wou'd not infer from hence that Women ge­
	<lb/>nerally ſpeaking, ought to govern in their Families
	<lb/>when they have a Husband, but I think this Inſtance
	<lb/>and Example is a ſufficient Proof, that if by Cuſtom or
	<lb/>Contract, or the Laws of the Country, or Birth-right
	<lb/>(as in the Caſe of Sovereign Princeſſes) they have the
	<lb/>ſupreme Authority, it is no Uſurpation, nor do they
	<lb/>Act contrary to Holy Scripture, nor conſequently to
	<lb/>the Law of Nature. For they are no where that I know
	<lb/>of forbidden to claim their Juſt Right: The Apoſtle
	<lb/>'tis true wou'd not have them <mcr rend="slant(upright)">uſurp</mcr> Authority where
	<lb/>Cuſtom and the Law of the ſtrongeſt had brought them
	<lb/>into Subjection, as it has in theſe parts of the World.
	<lb/>Tho' in remoter Regions, if Travellers rightly inform
	<lb/>us, the Succeſſion to the Crown is entail'd on the Fe­
	<lb/>male Line.</p>
        <p><mcr rend="case(allcaps)">God</mcr> Himſelf who is 
            <mcr rend="slant(upright)">no Reſpecter of Perſons,
	<lb/>with whom there is neither Bond nor Free, Male
	<lb/>nor Female, but <hi rend="slant(upright)">they</hi> are all one in 
            <persName ref="p:jchrist.hjn">Chriſt Jeſus</persName></mcr>,
	<lb/>did not deny Women that Divine Gift the Spirit of
	<lb/>Prophecy, neither under the Jewiſh nor Chriſtian Diſ­
	<lb/>penſation. We have nam'd two great Propheteſſes
	<lb/>already, <persName ref="p:miriam.inh" rend="slant(upright)">Miriam</persName> and 
            <persName ref="p:deborah.ina" rend="slant(upright)">Deborah</persName>, and beſides other In­
	<lb/>ſtances, <persName ref="p:huldah.tix" rend="slant(upright)">Huldah</persName> the Propheteſs was ſuch an Oracle that
	<lb/>the good <persName ref="p:josiah.xdn">King <hi rend="slant(upright)">Joſiah</hi></persName>, that great Pattern of Vertue,
	<lb/>ſends even the Hight Prieſt himſelf to conſult her, and
	<lb/>to receive directions from her in the moſt arduous Af­
        	<lb/>fairs. <quote source="b:IT50047" rend="slant(upright)">It ſhall come to paſs,</quote> ſaith the Lord,
        	<quote source="b:IT50047" rend="slant(upright)">that I
	<lb/>will pour out my Spirit upon all Fleſh, and your
	<lb/>Sons and your Daughters ſhall Propheſy,</quote> which
	<lb/>was accordingly fulfill'd by the Miſſion of the Holy
	  <mw rend="align(center)" type="sig">b</mw>
	  <mw rend="break(no)" type="catch">Ghost</mw>

	  
<pb n="xxii"/>
<milestone n="b1v" unit="sig"/>
	<lb/>Ghoſt on the day of <name rend="slant(upright)">Pentecoſt</name>, as <persName ref="p:peter.nex">St. 
            <hi rend="slant(upright)">Peter</hi></persName> tells us.
	<lb/>And beſides others, there is mention of four Daughters
	<lb/>of <persName ref="p:philip.oce" rend="slant(upright)">Philip</persName>, Virgins who did Propheſy. For as in the Old,
	<lb/>ſo in the <rs type="title" ref="b:IT55558">New Teſtament</rs>, Women make a conſiderable
	<lb/>Figure; the Holy Virgin receiving the greateſt Honour
	<lb/>that Human Nature is capable of, when the Son of
	<lb/><mcr rend="case(allcaps)">God</mcr> vouchſafed to be her Son and to derive his Hu­
	<lb/>manity from her only. And if it is a greater Bleſſing
	<lb/><mcr rend="slant(upright)">to hear the Word of 
            <mcr rend="slant(upright)case(allcaps)">God</mcr> and keep it,</mcr> who are
	<lb/>more conſiderable for their Aſſiduity in this than the
	<lb/>Female Diſciples of our Lord? <persName rend="slant(upright)" ref="p:mary.neb">Mary</persName> being Exemplary,
	<lb/>and receiving a noble Encomium from Him, for her
	<lb/>Choice of the better Part.</p>
        <p>It wou'd be thought tedious to enumerate all the
	<lb/>excellent Women mention'd in the <rs type="title" ref="b:IT55558">New Teſtament</rs>,
	<lb/>whoſe humble Penitence and ardent Love, as <persName ref="p:mmagdalen.mda" rend="slant(upright)">Mag­
	<lb/>dalen's</persName>; their lively Faith and holy Importunity, as
	<lb/>the <name rend="slant(upright)">Syrophenician's</name>; extraordinary Piety and Upright­
	<lb/>neſs, as <persName ref="p:elizabeth.cks" rend="slant(upright)">Elizabeth's</persName>; 
            Hoſpitality, Charity and Dili­
	<lb/>gence, as <persName ref="p:martha.cks" rend="slant(upright)">Martha's</persName>, 
	  <persName ref="p:athaliah.qzk" rend="slant(upright)">Tabitha's</persName>; &amp;c. (ſee <bibl source="b:IT50057"><regMe>St. 
<persName ref="p:luke.rgw" rend="slant(upright)">Luc.</persName> 8</regMe></bibl>)
	<lb/>frequent and aſſiduous Devotions and Auſterities, as
	<lb/><persName ref="p:anna.nsw" rend="slant(upright)">Anna's</persName>; Conſtancy and 
             Courage, Perſeverance and ar­
	<lb/>dent Zeal, as that of the Holy Women who attended
	<lb/>our Lord to His Croſs, when His Diſciples generally
	<lb/>forſook, and the moſt Courageous had deny'd, Him; are
	<lb/>Recorded for our Example. Their Love was ſtronger
	<lb/>than Death, it follow'd our Saviour into the Grave.
	<lb/>And as a Reward, both the Angel and even the Lord
	<lb/>Himſelf appears firſt to them, and ſends them to Preach
	<lb/>the great Article of Reſurrection to the very Apo­
	<lb/>ſtles, who being as yet under the Power of the Preju­
        	<lb/>dices of their Sex, eſteem'd the Holy Women's <quote source="b:IT50057" rend="slant(upright)">Words
	<lb/>as idle Tales and believed them not.</quote></p>
        <p>Some Men will have it, that the Reaſon of our
	<lb/>Lord's appearing firſt to the Women, was their being
	  <mw type="catch">leaſt</mw>

<pb n="xxiii"/>
<milestone n="b2r" unit="sig"/>
	<lb/>leaſt able to keep a Secret; a Witty and Maſculine
	<lb/>Remarque, and wonderfully Reverent! But not to
	<lb/>diſpute whether thoſe Women were Blabs or no, there
	<lb/>are many Inſtances in Holy Scripture of Women who
	<lb/>did not betray the Confidence repos'd in them. Thus
	<lb/><persName ref="p:rahab.ptz" rend="slant(upright)">Rahab</persName> tho' formerly an ill Woman, being Converted
	<lb/>by the <mcr rend="slant(upright)">Report</mcr> of thoſe Miracles, which
	    tho' the <name rend="slant(upright)">Iſ­
	    	<lb/>raelites</name> <mcr rend="slant(upright)">ſaw</mcr>, yet they <quote source="b:IT50050" rend="slant(upright)">believ'd not
	    in <mcr rend="slant(upright)case(allcaps)">God</mcr>, nor put
	<lb/>their Trust in his Word,</quote> She acknowledges the <mcr rend="case(allcaps)">God</mcr>
	<lb/>of <mcr rend="slant(upright)">Heaven</mcr>, and as a Reward of her faithful Service
	<lb/>in concealing <persName ref="p:joshua.wlu" rend="slant(upright)">Joſhua's</persName> 
            Spies, is with her Family ex­
	<lb/>empted from the Ruine of her Country, and alſo has
	<lb/>the Honor of being nam'd in the Meſſiah's Genealogy.
	<lb/><persName ref="p:michal.klb" rend="slant(upright)">Michal</persName> to ſave 
    <persName rend="slant(upright)" ref="p:david.yei">David's</persName> Life expoſes her ſelf to the
	<lb/>Fury of a Jealous and Tyrannical Prince. A Girl
	<lb/>was truſted by <persName ref="p:david.yei" rend="slant(upright)">David's</persName> Grave Councellors to convey
	<lb/>him Intelligence in his Son's Rebellion; and when a
	<lb/>Lad had found it out and blab'd it to <persName ref="p:absalom.oiw" rend="slant(upright)">Abſalom</persName>, the
	<lb/>King's Friends confiding in the Prudence and Fidelity
	<lb/>of a Woman were ſecur'd by her. When our Lord
	<lb/>eſcap'd from the <name rend="slant(upright)">Jews</name>, he truſted Himſelf in the hands
	<lb/>of <persName ref="p:martha.cks" rend="slant(upright)">Martha</persName> and 
	    <persName ref="p:mmagdalen.mda" rend="slant(upright)">Mary</persName>. So does 
            <persName ref="p:peter.nex">St. <hi rend="slant(upright)">Peter</hi></persName> with ano­
	<lb/>ther <persName ref="p:mmark.kjd" rend="slant(upright)">Mary</persName> when the Angel deliver'd
	    him from <persName ref="p:agrippai.bft" rend="slant(upright)">Herod</persName>,
	<lb/>the Damſel <persName ref="p:rhoda.hqi" rend="slant(upright)">Rhoda</persName> too was acquainted with the Secret.
	<lb/>More might be ſaid, but one wou'd think here is enough
	<lb/>to ſhew, that whatever other Great and Wiſe Rea­
	<lb/>ſons Men may have for deſpiſing Women, and keeping
	<lb/>them in Ignorance and Slavery, it can't be from their
	<lb/>having learnt to do ſo in Holy Scripture. <rs type="title" rend="slant(upright)" ref="b:IT55556">The Bible</rs>
	<lb/>is for, and not againſt us, and cannot without great
	<lb/>violence done to it, be urg'd to our Prejudice.</p>
        <p>However, there are ſtrong and prevalent Reaſons
	<lb/>which demonſtrate the Superiority and Pre-eminence of 
	<lb/>the Men. For in the firſt place, Boys have much
	<lb/>Time and Pains, Care and Cost bestow'd on their
	  <mw rend="align(center)" type="sig">b2</mw>
	  <mw rend="break(no)" type="catch">Education</mw>

<pb n="xxiv"/>
<milestone n="b2v" unit="sig"/>
	<lb/>Education, Girls have little or none. The former
	<lb/>are early initiated in the Sciences, are made acquaint­
	<lb/>ed with Antient and Modern Diſcoveries, they Study
	<lb/>Books and Men, have all imaginable encouragement;
	<lb/>not only Fame, a dry Reward now adays, but alſo
	<lb/>Title, Authority, Power, and Riches themſelves which
	<lb/>purchaſe all things, are the Reward of their Improve­
	<lb/>ment. The latter are reſtrain'd, frown'd upon, and
	<lb/>beat, not <mcr rend="slant(upright)">for</mcr> but 
            <mcr rend="slant(upright)">from</mcr> the Muſes; Laughter and
	<lb/>Ridicule that never-failing Scare-Crow is ſet up to
	<lb/>drive them from the Tree of Knowledge. But if in
	<lb/>ſpite of all Difficulties Nature prevails, and they
	<lb/>can't be kept ſo ignorant as their Maſters wou'd have
	<lb/>them, they are ſtar'd upon as Monſters, Cenſur'd, En­
	<lb/>vy'd, and every way Diſcourag'd, or at the beſt they
        	<lb/>have the Fate the Proverb aſſigns them, <quote source="b:IT00791 b:IT99999" rend="slant(upright)">Vertue is
	<lb/>prais'd and ſtarv'd.</quote> And therefore ſince the courſeſt
	<lb/>Materials need the moſt Curing, as every Workman
	<lb/>can inform you, and the worſt Ground the moſt elabo­
	<lb/>rate Culture, it undeniably follows, that Men's Un­
	<lb/>derſtandings are ſuperior to Women's, for after many
	<lb/>Years Study and Experience they become Wiſe and
	<lb/>Learned, and Women are not Born ſo!</p>
        <p>Again, Men are poſſeſs'd of all Places of Power,
	<lb/>Truſt and Profit, they make Laws and exerciſe the
	<lb/>Magiſtracy, not only the ſharpeſt Sword, but even all
	<lb/>the Swords and Blunderbuſſes are theirs, which by
	<lb/>the ſtrongeſt Logic in the World, gives them the beſt
	<lb/>Title to every thing they pleaſe to claim as their Pre­
	<lb/>rogative; who ſhall contend with them? Immemorial
	<lb/>Preſcription is on their ſide in theſe parts of the World,
	<lb/>Antient Tradition and Modern Uſage! Our Fathers
	<lb/>have all along both Taught and Practis'd Superiority
	<lb/>over the weaker Sex, and conſequently Women are by
	<lb/>Nature inferior to Men, as was to be Demonſtrated.
	  <mw type="catch">An</mw>

<pb n="xxv"/>
<milestone n="b3r" unit="sig"/>
	<lb/>An Argument which muſt be acknowledg'd unanſwera­
	<lb/>ble, for as well as I love my Sex, I will not pretend
	<lb/>a Reply to <mcr rend="slant(upright)">ſuch</mcr> Demonſtration!</p>
        <p>Only let me beg to be inform'd, to whom we poor
	<lb/>Fatherleſs Maids, and Widows who have loſt their Ma­
	<lb/>ſters, owe Subjection? It can't be to all Men in ge­
	<lb/>neral, unleſs all Men were agreed to give the ſame
	<lb/>Commands; do we then fall as Strays to the firſt who
	<lb/>finds us? By the Maxims of ſome Men, and the Con­
	<lb/>duct of ſome Women one wou'd think ſo. But whoever
	<lb/>he be that happens to become our Maſter, if he al­
	<lb/>lows us to be Reaſonable Creatures, and does not merely
	<lb/>Compliment us with that Title, ſince no man denies
	<lb/>our Readineſs to uſe our Tongues, it wou'd tend, I ſhou'd
	<lb/>think, to our Maſter's advantage, and therefore he may
	<lb/>pleaſe to be advis'd to teach us to improve our Reaſon.
	<lb/>But if Reaſon is only allow'd us by way of Raillery, and
	<lb/>the ſecret Maxim is that we have none, or little more
	<lb/>than Brutes, 'tis the beſt way to confine us with Chain
	<lb/>and Block to the Chimney-Corner, which probably might
	<lb/>ſave the Eſtates of ſome Families and the Honor of others.</p>
        <p>I do not propoſe this to prevent a Rebellion, for
	<lb/>Women are not ſo well united as to form an Inſur­
	<lb/>rection. They are for the moſt part Wiſe enough to
	<lb/>Love their Chains, and to diſcern how very becomingly
	<lb/>they ſet. They think as humbly of themſelves as their
	<lb/>Maſters can wiſh, with reſpect to the other Sex, but
	<lb/>in regard to their own, they have a Spice of Maſcu­
	<lb/>line Ambition, every one wou'd Lead, and none will
	<lb/>Follow. Both Sexes being too apt to Envy, and too
	<lb/>backward in Emulating, and take more delight in detra­
	<lb/>cting from their Neighbour's Vertue than in improving
	<lb/>their own. And therefore as to thoſe Women who find
	<lb/>themſelves born for Slavery, and are ſo ſenſible of their
	<lb/>own Meanneſs as to conclude it impoſſible to attain to
	  <mw type="catch">any</mw>

<pb n="xxvi"/>
<milestone n="b3v" unit="sig"/>
	<lb/>any thing excellent, ſince they are, or ought to be beſt
	<lb/>acquainted with their own Strength and Genius, She's
	<lb/>a Fool who wou'd attempt their Deliverance of Improve­
	<lb/>ment. No, let them enjoy the great Honor and Feli­
	<lb/>city of their Tame, Submiſſive and Depending Temper!
	<lb/>Let the men applaud, and let them Glory in, this
	<lb/>wonderful Humility! Let them receive the Flatteries
	<lb/>and Grimaces of the other Sex, live unenvy'd by
	<lb/>their own, and be as much Belov'd as one ſuch Woman
	<lb/>can afford to Love another! Let them enjoy the Glory
	<lb/>of treading in the Footſteps of their Predeceſſors, and
	<lb/>of having the Prudence to avoid that audacious at­
	<lb/>tempt of ſoaring beyond their Sphere! Let them Huſ­
	<lb/>wife or Play, Dreſs and be pretty entertaining Com­
	<lb/>pany! Or which is better, relieve the Poor to eaſe their
	<lb/>own Compaſſions, reade Pious Books, ſay their Prayers
	<lb/>and go to Church, becauſe they have been Taught and
	<lb/>Us'd to do ſo, without being able to give a better Rea­
	<lb/>ſon for their Faith and Practice! Let them not by
	<lb/>any means aſpire at being Women of Underſtanding,
	<lb/>becauſe no Man can endure a Woman of Superior Senſe,
	<lb/>or wou'd treat a reaſonable Woman civilly, but that he
	<lb/>thinks he ſtands on higher ground, and that ſhe is ſo
	<lb/>Wiſe as to make exceptions in his Favour, and to
	<lb/>take her Meaſures by his Directions; they may pre­
	<lb/>tend to Senſe indeed, ſince mere Pretences only render
	<lb/>one the more Ridiculous! Let them in ſhort be what
	<lb/>is call'd <mcr rend="slant(upright)">very</mcr> Women, for this is moſt
	    acceptable to
	<lb/>all ſorts of Men; or let them aim at the Title of
	<lb/><mcr rend="slant(upright)">Good Devout</mcr> Women, ſince ſome Men can bear with
	<lb/>this; but let them not Judge of the Sex by their own
	<lb/>Scantling. For the great Author of Nature and Foun­
	<lb/>tain of all Perfection, never deſign'd that the Mean 
	<lb/>and Imperfect, but that the moſt Compleat and Ex­
	  <mw type="catch">cellent</mw>

<pb n="xxvii"/>
<milestone n="b4r" unit="sig"/>
	<lb/>cellent of His Creatures in every Kind, ſhou'd be the
	<lb/>Standard to the reſt.</p>
        <p>To conclude, if that <mcr rend="slant(upright)case(allcaps)">Great Queen</mcr> who has
	<lb/>ſubdu'd the Proud, and made the pretended Invincible
	<lb/>more than once fly before her; who has Reſcu'd an Em­
	<lb/>pire, Reduc'd a Kingdom, Conquer'd Provinces in as
	<lb/>little time almoſt as one can Travel them, and ſeems to
	<lb/>have Chain'd Victory to her Standard; who diſpoſes of
	<lb/>Crowns, gives Laws and Liberty to <name rend="slant(upright)">Europe</name>, and is
	<lb/>the chief Inſtrument in the Hand of the Almighty to
	<lb/>pull down and to ſet up the Great Men of the Earth;
	<lb/>who Conquers every where for others, and no where for
	<lb/>her ſelf but in the Hearts of the Conquer'd, who are
	<lb/>of the number of thoſe who reap the benefit of her Tri­
	<lb/>umphs; whilſt ſhe only reaps for her ſelf the Lawrels
	<lb/>of Diſintereſſed Glory, and the Royal Pleaſure of do­
	<lb/>ing Heroically; if this Glory of her own Sex and En­
	<lb/>vy of the other, will not think we need, or does not
	<lb/>hold us worthy of, the Protection of her ever Victorious
	<lb/>Arms, and Men have not the Gratitude for her ſake
	<lb/>at leaſt to do Juſtice to her Sex, who has been ſuch a
	<lb/>univerſal Benefactreſs to theirs: Adieu to the Liber­
	<lb/>ties not of this or that Nation or Region only, but of
	<lb/>the Moiety of Mankind! To all the great things that
	<lb/>Women might perform, Inſpir'd by her Example, En­
	<lb/>courag'd by her Smiles, and ſupported by her Power!
	<lb/>To their Diſcovery of New Worlds for the Exerciſe of
	<lb/>her Goodneſs, New Sciences to publiſh her Fame, and
	<lb/>reducing Nature it ſelf to a Subjection to her Em­
	<lb/>pire! To their deſtroying thoſe worſt of Tyrants
	<lb/>Impiety and Immorality, which dare to ſtalk about even
	<lb/>in her own Dominions, and to devour Souls almoſt with­
	<lb/>in view of her Throne, leaving a ſtench behind them
	<lb/>ſcarce to be corrected even by the Incenſe of her Devo­
	<lb/>tions! To the Women's Tracing a new Path to Honor,
	  <mw type="catch">in</mw>

<pb n="xxviii"/>
<milestone n="b4v" unit="sig"/>
	<lb/>in which none ſhall walk but ſuch as ſcorn to Cringe
	<lb/>in order to Riſe, and who are Proof both againſt giving
	<lb/>and receiving Flattery! In a word, to thoſe Halcyon,
	<lb/>or if you will <mcr rend="slant(upright)">Millennium</mcr> Days, in which the Wolf
	<lb/>and the Lamb ſhall feed together, and a Tyrannous
	<lb/>Domination which Nature never meant, ſhall no lon­
	<lb/>ger render uſeleſs if not hurtful, the Induſtry and Un­
	<lb/>derſtandings of half Mankind!</p>
      </div>
      <div type="corrigenda">
        <head rend="pre(#rule)case(allcaps)slant(italic)">Errata.</head>
        <p>
          <list type="errata">
            <item rend="break(no)"><hi rend="class(#DIC)">I</hi><hi rend="case(allcaps)">n</hi> the 
            	<title rend="slant(italic)" ref="b:TR00465.1">Preface</title> P. 1. l. 8. r. <ref xml:id="ec1" type="correction" target="#er1">are</ref>.</item>
            <item rend="break(no)">p. 2. l. 7. r. <ref xml:id="ec2" type="correction" target="#er2">Ingenuous</ref></item>
            <lb/>
            <item rend="break(no)">p. 6. l. 22. r. <ref xml:id="ec3" type="correction" target="#er3">Men.</ref></item>
            <item rend="break(no)">p. 8. l. 17. r. <ref xml:id="ec4" type="correction" target="#er4">Women.</ref></item>
            <item rend="break(no)">p. 11. l. 28. 
<lb/>r. <ref xml:id="ec5" type="correction" target="#er5">in neither.</ref></item>
            <item rend="break(no)">p. 17. l. 22. r. <ref xml:id="ec6" type="correction" target="#er6">Sheba.</ref></item>
          </list>
        </p>
        <p>
          <list type="errata">
            <item rend="break(no)">In the <mcr>Book</mcr> p. 1. l. 16. for had read <ref xml:id="ec7" type="correction" target="#er7">once</ref>.</item>
            <item rend="break(no)">p. 5. l. 22 for <mcr>meer</mcr> r. <ref xml:id="ec8" type="correction" target="#er8">mixt</ref>.</item>
            <item rend="break(no)">p. 19. l. 15. for <mcr>like</mcr> r. <ref xml:id="ec9" type="correction" target="#er9">as</ref>.</item>
            <item rend="break(no)">p. 32. l. 27 for <mcr>but</mcr> r. <ref xml:id="ec10" type="correction" target="#er10">and</ref>.</item>
            <item rend="break(no)">p. 33. l. 19. r. <ref xml:id="ec11" type="correction" target="#er11">is to receive</ref>.</item>
            <item rend="break(no)">p. 35. l. 26. for <mcr>of</mcr> r. <ref xml:id="ec12" type="correction" target="#er12">for</ref>.</item>
            <item rend="break(no)">p. 42. l. 4. r. <ref xml:id="ec13" type="correction" target="#er13">Women</ref>.</item>
            <item rend="break(no)">p. 56. l. 5. r. <ref xml:id="ec14" type="correction" target="#er14">the</ref>.</item>
            <item rend="break(no)">p. 77 l. 2. <choice><abbr>dele</abbr><expan>delete</expan></choice> <ref xml:id="ec15" type="correction" target="#er15">to</ref>.</item>
          </list>
        </p>
      </div>
    </front>
  	<pb n="1"/>
  	<milestone n="B1r" unit="sig"/>
  	<mw rend="align(center)" type="pageNum">1</mw>
  	<body rend="pre(#rule)" type="essay">

    
        <head rend="align(center)case(allcaps)"><lb/>Some
	  <lb/>Reflections
	  <lb/>Upon
	  <lb/>Marriage.</head>
        <p><hi rend="class(#DIC)">C</hi><hi rend="case(allcaps)">u</hi>riosity, which is
	  ſometimes an
	<lb/>occaſion of Good, and too fre­
	<lb/>quently of Miſchief, by diſtur­
	<lb/>bing either our Own, or our
	<lb/>Neighbour's Repoſe, having put me upon
	<lb/>reading <mcr>the Duke and Dutcheſs of <persName ref="p:hmancini.pxr" rend="slant(upright)">Maza­
	<lb/>rine's</persName> Caſe</mcr>; I thought an Afternoon wou'd 
	<lb/>not be quite thrown away in purſuing
	<lb/>ſome Reflections that it occaſion'd. The
	<lb/>Name of <persName ref="p:hmancini.pxr">Mazarine</persName> is conſiderable enough
	<lb/>to draw the Eyes of the Curious, and
	<lb/>when one remembers what a noiſe it <ref xml:id="er7" type="error" target="#ec7">had</ref>
	<lb/>made in <placeName>Europe</placeName>, what Politick Schemes
	<lb/>have been laid, what vaſt Deſigns brought
	<lb/>about by the Cardinal that bore it; how
	<lb/>well his meaſures were concerted for the
	<lb/>Grandeur of that Naton into which he
	<lb/>was tranſplanted, and that he wanted nei­
	<lb/>ther Power nor Inclination to eſtabliſh his
	<lb/>own Family and make it as conſiderable as
	  <mw rend="align(center)" type="sig">B</mw>
	  <mw rend="break(no)" type="catch">any</mw>

<pb n="2"/>
<milestone n="B1v" unit="sig"/>
<mw rend="align(left)" type="pageNum">2</mw>
	<lb/>any Subject's could poſſible be, and what
	<lb/>Honours and Riches he had heap'd toge­
	<lb/>ther in order to this; one cannot but en­
	<lb/>quire how it comes about that he ſhould
	<lb/>be ſo defeated in this laſt deſign? and that
	<lb/>thoſe to whom he intruſted his Name and
	<lb/>Treaſure, ſhould make a figure ſo very
	<lb/>different from what might have been ex­
	<lb/>pected from them? And tho' one had not
	<lb/>Piety enough to make a Religious Refle­
	<lb/>ction, yet Civil Prudence would almoſt en­
        	<lb/>force them to ſay, that <quote source="b:IT50072">Man being in Ho­
	<lb/>nour has no Underſtanding, but is compar'd
	<lb/>unto the Beaſts that periſh.</quote> He bleſſeth his
	<lb/>Soul, and thinks himſelf a happy Man,
	<lb/>imagining his Houſe will endure for ever,
	<lb/>and that he has eſtabliſh'd his Name and
	<lb/>Family. But how wiſe ſoever he may be
	<lb/>in other reſpects, in this he acts no better
	<lb/>than the Ignorant and Fooliſh. For as he
	<lb/>carries nothing away with him when he
	<lb/>dies, ſo neither will his Pomp and Glory
	<lb/>deſcend as he intended. Generous and
	<lb/>Worthy Actions only can ſecure him from
	<lb/>Oblivion, or what is worſe, being remem­
	<lb/>bred with Contempt; ſo little reaſon have
	<lb/>we to Envy any Man's Wealth and Great­
	<lb/>neſs, but much to Emulate his Wiſdom
	<lb/>and Vertue.</p>
        <p>The <persName ref="p:hmancini.pxr"><hi rend="slant(upright)">Dutcheſs of</hi> <placeName>Mazarine</placeName>'s</persName> Name has
	<lb/>ſpread perhaps as far as her Uncle's, and
	  <mw type="catch">one</mw>

<pb n="3"/>
<milestone n="B2r" unit="sig"/>
<mw type="pageNum">3</mw>
	<lb/>one can't help wiſhing that ſo much Wit
	<lb/>and Beauty, ſo much Politeneſs and Ad­
	<lb/>dreſs, had been accompany'd and ſuppor­
	<lb/>ted by more valuable and laſting Quali­
	<lb/>ties; one cannot but deſire that her Ad­
	<lb/>vocate inſtead of recriminating had clear'd
	<lb/>the imputations laid on her, and that ſhe
	<lb/>her ſelf, who ſays enough in her Memoirs
	<lb/>to ſhew ſhe was unfortunate, had ſaid more
	<lb/>to prove her ſelf diſcreet. They muſt be high­
	<lb/>ly ill-natur'd who do not pity her ill For­
	<lb/>tune at the ſame time that they muſt blame
	<lb/>her Conduct, and regret that ſuch a Tre­
	<lb/>ſure ſhould fall into his hands who was not
	<lb/>worthy of it, nor knew how to value and
	<lb/>improve it; that ſhe who was capable of 
	<lb/>being a great Ornament to her Family and
	<lb/>bleſſing to the Age ſhe liv'd in, ſhould on­
	<lb/>ly ſerve (to ſay no worſe) as an unhappy
	<lb/>Shipwrack to point out the dangers of an
	<lb/>ill Education and unequal Marriage.</p>
        <p><persName ref="p:adelaport.qct"><hi rend="slant(upright)">Monſieur</hi> Mazarine</persName> is not to be juſtified,
	<lb/>nor Madam his Spouſe excus'd. It is no
	<lb/>queſtion which is moſt Criminal, the ha­
	<lb/>ving no Senſe, or the abuſe of a liberal
	<lb/>Portion; nor any hard matter to deter­
	<lb/>mine who is moſt to be pity'd, he whom
	<lb/>Nature never qualify'd for great things,
	<lb/>who therefore can't be very ſenſible of
	<lb/>great Misfortunes; or ſhe, who being ca­
	<lb/>pable of every thing, muſt therefore ſuf­
	  <mw rend="align(center)" type="sig">B2</mw>
	  <mw rend="break(no)" type="catch">fer</mw>

<pb n="4"/>
<milestone n="B2v" unit="sig"/>
<mw rend="align(left)" type="pageNum">4</mw>
	<lb/>fer more and be the more lamented. To
	<lb/>be yok'd for Life to a diſagreeable Perſon
	<lb/>and Temper; to have Folly and Ignorance
	<lb/>tyrannize over Wit and Senſe; to be con­
	<lb/>tradicted in every thing one does or ſays,
	<lb/>and bore down not by Reaſon but Autho­
	<lb/>rity; to be denied ones moſt innocent de­
	<lb/>ſires, for no other cauſe but the Will and
	<lb/>Pleaſure of an abſolute Lord and Maſter,
	<lb/>whoſe Follies a Woman with all her Pru­
	<lb/>dence cannot hide, and whoſe Commands
	<lb/>ſhe cannot but deſpiſe at the ſame time
	<lb/>ſhe obeys them; is a miſery none can have
	<lb/>a juſt Idea of, but thoſe who have felt it.</p>
        <p>Theſe are great Provocations, but no­
	<lb/>thing can juſtify the revenging the Injuries
	<lb/>we receive from others, upon our ſelves:
	<lb/>The <name>Italian</name> Proverb ſhews a much better
	<lb/>way; <quote source="b:IT99999">If you would be reveng'd of your
	<lb/>Enemies, live well.</quote> Had <persName ref="p:hmancini.pxr"><hi rend="slant(upright)">Madam</hi> Maza­
	<lb/>rine's</persName> Education made a right Improve­
	<lb/>ment of her Wit and Senſe, we ſhould not
	<lb/>have found her ſeeking Relief by ſuch im­
	<lb/>prudent, not to ſay ſcandalous Methods, as
	<lb/>the running away in Diſguiſe with a ſpruce
	<lb/>Cavalier, and rambling to ſo many Courts
	<lb/>and Places, nor diverting her ſelf with
	<lb/>ſuch Childiſh, Ridiculous, or Ill-natur'd
	<lb/>Amuſements, as the greateſt part of the
	<lb/>Adventures in her Memoirs are made up
	<lb/>of. True Wit conſiſts not meerly in doing
	  <mw type="catch">or</mw>

<pb n="5"/>
<milestone n="B3r" unit="sig"/>
<mw type="pageNum">5</mw>
	<lb/>or ſaying what is out of the way, but in
	<lb/>ſuch ſurprizing things as are fit and be­
	<lb/>coming the perſon from whom they come.
	<lb/>That which ſtirs us up to Laughter moſt
	<lb/>commonly excites our Contempt; to pleaſe 
	<lb/>and to make Merry are two very different
	<lb/>Talents. But what Remedies can be admi­
	<lb/>niſtred, what Relief expected, when Devo­
	<lb/>tion, the only true Support in Diſtreſs, is
	<lb/>turn'd into Ridicule? Unhappy is that
	<lb/>Grandeur which makes us too great to be
	<lb/>good; and that Wit which ſets us at a di­
	<lb/>ſtance from true Wiſdom. Even Bigotry
	<lb/>it ſelf, as contemptible as it is, is prefera­
	<lb/>ble to Prophane Wit; for <mcr>that</mcr> only re­
	<lb/>quires our Pity, but <mcr>this</mcr> deſerves our Ab­
	<lb/>horrence.</p>
        <p>A Woman who ſeeks Conſolation under
	<lb/>Domeſtic troubles from the Gaieties of a
	<lb/>Court, from Gaming and Courtſhip, from
	<lb/>Rambling and odd Adventures, and the
	<lb/>Amuſements <ref xml:id="er8" type="correction" target="#ec8">meer</ref> Company affords, may
	<lb/>Plaiſter up the Sore, but will never heal it;
	<lb/>nay, which is worſe, ſhe makes it Feſter be­
	<lb/>yond a poſſibility of Cure. She juſtifies the
	<lb/>Injury her Husband has done her, by ſhew­
	<lb/>ing that whatever other good Qualities ſhe
	<lb/>may have, Diſcretion, one of the Princi­
	<lb/>pal, is wanting. She may be Innocent, but
	<lb/>ſhe can never prove ſhe is ſo; all that Cha­
	<lb/>rity can do for her when ſhe's Cenſur'd is
	  <mw rend="align(center)" type="sig">B3</mw>
	  <mw rend="break(no)" type="catch">only</mw>

<pb n="6"/>
<milestone n="B3v" unit="sig"/>
<mw rend="align(left)" type="pageNum">6</mw>
	<lb/>only to be ſilent, it can make no Apologies
	<lb/>for ſuſpicious Actions. An ill Husband may
	<lb/>deprive a Wife of the comfort and quiet of
	<lb/>her Life; may give her occaſion of exerci­
	<lb/>ſing her Virtue, may try her Patience and
	<lb/>Fortitude to the utmoſt, but that's all he
	<lb/>can do: 'tis her ſelf only can accompliſh
	<lb/>her Ruin. Had <persName ref="p:hmancini.pxr"><hi rend="slant(upright)">Madam</hi> Mazarine's</persName> Re­
	<lb/>ſerve been what it ought to be, <persName ref="p:herard.ijs"><hi rend="slant(upright)">Monſieur</hi><lb/>Herard</persName> needed not to have warded off ſo 
	<lb/>carefully, the nice Subject of the Lady's
	<lb/>Honour, nor her Advocate have ſtrain'd ſo
	<lb/>hard for Colours to excuſe ſuch Actions as
	<lb/>will hardly bear 'em; a Man indeed ſhews
	<lb/>the beſt ſide of his Wit, tho' the worſt of
	<lb/>his Integrity, when he has an ill Cauſe to
	<lb/>manage. Truth is bold and vehement; ſhe
	<lb/>depends upon her own ſtrength, and ſo ſhe
	<lb/>be plac'd in a true Light, thinks it not ne­
	<lb/>ceſſary to uſe Artifice and Addreſs as a Re­
	<lb/>commendation; but the prejudices of Men
	<lb/>have made them neceſſary: their Imagina­
	<lb/>tion gets the better of their Underſtanding,
	<lb/>and more judge according to Appearances,
	<lb/>than ſearch after the Truth of Things.</p>
        <p>What an ill Figure does a Woman make
	<lb/>with all the Charms of her Beauty and
	<lb/>Sprightlineſs of her Wit, with all her good
	<lb/>Humour and inſinuating Addreſs; tho' ſhe
	<lb/>be the beſt Œconomiſt in the World, the
	<lb/>moſt entertaining Converſation; if ſhe re­
	  <mw type="catch">mit</mw>

<pb n="7"/>
<milestone n="B4r" unit="sig"/>
<mw type="pageNum">7</mw>
	<lb/>mit her Guard, abate in the Severity of her
	<lb/>Caution and Strictneſs of her Vertue, and
	<lb/>neglect thoſe Methods which are neceſſary
	<lb/>to keep her not only from a Crime, but
	<lb/>from the very ſuſpicion of one.</p>
        <p>Are the being forbid having Comedies in
	<lb/>her Houſe, an ill natur'd Jeſt, diſmiſſing of
	<lb/>a Servant, impoſing Domeſtics, or fre­
	<lb/>quent changing them, ſufficient Reaſons to
	<lb/>Authorize a Woman's leaving her Husband
	<lb/>and breaking from the ſtrongeſt Bands, ex­
	<lb/>poſing her ſelf to Temptations and Injuries
	<lb/>from the Bad, to the contempt, or at the
	<lb/>beſt to the pity of the Good, and the juſt
	<lb/>Cenſure of all? A Woman of ſenſe one
	<lb/>would think ſhould take little ſatisfaction in
	<lb/>the Cringes and Courtſhip of her Adorers,
	<lb/>even when ſhe is ſingle; but it is Criminal
	<lb/>in a Wife to admit them: intereſted Per­
	<lb/>ſons may call it Gallantry, but with the
	<lb/>modeſt and diſcreet it is like to have a har­
	<lb/>der Name, or elſe Gallantry will paſs for a
	<lb/>ſcandalous thing, not to be allow'd among 
	<lb/>Vertuous Perſons.</p>
        <p>But <persName ref="p:hmancini.pxr"><hi rend="slant(upright)">Madam</hi> Mazarine</persName> is dead, may her
	<lb/>Faults die with her; may there be no more
	<lb/>occaſion given for the like Adventures, or
	<lb/>if there is, may the Ladies be more Wiſe
	<lb/>and Good than to take it! Let us ſee then
	<lb/>from whence the miſchief proceeds, and
	<lb/>try if it can be prevented; for certainly
	  <mw rend="align(center)" type="sig">B4</mw>
	  <mw rend="break(no)" type="catch">Men</mw>

<pb n="8"/>
<milestone n="B4v" unit="sig"/>
<mw rend="align(left)" type="pageNum">8</mw>
	<lb/>Men may be very happy in a Married State;
	<lb/>'tis their own fault if they are at any time
	<lb/>otherwiſe. The wiſe Inſtitutor of Matri­
	<lb/>mony never did any thing in vain; we are
	<lb/>the Sots and Fools if what he deſign'd for
	<lb/>our Good, be to us an occaſion of falling.
	<lb/>For Marriage, notwithſtanding all the looſe
	<lb/>talk of the Town, the Satyrs of Ancient or
	<lb/>Modern pretenders to Wit, will never loſe
	<lb/>its due praiſe from judicious Perſons. Tho'
	<lb/>much may be ſaid againſt this or that Match,
	<lb/>tho' the Ridiculouſneſs of ſome, the Wick­
	<lb/>edneſs of others and Imprudence of too ma­
	<lb/>ny, too often provoke our wonder or ſcorn,
	<lb/>our indignation or pity, yet Marriage in
	<lb/>general is too ſacred to be treated with
	<lb/>Diſreſpect, too venerable to be the ſubject
	<lb/>of Raillery and Buffonery. It is the Inſti­
	<lb/>tution of Heaven, the only Honourable
	<lb/>way of continuing Mankind, and far be it
	<lb/>from us to think there could have been a
	<lb/>better than infinite Wiſdom has found out
	<lb/>for us.</p>
        <p>But upon what are the Satyrs againſt
	<lb/>Marriage grounded? Not upon the State
	<lb/>it ſelf, if they are juſt, but upon the ill
	<lb/>Choice, or fooliſh Conduct of thoſe who
	<lb/>are in it, and what has Marriage, conſi­
	<lb/>dered in its ſelf, to do with theſe? Let
	<lb/>every Man bear his own Burden: If
	<lb/>through inordinate Paſſion, Raſhneſs, Hu­
	  <mw type="catch">mour,</mw>

<pb n="9"/>
<milestone n="B5r" unit="sig"/>
<mw type="pageNum">9</mw>
	<lb/>mour, Pride, Covetouſneſs, or any the like
	<lb/>Folly, a Man makes an Imprudent Choice,
	<lb/>Why ſhould Marriage be exclaim'd a­
	<lb/>gainſt? Let him blame himſelf for en­
	<lb/>tring into an unequal Yoke, and making
	<lb/>Choice of one who perhaps may prove a
	<lb/>Burthen, a Diſgrace and Plague, inſtead
	<lb/>of a Help and Comfort to him. Could
	<lb/>there be no ſuch thing as an happy Mar­
	<lb/>riage, Arguments againſt Marriage would
	<lb/>hold good, but ſince the thing is not only
	<lb/>poſſible, but even very probable, provided
	<lb/>we take but competent Care, Act like Wiſe
	<lb/>Men and Chriſtians, and acquit our ſelves
	<lb/>as we ought, all we have to ſay againſt it
	<lb/>ſerves only to ſhew the Levity or Impiety
	<lb/>of our own Minds; we only make ſome
	<lb/>flouriſhes of Wit, tho' ſcarce without In­
	<lb/>juſtice; and tho' we talk prettily it is but
	<lb/>very little to the purpoſe.</p>
        <p>Is it the being ty'd to <mcr>One</mcr> that offends
	<lb/>us? Why this ought rather to recom­
	<lb/>mend Marriage to us, and would really do
	<lb/>ſo, were we guided by Reaſon, and not by
	<lb/>Humour or brutiſh Paſſion. He who does
	<lb/>not make Friendſhip the chief inducement
	<lb/>to his Choice, and prefer it before any
	<lb/>other conſideration, does not deſerve a
	<lb/>good Wife, and therefore ſhould not com­
	<lb/>plain if he goes without one. Now we
	<lb/>can never grow weary of our Friends; the
	  <mw type="catch">longer</mw>

<pb n="10"/>
<milestone n="B5v" unit="sig"/>
<mw rend="align(left)" type="pageNum">10</mw>
	<lb/>longer we have had them the more they
	<lb/>are endear'd to us; and if we have One
	<lb/>well aſſur'd, we need ſeek no further, but
	<lb/>are ſufficiently happy in Her. The love
	<lb/>of Variety in this and in other caſes, ſhews
	<lb/>only the ill Temper of our own Minds, in
	<lb/>that we ſeek for <mcr>ſettled</mcr> Happineſs in this
	<lb/>preſent World, where it is not to be found,
	<lb/>inſtead of being Content with a competent
	<lb/>ſhare, chearfully enjoying and being thank­
	<lb/>ful for the Good that is afforded us, and
	<lb/>patiently bearing with the Inconveniences
	<lb/>that attend it.</p>
        <p>The Chriſtian Inſtitution of Marriage 
	<lb/>provides the beſt that may be for Domeſtic
	<lb/>Quiet and Content, and for the Education
	<lb/>of Children; ſo that if we were not under
	<lb/>the tye of Religion, even the Good of So­
	<lb/>ciety and civil Duty would oblige us to
	<lb/>what that requires at our Hands. And ſince
	<lb/>the very beſt of us are but poor frail Crea­
	<lb/>tures, full of Ignorance and Infirmity, ſo
	<lb/>that in Juſtice we ought to tolerate each
	<lb/>other, and exerciſe that Patience towards
	<lb/>our Companions to Day, which we ſhall
	<lb/>give them occaſion to ſhew towards us to
	<lb/>Morrow, the more we are accuſtom'd to
	<lb/>any one's Converſation, the better ſhall
	<lb/>we underſtand their Humour, be more able
	<lb/>to comply with their Weakneſs and leſs of­
	<lb/>fended at it. For he who would have every
	  <mw type="catch">one</mw>

<pb n="11"/>
<milestone n="B6r" unit="sig"/>
<mw type="pageNum">11</mw>
	<lb/>one ſubmit to his Humours and will not
	<lb/>in his turn comply with them, tho' we
	<lb/>ſhould ſuppoſe him always in the Right,
	<lb/>whereas a Man of this temper very ſeldom
	<lb/>is ſo, he's not fit for a Husband, ſcarce fit
	<lb/>for Society, but ought to be turn'd out of
	<lb/>the Herd to live by himſelf.</p>
        <p>There may indeed be inconveniencies
	<lb/>in a Married Life; but is there any Con­
	<lb/>dition without them? And he who lives 
	<lb/>ſingle that he may indulge Licentiouſneſs
	<lb/>and give up himſelf to the conduct of wild
	<lb/>and ungovern'd Deſires, or indeed out of
	<lb/>any other inducement, than the Glory of
	<lb/><mcr rend="slant(upright)case(allcaps)">God</mcr> and the Good of his Soul, through
	<lb/>the proſpect he has of doing more Good,
	<lb/>or becauſe his frame and diſpoſition of
	<lb/>Mind are fitted for it, may rail as he
	<lb/>pleaſes againſt Matrimony, but can ne­
	<lb/>ver juſtifie his own Conduct, nor clear it
	<lb/>from the imputation of Wickedneſs and
	<lb/>Folly.</p>
        <p>But if Marriage be ſuch a bleſſed State,
	<lb/>how comes it, may you ſay, that there are
	<lb/>ſo few happy Marriages? Now in an­
	<lb/>ſwer to this, it is not to be wonder'd that
	<lb/>ſo few ſucceed, we ſhould rather be ſur­
	<lb/>priz'd to find ſo many do, conſidering how
	<lb/>imprudently Men engage, the Motives they
	<lb/>act by, and the very ſtrange Conduct they 
	<lb/>obſerve throughout.</p>
        <mw type="catch">For</mw>
        <pb n="12"/>
        <milestone n="B6v" unit="sig"/>
        <mw rend="align(left)" type="pageNum">12</mw>
        <p>For pray, what do Men propoſe to
	  <lb/>themſelves in Marriage? What Qualifi­
	  <lb/>cations do they look after in a Spouſe?
	  <lb/>What will ſhe bring is the firſt enquiry?
	  <lb/>How many Acres? Or how much ready
	  <lb/>Coin? Not that this is altogether an un­
	  <lb/>neceſſary Queſtion, for Marriage with­
	  <lb/>out a Competency, that is, not only a
	  <lb/>bare Subſiſtence, but even a handſome
	  <lb/>and plentiful Proviſion, according to the
	  <lb/>Quality and Circumſtances of the Parties,
	  <lb/>is no very comfortable Condition. They
	  <lb/>who marry for Love as they call it, find
	  <lb/>time enough to repent their raſh Folly,
	  <lb/>and are not long in being convinc'd, that
	  <lb/>whatever fine Speeches might be made in
	  <lb/>the heat of Paſſion, there could be no <mcr>real
	    <lb/>Kindneſs</mcr> between thoſe who can agree to
	  <lb/>make each other miſerable. But as an
	  <lb/>Eſtate is to be conſider'd, ſo it ſhould not
	  <lb/>be the <mcr>Main</mcr>, much leſs the <mcr>Only</mcr> conſide­
	  <lb/>ration, for Happineſs does not depend on
	  <lb/>Wealth, <mcr>that</mcr> may be wanting, and too
	  <lb/>often is, where <mcr>this</mcr> abounds. He who Mar­
	  <lb/>ries himſelf to a Fortune only, muſt expect
	  <lb/>no other ſatisfaction than that can bring
	  <lb/>him, but let him not ſay that<sic>e</sic> Marriage,
	  <lb/>but that his own Covetous or Prodigal
	  <lb/>Temper, has made him unhappy. What
	  <lb/>Joy has that Man in all his Plenty, who
	  <lb/>muſt either run from home to poſſeſs it,
	  <mw type="catch">con-</mw>

<pb n="13"/>
<milestone n="B7r" unit="sig"/>
<mw type="pageNum">13</mw>
	  <lb/>contrary to all the Rules of Justice, to the
	  <lb/>Laws of <mcr rend="slant(upright)case(allcaps)">God</mcr> and Man, nay, even in
	  <lb/>oppoſition to Good nature, and Good
	  <lb/>breeding too, which ſome Men make more
	  <lb/>account of than all the reſt; or elſe be
	  <lb/>forc'd to ſhare it with a Woman whoſe
	  <lb/>Perſon or Temper is diſagreeable, whoſe
	  <lb/>preſence is ſufficient to ſour all his En­
	  <lb/>joyments, ſo that if he has any re­
	  <lb/>mains of Religion, or Good manners, he
	  <lb/>muſt ſuffer the uneaſineſs of a continual
	  <lb/>watch, to force himſelf to a conſtrain'd
	  <lb/>Civility!</p>
        <p>Few Men have ſo much Goodneſs as to
	  <lb/>bring themſelves to a liking of what they
	  <lb/>loath'd, meerly becauſe it is their Duty
	  <lb/>to like; on the contrary, when they Mar­
	  <lb/>ry with an indifferency, to pleaſe their
	  <lb/>Friends or encreaſe their Fortune, the
	  <lb/>indifferency proceeds to an averſion, and
	  <lb/>perhaps even the kindneſs and complaiſance
	  <lb/>of the poor abus'd Wife ſhall only ſerve
	  <lb/>to encreaſe it. What follows then? There
	  <lb/>is no content at home, ſo it is ſought
	  <lb/>elſewhere, and the Fortune ſo unjuſtly
	  <lb/>got, is as careleſsly ſquander'd. The Man
	  <lb/>takes a looſe, what ſhou'd hinder him?
	  <lb/>He has all in his hands, and Cuſtom has
	  <lb/>almoſt taken off that ſmall Reſtraint Repu­
	  <lb/>tation us'd to lay. The Wife finds too
	  <lb/>late what was the Idol the Man adored,
	  <mw type="catch">which</mw>

<pb n="14"/>
<milestone n="B7v" unit="sig"/>
<mw rend="align(left)" type="pageNum">14</mw>
	<lb/>which her Vanity perhaps, or it may be
	<lb/>the Commands and importunities of Re­
	<lb/>lations, wou'd not let her ſee before;
	<lb/>and now he has got <mcr>that</mcr> into his poſſeſſi­
	<lb/>on, ſhe muſt make court to him for a little
	<lb/>ſorry Alimony out of her own Eſtate.
	<lb/>If Diſcretion and Piety prevails upon her
	<lb/>Paſſions ſhe ſits down quietly, contented
	<lb/>with her lot, ſeeks no Conſolation in the
	<lb/>Multitude of Adorers, ſince he whom
	<lb/>only ſhe deſir'd to pleaſe, becauſe it was
	<lb/>her duty to do ſo, will take no delight in
	<lb/>her Wit or Beauty: She follows no Di­
	<lb/>verſion to allay her Grief, uſes no Cor­
	<lb/>dials to ſupport her Spirit, that may ſully
	<lb/>her Vertue or bring a Cloud upon her
	<lb/>Reputation, ſhe makes no appeals to the
	<lb/>miſ-judging Croud, hardly mentions her
	<lb/>Misfortunes to her moſt intimate Ac­
	<lb/>quaintance, nor lays a load on her Hus­
	<lb/>band to eaſe her ſelf, but wou'd if it
	<lb/>were poſſible conceal his Crimes, tho'
	<lb/>her Prudence and Vertue give him a
	<lb/>thouſand Reproaches without her Inten­
	<lb/>tion or knowledge; and retiring from
	<lb/>the World; ſhe ſeeks a more ſolid Com­
	<lb/>fort than it can give her, taking care to
	<lb/>do nothing that Cenſoriouſneſs or even
	<lb/>Malice itſelf can miſconſtrue to her pre­
	<lb/>judice. Now ſhe puts on all her Reſerves,
	<lb/>and thinks even innocent Liberties ſcarce
	  <mw type="catch">allow-</mw>

<pb n="15"/>
<milestone n="B8r" unit="sig"/>
<mw type="pageNum">15</mw>
	<lb/>allowable in her Diſconſolate State;
	<lb/>ſhe has other Buſineſs to mind: Nor
	<lb/>does ſhe in her Retirements reflect ſo
	<lb/>much upon the hand that adminiſters this
	<lb/>bitter Cup, as conſider what is the beſt
	<lb/>uſe ſhe can make of it. And thus indeed
	<lb/>Marriage, however unfortunate in other
	<lb/>reſpects, becomes a very great Bleſſing to
	<lb/>her. She might have been expoſed to all
	<lb/>the Temptations of a plentiful Fortune,
	<lb/>have given up her ſelf to Sloth and Luxu­
	<lb/>ry, and gone on at the common rate even
	<lb/>of the better ſort, in doing no hurt, and
	<lb/>as little good: But now her kind Hus­
	<lb/>band obliges her to <mcr>Conſider</mcr>, and gives
	<lb/>opportunity to exerciſe her Vertue; he
	<lb/>makes it neceſſary to withdraw from thoſe
	<lb/>Gaities and Pleaſures of Life, which do
	<lb/>more miſchief under the Shew of Inno­
	<lb/>cency, than they cou'd if they appear'd
	<lb/>attended with a Crime, diſcompoſing and
	<lb/>diſſolving the Mind, and making it un­
	<lb/>capable of any manner of good, to be ſure
	<lb/>of any thing Great and Excellent. Si­
	<lb/>lence and Solitude, the being forc'd from
	<lb/>the ordinary Entertainments of her Sta­
	<lb/>tion, may perhaps ſeem a deſolate condi­
	<lb/>tion at firſt, and we may allow her, poor
	<lb/>weak Woman! to be ſomewhat ſhock'd at
	<lb/>it, ſince even a wiſe and courageous Man
	<lb/>perhaps would not keep his ground. We
	  <mw type="catch">would</mw>

<pb n="16"/>
<milestone n="B8v" unit="sig"/>
<mw rend="align(left)" type="pageNum">16</mw>
	<lb/>would conceal if we could for the Ho­
	<lb/>nour of the Sex, Men's being baffled
	<lb/>and diſpirited by a ſmaller Matter, were
	<lb/>not the Inſtances too frequent and too no­
	<lb/>torious.</p>
        <p>But a little time wears off all the un­
	<lb/>eaſineſs, and puts her in poſſeſſion of Plea­
	<lb/>ſures, which till now ſhe has unkindly
	<lb/>been kept a ſtranger to. Affliction, the ſin­
	<lb/>cereſt Friend, the frankeſt Monitor, the
	<lb/>beſt Inſtructer, and indeed the only uſeful
	<lb/>School that Women are ever put to, rouſes
	<lb/>her underſtanding, opens her Eyes, fixes
	<lb/>her Attention, and diffuſes ſuch a Light,
	<lb/>ſuch a Joy into her Mind, as not only In­
	<lb/>forms her better, but Entertains her more
	<lb/>than ever her <mcr>Ruel</mcr> did tho' crouded by
	<lb/>the Men of Wit. She now diſtinguiſhes
	<lb/>between Truth and Appearances, between
	<lb/>ſolid and apparent Good; has found out
	<lb/>the inſtability of all Earthly Things, and
	<lb/>won't any more be deceiv'd by relying on
	<lb/>them; can diſcern who are the Flatter­
	<lb/>ers of her Fortune, and who the Admi­
	<lb/>rers and Encouragers of her Vertue; ac­
	<lb/>counting it no little bleſſing to be rid
	<lb/>of thoſe Leeches, who only hung upon
	<lb/>her for their own Advantage. Now ſo­
	<lb/>ber Thoughts ſucceed to hurry and imper­
	<lb/>tinence, to Forms and Ceremony, ſhe
	<lb/>can ſecure her Time, and knows how to
	  <mw type="catch">Improve</mw>

<pb n="17"/>
<milestone n="C1r" unit="sig"/>
<mw type="pageNum">17</mw>
	<lb/>Improve it; never truly a Happy Woman
	<lb/>till ſhe came in the Eye of the World to
	<lb/>be reckon'd Miſerable.</p>
        <p>Thus the Husband's Vices may become
	<lb/>an occaſion of the Wife's Vertues, and
	<lb/>his Neglect do her a more real Good than
	<lb/>his Kindneſs could. But all injur'd Wives
	<lb/>don't behave themſelves after this Faſhion,
	<lb/>nor can their Husbands juſtly expect it.
	<lb/>With what Face can he blame her for
	<lb/>following his Example, and being as ex­
	<lb/>travagant on the one Hand, as he is on
	<lb/>the other? Tho' ſhe cannot juſtifie her
	<lb/>Exceſſes to <mcr rend="slant(upright)case(allcaps)">God</mcr>, to the World, nor to
	<lb/>her ſelf, yet ſurely in reſpect of him they
	<lb/>may admit of an excuſe. For all the reſt
	<lb/>of his Abſurdities, (for Vice is always un­
	<lb/>reaſonable,) he adds one more, who ex­
	<lb/>pects that Vertue from another which he
	<lb/>won't practiſe himſelf</p>
        <p>But ſuppoſe a Man does not Marry for
	<lb/>Money, tho' for one that does not, perhaps
	<lb/>there are thouſands that do; let him Mar­
	<lb/>ry for Love, an Heroick Action, which
	<lb/>makes a mighty noiſe in the World, partly
	<lb/>becauſe of its rarity, and partly in regard
	<lb/>of its extravagancy, and what does his
	<lb/>Marrying for Love amount to? There's no
	<lb/>great odds between his Marrying for the
	<lb/>Love of Money, or for the Love of Beau­
	<lb/>ty, the Man does not act according to Rea­
	  <mw rend="align(center)" type="sig">C</mw>
	  <mw rend="break(no)" type="catch">ſon</mw>

<pb n="18"/>
<milestone n="C1v" unit="sig"/>
<mw rend="align(left)" type="pageNum">18</mw>
	<lb/>ſon in either Caſe, but is govern'd by ir­
	<lb/>regular Appetites. But he loves her Wit
	<lb/>perhaps, and this you'll ſay is more Spiri­
	<lb/>tual, more refin'd; not at all if you exa­
	<lb/>mine it to the Bottom. For what is that
	<lb/>which now adays paſſes under the name
	<lb/>of Wit? A bitter and ill-natur'd Rail­
	  <lb/>lery, a per<unclear reason="obscured">t</unclear> Repartée, or a confident talk­
	<lb/>ing at all, and in ſuch a multitude of
	<lb/>Words, it's odds if ſomething or other
	<lb/>does not paſs that is ſurprizing, tho' every
	<lb/>thing that ſurprizes does not pleaſe; ſome
	<lb/>things being wonder'd at for their Ugli­
	<lb/>neſs, as well as others for their Beauty.
	<lb/>True Wit, durſt one venture to deſcribe
	<lb/>it, is quite another thing, it conſiſts in
	<lb/>ſuch a Sprightlineſs of Imagination, ſuch
	<lb/>a reach and turn of thought, ſo properly ex­
	<lb/>preſt, as ſtrikes and pleaſes a judicious Taſt.
        	<lb/>For tho' as one ſays of Beauty, <quote source="b:IT01038">'tis in no
	<lb/>Face but in the Lover's Mind,</quote> ſo it may
	<lb/>be ſaid of ſome ſort of Wit, it is not in
	<lb/>him that ſpeaks, but in the Imagination
	<lb/>of his Hearer, yet doubtleſs there is a true
	<lb/>Standard-Wit, which muſt be allow'd for
	<lb/>ſuch by every one who underſtands the
	<lb/>Terms, I don't ſay that they ſhall <mcr>equally</mcr>
	<lb/>like it; and it is this Standard-Wit that
	<lb/>always pleaſes, the Spurious does ſo only
	<lb/>for a Seaſon.</p>
        <mw type="catch">Now</mw>
        <pb n="19"/>
        <milestone n="C2r" unit="sig"/>
        <mw type="pageNum">19</mw>
        <p>Now what is it that ſtrikes a judicious
	<lb/>Taſt? Not that to be ſure which injures
	<lb/>the abſent, or provokes the Company, which
	<lb/>poiſons the Mind under pretence of enter­
	<lb/>taining it, proceeding from or giving Coun­
	<lb/>tenance to falſe Ideas, to dangerous and
	<lb/>immoral Principles. Wit indeed is diſtinct
	<lb/>from Judgment, but it is not contrary to
	<lb/>it; 'tis rather its Handmaid, ſerving to a­
	<lb/>waken and fix the Attention, that ſo we
	<lb/>may Judge rightly. Whatever Charms, does
	<lb/>ſo becauſe of its Regularity and Propor­
	<lb/>tion; otherwiſe, tho' it is extraordinary
	<lb/>and out of the way, it will only be ſtar'd
	<lb/>on <ref xml:id="er9" type="correction" target="#ec9">like</ref> a Monſter, but can never be lik'd.
	<lb/>And tho' a thought is ever ſo fine and new,
	<lb/>ever ſo well expreſt, if it ſuits not with
	<lb/>Decorum and good Manners, it is not juſt
	<lb/>and fit, and therefore offends our Reaſon,
	<lb/>and conſequently has no Charms, nor
	<lb/>ſhould afford us any entertainment.</p>
        <p>But it muſt not be ſuppos'd that Women's
	<lb/>Wit approaches thoſe heights which Men
	<lb/>arrive at, or that they indulge thoſe Li­
	<lb/>berties the other take. Decency lays great­
	<lb/>er reſtraints on them, their timorouſneſs
	<lb/>does them this one, and perhaps this only
	<lb/>piece of Service, it keeps them from break­
	<lb/>ing thro' thoſe reſtraints, and following
	<lb/>their Maſters and Guides in many of their
	<lb/>daring and maſculine Crimes. As the
	  <mw rend="align(center)" type="sig">C2</mw>
          <mw rend="break(no)" type="catch">World</mw>

<pb n="20"/>
<milestone n="C2v" unit="sig"/>
<mw rend="align(left)" type="pageNum">20</mw>
	<lb/>World goes, your Witty Men are uſually
	<lb/>diſtinguiſh'd by the Liberty they take
	<lb/>with Religion, good Manners, or their
	<lb/>Neighbour's Reputation: But, <mcr rend="slant(upright)case(allcaps)">God</mcr> be
	<lb/>thank'd, it is not yet ſo bad, as that Wo­
	<lb/>men ſhould form Cabals to propagate Athe­
	<lb/>iſm and Irreligion. A Man then cannot
	<lb/>hope to find a Woman whoſe Wit is of a
	<lb/>ſize with his, but when he doats on Wit
	<lb/>it is to be imagin'd he makes choice of
	<lb/>that which comes the neareſt to his own.</p>
        <p>Thus, whether it be Wit or Beauty that
	<lb/>a Man's in Love with, there's no great
	<lb/>hopes of a laſting Happineſs; Beauty with
	<lb/>all the helps of Art is of no long date,
	<lb/>the more it is help'd the ſooner it decays,
	<lb/>and he who only or chiefly choſe for Beau­
	<lb/>ty, will in a little time find the ſame rea­
	<lb/>ſon for another Choice. Nor is that ſort
	<lb/>of Wit which he prefers of a more ſure
	<lb/>tenure, or allowing it to laſt, it will not
	<lb/>always pleaſe. For that which has not a
	<lb/>real excellency and value in it ſelf, enter­
	<lb/>tains no longer than that giddy Humour
	<lb/>which recommended it to us holds; and
	<lb/>when we can like on no juſt, or on very
	<lb/>little Ground,<choice><sic/><corr> </corr></choice>tis certain a diſlike will a­
	<lb/>riſe, as lightly and as unaccountably. And
	<lb/>it is not improbable that ſuch a Huſband
	<lb/>may in a little time by ill uſage provoke
	<lb/>ſuch a Wife to exerciſe her Wit, that is, 
	  <mw type="catch">her</mw>

<pb n="21"/>
<milestone n="C3r" unit="sig"/>
<mw type="pageNum">21</mw>
	<lb/>her Spleen on him, and then it is not hard
	<lb/>to gueſs how very agreeable it will be to
	<lb/>him.</p>
        <p>In a word, when we have reckon'd up
	<lb/>how many look no further than the making
	<lb/>of their Fortune, as they call it; who
	<lb/>don't ſo much as propoſe to themſelves
	<lb/>any ſatisfaction in the Woman to whom
	<lb/>they Plight their Faith, ſeeking only to
	<lb/>be Maſters of her Eſtate, that ſo they may
	<lb/>have Money enough to indulge all their ir­
	<lb/>regular Appetites; who think they are as
	<lb/>good as can be expected, if they are but
	<lb/>according to the faſhionable Term, <mcr>Civil
	<lb/>Husbands</mcr>; when we have taken the num­
	<lb/>ber of your giddy Lovers, who are not
	<lb/>more violent in their Paſſion than they
	<lb/>are certain to Repent of it; when to theſe
	<lb/>you have added ſuch as Marry without
	<lb/>any Thought at all, further than that it is
	<lb/>the Cuſtom of the World, what others
	<lb/>have done before them, that the Family
	<lb/>muſt be kept up, the ancient Race preſerv'd,
	<lb/>and therefore their kind Parents and Guar­
	<lb/>dians chuſe as they think convenient, with­
	<lb/>out ever conſulting the Young ones Incli­
	<lb/>nations, who muſt be ſatisfied or pretend
	<lb/>ſo at leaſt, upon pain of their diſpleaſure,
	<lb/>and that heavy conſequence of it, forfei­
	<lb/>ture of their Eſtate: Theſe ſet aſide, I
	<lb/>fear there will be but a ſmall remainder to
	  <mw rend="align(center)" type="sig">C3</mw>
	  <mw rend="break(no)" type="catch">Marry</mw>

<pb n="22"/>
<milestone n="C3v" unit="sig"/>
<mw rend="align(left)" type="pageNum">22</mw>
	<lb/>Marry out of better conſiderations, and
	<lb/>even amongſt the few that do, not one in
	<lb/>a hundred takes care to deſerve his
	<lb/>Choice.</p>
        <p>But do the Women never chuſe amiſs?
	<lb/>Are the Men only in fault? that is not
	<lb/>pretended; for he who will be juſt, muſt
	<lb/>be forc'd to acknowledge, that neither Sex
	<lb/>are always in the right. A Woman indeed
	<lb/>can't properly be ſaid to Chooſe, all that
	<lb/>is allow'd her, is to Refuſe or Accept what
	<lb/>is offer'd. And when we have made ſuch
	<lb/>reaſonable allowances as are due to the Sex,
	<lb/>perhaps they may not appear ſo much in
	<lb/>fault as one would at firſt imagine, and
	<lb/>a generous Spirit will find more occaſion
	<lb/>to pity, than to reprove. But ſure I tranſ­
	<lb/>greſs ―― it muſt not be ſuppos'd that the
	<lb/>Ladies can do amiſs! he is but an ill-bred
	<lb/>Fellow who pretends that they need a­
	<lb/>mendment! They are no doubt on't al­
	<lb/>ways in the right, and moſt of all when
	<lb/>they take pity on diſtreſſed Lovers! what­
	<lb/>ever they <mcr>ſay</mcr> carries an Authority that no
	<lb/>Reaſon can reſiſt, and all that they <mcr>do</mcr> muſt
	<lb/>needs be Exemplary! This is the Modiſh
	<lb/>Language, nor is there a Man of Honour
	<lb/>amongſt the whole Tribe that would not
	<lb/>venture his Life, nay and his Salvation too
	<lb/>in their Defence, if any but himſelf at­
	<lb/>tempts to injure them. But I muſt ask par­
	  <mw type="catch">don</mw>

<pb n="23"/>
<milestone n="C4r" unit="sig"/>
<mw type="pageNum">23</mw>
	<lb/>don if I can't come up to theſe heights, nor
	<lb/>flatter them with the having no faults, which
	<lb/>is only a malicious way of continuing and
	<lb/>encreaſing their Miſtakes.</p>
        <p>Women, it's true, ought to be treated
	<lb/>with Civility; for ſince a little Ceremony
	<lb/>and out-ſide Reſpect is all thier Guard, all
	<lb/>the privilege that's allow'd them, it were
	<lb/>barbarous to deprive them of it; and be­
	<lb/>cauſe I would treat them civilly, I would
	<lb/>not expreſs my Civility at the uſual rate.
	<lb/>I would not under pretence of honouring
	<lb/>and paying a mighty Deference to the La­
	<lb/>dies, call them fools to their faces; for
	<lb/>what are all the fine Speeches and Sub­
	<lb/>miſſions that are made, but an abuſing
	<lb/>them in a well-bred way? She muſt be a
	<lb/>Fool with a witneſs, who can believe a
	<lb/>Man, Proud and Vain as he is, will lay
	<lb/>his boaſted Authority, the Dignity and
	<lb/>Prerogative of his Sex, one Moment at
	<lb/>her Feet, but in proſpect of taking it up
	<lb/>again to more advantage; he may call
	<lb/>himſelf her Slave a few days, but it is on­
	<lb/>ly in order to make her his all the reſt of
	<lb/>his Life.</p>
        <p>Indeed that miſtaken Self-Love that
	<lb/>reigns in the moſt of us, both Men and
	<lb/>Women, that over-good Opinion we have
	<lb/>of our ſelves, and deſire that others ſhould
	<lb/>have of us, makes us ſwallow every thing
	  <mw rend="align(center)" type="sig">C4</mw>
	  <mw rend="break(no)" type="catch">that</mw>

<pb n="24"/>
<milestone n="C4v" unit="sig"/>
<mw rend="align(left)" type="pageNum">24</mw>
	<lb/>that looks like Reſpect, without examin­
	<lb/>ing how wide it is from what it appears
	<lb/>to be. For nothing is in truth a greater 
	<lb/>outrage than Flattery and feign'd Submiſ­
	<lb/>ſions, the plain <name rend="slant(upright)">Engliſh</name> of which is this,
	<lb/><said rend="bestow((pre(“))(lb))">I have a very mean Opinion both of your
	<lb/>Underſtanding and Vertue, you are
	<lb/>weak enough to be impos'd on, and vain
	<lb/>enough to ſnatch at the Bait I throw;
	<lb/>there's no danger of your finding out
	<lb/>my meaning, or diſappointing me of my
	<lb/>Ends. I offer you <mcr>Incenſe</mcr> 'tis true, but
	<lb/>you are like to pay for't, and to make
	<lb/>me a Recompence for your Folly in I­
	<lb/>magining I would give my ſelf this trou­
	<lb/>ble, did I not hope, nay were I not ſure,
	<lb/>to find my own account in it. If for
	<lb/>nothing elſe, you'll ſerve at leaſt as an
	<lb/>exerciſe of my Wit, and how much ſo­
	<lb/>ever you ſwell with my Breath, 'tis I de­
	<lb/>ſerve the Praiſe for talking ſo well on ſo
	<lb/>poor a Subject. We who make the Idols,
	<lb/>are the greater Deities; and as we ſet
	<lb/>you up, ſo it is in our power to reduce
	<lb/>you to your firſt obſcurity, or to ſome­
	<lb/>what worſe, to Contempt; you are there­
	<lb/>fore only on your good behaviour, and
	<lb/>are like to be no more than what we
	<lb/>pleaſe to make you.</said> This is the Flat­
	<lb/>terer's Language aſide, this is the true ſenſe
	<lb/>of his heart, whatever his Grimace may be
	<lb/>before the Company.</p>
        <mw type="catch">Not</mw>
        <pb n="25"/>
        <milestone n="C5r" unit="sig"/>
        <mw type="pageNum">25</mw>
        <p>Not but that 'tis poſſible, and ſome­
	<lb/>times matter of Fact, to expreſs our ſelves
	<lb/>beyond the Truth in praiſe of a Perſon,
	<lb/>and yet not be guilty of Flattery; but
	<lb/>then we muſt Think what we Say, and
	<lb/>Mean what we Profeſs. We may be ſo
	<lb/>blinded by ſome Paſſion or other, eſpeci­
	<lb/>ally Love, which in Civil and Good-na­
	<lb/>tur'd Perſons is apt to exceed, as to believe
	<lb/>ſome Perſons more deſerving than really
	<lb/>they are, and to pay them greater Re­
	<lb/>ſpect and Kindneſs than is in ſtrictneſs due
	<lb/>to them. But this is not the preſent Caſe;
	<lb/>for our fine Speech-makers doat too much
	<lb/>on themſelves to have any great paſſion
	<lb/>for another, their Eyes are too much fixt
	<lb/>on their own Excellencies, to view an­
	<lb/>other's good Qualities through a magnify­
	<lb/>ing Glaſs; or at leaſt, if ever they turn
	<lb/>that end of their Perſpective towards their
	<lb/>Neighbours, 'tis only in reſpect and re­
	<lb/>ference to themſelves. They are their own
	<lb/>Centres, they find a diſproportion in every
	<lb/>line that does not tend thither, and in
	<lb/>the next viſit they make, you ſhall hear
	<lb/>all the fine things they had ſaid repeated
	<lb/>to the new Object, and nothing remem­
	<lb/>bred of the former but her Vanity, or ſome­
	<lb/>thing elſe as Ridiculous, which ſerves for
	<lb/>a foil, or a whet to Diſcourſe. For let
	<lb/>there be ever ſo many Wits in the Com­
	  <mw type="catch">pany,</mw>

<pb n="26"/>
<milestone n="C5v" unit="sig"/>
<mw rend="align(left)" type="pageNum">26</mw>
	<lb/>pany, Converſation would languiſh, and
	<lb/>they would be at a loſs, did not a little
	<lb/>Cenſoriouſneſs come in at a need to help
	<lb/>them.</p>
        <p>Let us then treat the Ladies as Civilly
	<lb/>as may be, but let us not do it by Flat­
	<lb/>tering them, but by endeavouring to make
	<lb/>them ſuch as may truly deſerve our hear­
	<lb/>ty Eſteem and Kindneſs. Men ought re­
	<lb/>ally for their own ſakes to do what in them
	<lb/>lies to make Women Wiſe and Good, and
	<lb/>then it might be hoped they themſelves
	<lb/>would effectually Study and Practiſe that 
	<lb/>Wiſdom and Vertue they recommend to
	<lb/>others. But ſo long as Men have baſe and
	<lb/>unworthy Ends to ſerve, it is not to be ex­
	<lb/>pected that they ſhould conſent to ſuch
	<lb/>Methods as would certainly diſappoint
	<lb/>them. They would have their own Rela­
	<lb/>tions do well, it is their Intereſt; but it
	<lb/>ſometimes happens to be for their turn that 
	<lb/>another Man's ſhould not, and then their
	<lb/>Generoſity fails them, and no Man is apter
	<lb/>to find fault with another's diſhonourable
	<lb/>Actions, than he who is ready to do, or
	<lb/>perhaps has done the ſame himſelf.</p>
        <p>And as Men have little reaſon to expect
	<lb/>Happineſs when they Marry only for the
	<lb/>Love of Money, Wit or Beauty, as has
	<lb/>been already ſhewn, ſo much leſs can a
	<lb/>Woman expect a tolerable life, when ſhe
	  <mw type="catch">goes</mw>

	  
<pb n="27"/>
<milestone n="C6r" unit="sig"/>
<mw type="pageNum">27</mw>
	<lb/>goes upon theſe Conſiderations. Let the
	<lb/>buſineſs be carried as Prudently as it can be
	<lb/>on the Woman's ſide, a reaſonable Man
	<lb/>can't deny that ſhe has by much the harder 
	<lb/>bargain. Becauſe ſhe puts her ſelf entirely
	<lb/>into her Huſband's Power, and if the
	<lb/>Matrimonial Yoke be grievous, neither
	<lb/>Law nor Cuſtom afford her that redreſs
	<lb/>which a Man obtains. He who has Sove­
	<lb/>reign Power does not value the Provoca­
	<lb/>tions of a Rebellious Subject, but knows
	<lb/>how to ſubdue him with eaſe, and will
	<lb/>make himſelf obey'd; but Patience and
	<lb/>Submiſſion are the only Comforts that are
	<lb/>left to a poor People, who groan under
	<lb/>Tyranny, unleſs they are Strong enough
	<lb/>to break the Yoke, to Depoſe and Abdi­
	<lb/>cate, which I doubt wou'd not be allow'd
	<lb/>of here. For whatever may be ſaid againſt
	<lb/>Paſſive-Obedience in another caſe, I ſup­
	<lb/>poſe there's no Man but likes it very well
	<lb/>in this; how much ſoever Arbitrary Pow­
	<lb/>er may be diſlik'd on a Throne, not <persName ref="p:jmilton.kta">Mil­
	<lb/>ton</persName> himſelf wou'd cry up Liberty to poor
	<lb/><mcr>Female Slaves</mcr>, or plead for the Lawfulneſs
	<lb/>of Reſiſting a Private Tyranny.</p>
        <p>If there be a diſagreeableneſs of Hu­
	<lb/>mours, this in my mind is harder to be
	<lb/>born than greater faults, as being a conti­
	<lb/>nual Plague, and for the moſt part incura­
	<lb/>ble; other Vices a Man may grow weary
	  <mw type="catch">of,</mw>

<pb n="28"/>
<milestone n="C6v" unit="sig"/>
<mw rend="align(left)" type="pageNum">28</mw>
	<lb/>of, or may be convinced of the evil of 
	<lb/>them, he may forſake them, or they him,
	<lb/>but his Humour and Temper are ſeldom,
	<lb/>if ever put off, Ill-nature ſticks to him
	<lb/>from his Youth to his grey Hairs, and a
	<lb/>Boy that's Humorous and Proud, makes <choice><sic>a</sic><corr/></choice>
	<lb/>a Peeviſh, Poſitive and Inſolent Old Man.
	<lb/>Now if this be the caſe, and the Husband
	<lb/>be full of himſelf, obſtinately bent on his
	<lb/>own way with or without Reaſon, if he be
	<lb/>one who muſt be always Admir'd, always
	<lb/>Humour'd, and yet ſcarce knows what
	<lb/>will pleaſe him, if he has Proſperity e­
	<lb/>nough to keep him from conſidering, and
	<lb/>to furniſh him with a train of Flatterers
	<lb/>and obſequious Admirers; and Learning
	<lb/>and Senſe enough to make him a Fop in
	<lb/>Perfection; for a Man can never be a com­
	<lb/>plete Coxcomb, unleſs he has a conſider­
	<lb/>able ſhare of theſe to value himſelf upon;
	<lb/>what can the poor Woman do? the Huſ­
	<lb/>band is too wiſe to be Advis'd, too good
	<lb/>to be Reform'd, ſhe muſt follow all his
	<lb/>Paces, and tread in all his unreaſonable
	<lb/>ſteps, or there is no Peace, no Quiet for
	<lb/>her, ſhe muſt obey with the greateſt exact­
	<lb/>neſs, 'tis in vain to expect any manner of
	<lb/>Compliance on his ſide, and the more ſhe
	<lb/>complies the more ſhe may; his fantaſti­
	<lb/>cal humours grow with her deſire to gra­
	<lb/>tifie them, for Age encreaſes Opiniatry in
	  <mw type="catch">ſome,</mw>

<pb n="29"/>
<milestone n="C7r" unit="sig"/>
<mw type="pageNum">29</mw>
	<lb/>ſome, as well as it does Experience in o­
	<lb/>thers. Of ſuch ſort of folks as theſe it was
        	<lb/>that <persName ref="p:solomon.yer">Solomon</persName> ſpake, when he ſaid, <quote source="b:IT50070">Seeſt
	<lb/>thou a Man wiſe in his own conceit, there
	<lb/>is more hope of a Fool than of him</quote>; That is,
	<lb/>the profligate Sinner, ſuch a one being al­
	<lb/>ways a Fool in <persName ref="p:solomon.yer">Solomon's</persName> Language, is in
	<lb/>a fairer way of being convinc'd of his
	<lb/>Folly, and brought to Reaſon, than the
	<lb/>Proud Conceited Man. That Man indeed
	<lb/>can never be good at heart, who is full of
	<lb/>himſelf and his own Endowments. Not
	<lb/>that it is neceſſary becauſe it is not poſſi­
	<lb/>ble for one to be totally ignorant of his 
	<lb/>own good Qualities. I had almoſt ſaid he
	<lb/><emph>ought</emph> to have a Modeſt ſenſe of 'em, other­
	<lb/>wiſe he can't be duly thankful, nor make
	<lb/>the uſe of them that is required, to the
	<lb/>Glory of God, and the good of Mankind;
	<lb/>but he views them in a wrong light, if he
	<lb/>diſcerns any thing that may exalt him a­
	<lb/>bove his Neighbours, make him over-look
	<lb/>their Merit, or treat them with Neglect
	<lb/>or Contempt. He ought to behold his Ad­
	<lb/>vantages with fear and trembling, as Ta­
	<lb/>lents which he has freely receiv'd, and for
	<lb/>which he is highly Accountable, and there­
	<lb/>fore they ſhou'd not excite his Pride, but 
	<lb/>his Care and Induſtry.</p>
        <p>And if Pride and Self-conceit keep a
	<lb/>Man who has ſome good Qualities, and is
	  <mw type="catch">not</mw>
<pb n="30"/>
<milestone n="C7v" unit="sig"/>
<mw rend="align(left)" type="pageNum">30</mw>
	<lb/>not ſo bad as the moſt of his Neighbours,
	<lb/>from growing better, it for certain con­
	<lb/>firms and hardens the Wicked in his
	<lb/>Crimes, it ſets him up for a Wit, that is,
	<lb/>according to Modern acceptation, one
	<lb/>who rallies all that is ſerious, a Contem­
	<lb/>ner of the Prieſts firſt, and then of the De­
	<lb/>ity Himſelf. For Penitence and Self-con­
	<lb/>demnation are what his Haughtineſs can­
	<lb/>not bear, and ſince his Crimes have brought
	<lb/>upon him the reproaches of his own Mind,
	<lb/>ſince he will not take the regular way to
	<lb/>be rid of them, which is by Humbling
	<lb/>himſelf and making his Peace with <placeName rend="slant(upright)">Hea­
	<lb/>ven</placeName>, he bids defiance to it, and wou'd if
	<lb/>he could believe there is no future State,
	<lb/>no after Retribution, becauſe he knows
	<lb/>that a heavy lot is in juſtice due to him.</p>
        <p>If therefore it is a Woman's hard Fate
	<lb/>to meet with a diſagreeable Temper, and
	<lb/>of all others the Haughty, Imperious and
	<lb/>Self-conceited are the moſt ſo, ſhe is as
	<lb/>unhappy as any thing in this World can
	<lb/>make her. For when a Wife's Temper
	<lb/>does not pleaſe, if ſhe makes her Huſband
	<lb/>uneaſie, he can find entertainments abroad,
	<lb/>he has a hundred ways of relieving him­
	<lb/>ſelf, but neither Prudence nor Duty will
	<lb/>allow a Woman to fly out, her Buſineſs
	<lb/>and Entertainment are at home, and tho'
	  <mw type="catch">he</mw>

<pb n="31"/>
<milestone n="C8r" unit="sig"/>
<mw type="pageNum">31</mw>
	<lb/>he makes it ever ſo uneaſie to her ſhe muſt
	<lb/>be content and make her beſt on't. She
	<lb/>who Elects a Monarch for Life, who gives
	<lb/>him an Authority ſhe cannot recall how­
	<lb/>ever he miſapply it, who puts her Fortune
	<lb/>and Perſon entirely in his Power; nay even
	<lb/>the very deſires of her Heart according to
	<lb/>ſome learned Caſuiſts, ſo as that it is not
	<lb/>lawful to Will or Deſire any thing but
	<lb/>what he approves and allows; had need be
	<lb/>very ſure that ſhe does not make a Fool her
	<lb/>Head, nor a Vicious Man her Guide and
	<lb/>Pattern, ſhe had beſt ſtay till ſhe can meet
	<lb/>with one who has the Government of his
	<lb/>own Paſſions, and has duly regulated his
	<lb/>own Deſires, ſince he is to have ſuch an
	<lb/>abſolute Power over hers. But he who
	<lb/>doats on a Face, he who makes Money
	<lb/>his Idol, he who<choice><sic>-</sic><corr/></choice> is Charm'd with vain
	<lb/>and empty Wit, gives no ſuch Evidence,
	<lb/>either of Wiſdom or Goodneſs, that a Wo­
	<lb/>man of any tolerable Senſe ſhou'd care to
	<lb/>venture her ſelf to his Conduct.</p>
        <p>Indeed, your fine Gentleman's Actions
	<lb/>are now adays ſuch, that did not Cuſtom
	<lb/>and the Dignity of his Sex give Weight
	<lb/>and Authority to them, a Woman that 
	<lb/>thinks twice might bleſs her ſelf, and ſay,
	<lb/>is this the Lord and Maſter to whom I am
	<lb/>to promiſe Love, Honour and Obedience?
	<lb/>What can be the object of Love but ami­
	  <mw type="catch">able</mw>

<pb n="32"/>
<milestone n="C8v" unit="sig"/>
<mw rend="align(left)" type="pageNum">32</mw>
	<lb/>able Qualities, the Image of the Deity
	<lb/>impreſs'd upon a generous and God-like
	<lb/>Mind, a Mind that is above this World,
	<lb/>to be ſure above all the Vices, the Tricks
	<lb/>and Baſeneſs of it; a Mind that is not full
	<lb/>of it ſelf, nor contracted to little private
	<lb/>Intereſts, but which in Imitation of that
	<lb/>glorious Pattern it endeavours to Copy af­
	<lb/>ter, expands and diffuſes it ſelf to its ut­
	<lb/>moſt capacity in doing Good? But this fine
	<lb/>Gentleman is quite of another Strain, he is
	<lb/>the reverſe of this in every Inſtance. He
	<lb/>is I confeſs very fond of his own Dear Per­
	<lb/>ſon, he ſees very much in it to admire;
	<lb/>his Air and Mien, his Words and Actions,
	<lb/>every Motion he makes declares it; but
	<lb/>they muſt have a Judgment of his ſize, every
	<lb/>whit as Shallow, and a Partiality as great
	<lb/>as his own, who can be of his Mind. How
	<lb/>then can I Love? And if not Love, much
	<lb/>leſs Honour. Love may ariſe from Pity or
	<lb/>a generous Deſire to make that Lovely
	<lb/>which as yet is not ſo, when we ſee any
	<lb/>hopes of Succeſs in our Endeavours of im­
	<lb/>proving it; but Honour ſuppoſes ſome
	<lb/>excellent Qualities already, ſomething
	<lb/>worth our Eſteem, <ref xml:id="er10" type="correction" target="#ec10">but</ref> alas there is nothing
	<lb/>more contemptible than this trifle of a Man,
	<lb/>this meer Out-ſide, whoſe Mind is as baſe
	<lb/>and Mean as his external Pomp is Glitter­
	<lb/>ing. His Office or Title apart, to which
	  <mw type="catch">ſome</mw>

<pb n="33"/>
<milestone n="D1r" unit="sig"/>
<mw type="pageNum">33</mw>
	<lb/>ſome Ceremonious Obſervance muſt be paid
	<lb/>for Order's ſake, there's nothing in him
	<lb/>that can command our Reſpect. Strip
	<lb/>him of Equipage and Fortune, and ſuch
	<lb/>things as only dazle our Eyes and Imagi­
	<lb/>nations, but don't in any meaſure affect
	<lb/>our Reaſon, or cauſe a Reverence in our
	<lb/>Hearts, and the poor Creature ſinks be­
	<lb/>neath our Notice, becauſe not ſupported
	<lb/>by real Worth. And if a Woman can
	<lb/>neither Love nor Honour, ſhe does ill in
	<lb/>promiſing to Obey, ſince ſhe is like to have 
	<lb/>but a crooked Rule to regulate her Actions.</p>
        <p>A meer Obedience, ſuch as is paid only 
	<lb/>to Authority, and not out of Love and a
	<lb/>ſenſe of the Juſtice and Reaſonableneſs of
	<lb/>the Command, will be of an uncertain
	<lb/>Tenure. As it can't but be uneaſie to the
	<lb/>Perſon who pays it, ſo he who 
            <ref xml:id="er11" type="correction" target="#ec11">receives</ref> it
	<lb/>will be ſometimes diſappointed when he
	<lb/>expects to find it; for that Woman muſt 
	<lb/>be endow'd with a Wiſdom and Good­
	<lb/>neſs much above what we ſuppoſe the Sex
	<lb/>capable of, I fear much greater than e're
	<lb/>a Man can pretend to, who can ſo con­
	<lb/>ſtantly conquer her Paſſions, and diveſt
	<lb/>her ſelf even of Innocent Self-Love, as to
	<lb/>give up the Cauſe when ſhe is in the
	<lb/>right, and to ſubmit her enlightned Rea­
	<lb/>ſon, to the Imperious Dictates of a blind
	<lb/>Will, and wild Imagination, even when
	  <mw rend="align(center)" type="sig">D</mw>
	  <mw rend="break(no)" type="catch">ſhe</mw>

<pb n="34"/>
<milestone n="D1v" unit="sig"/>
<mw rend="align(left)" type="pageNum">34</mw>
	<lb/>ſhe clearly perceives the ill Conſequences
	<lb/>of it, the Imprudence, nay Folly and Mad­
	<lb/>neſs of ſuch a Conduct.</p>
        <p>And if a Woman runs ſuch a Riſque
	<lb/>when ſhe Marries Prudently according to
	<lb/>the Opinion of the World, that is, when
	<lb/>ſhe permits her ſelf to be diſpos'd of to a
	<lb/>Man equal to her in Birth, Education
	<lb/>and Fortune, and as good as the moſt of
	<lb/>his Neighbours, (for if none were to
	<lb/>Marry, but Men of ſtrict Vertue and
	<lb/>Honour, I doubt the World would be but
	<lb/>thinly peopled) if at the very beſt her
	<lb/>Lot is hard, what can ſhe expect who is
	<lb/>Sold, or any otherwiſe betray'd into mer­
	<lb/>cenary Hands, to one who is in all, or
	<lb/>moſt reſpects unequal to her? A Lover
	<lb/>who comes upon what is call'd equal
	<lb/>Terms, makes no very advantageous Pro­
	<lb/>poſal to the Lady he Courts, and to whom
	<lb/>he ſeems to be an humble Servant. For
	<lb/>under many founding Compliments,
	<lb/>Words that have nothing in them, this is
	<lb/>his true meaning, he wants one to manage 
	<lb/>his Family, an Houſe-keeper, a neceſ­
	<lb/>ſary Evil, one whoſe Intereſt it will be
	<lb/>not to wrong him, and in whom there­
	<lb/>fore he can put greater confidence than in
	<lb/>any he can hire for Money. One who
	<lb/>may breed his Children, taking all the
	<lb/>care and trouble of their Education, to
	  <mw type="catch">preſerve</mw>

<pb n="35"/>
<milestone n="D2r" unit="sig"/>
<mw type="pageNum">35</mw>
	<lb/>preſerve his Name and Family. One whoſe
	<lb/>Beauty, Wit, or good Humour and a­
	<lb/>greeable Converſation, will entertain
	<lb/>him at Home when he has been contra­
	<lb/>dicted and diſappointed abroad; who will
	<lb/>do him that Juſtice the ill-natur'd World
	<lb/>denies him, that is, in any one's Language
	<lb/>but his own, ſooth his Pride and Flatter
	<lb/>his Vanity, by having always ſo much
	<lb/>good Senſe as to be on his ſide, to conclude
	<lb/>him in the right, when others are ſo Igno­
	<lb/>rant, or ſo rude as to deny it. Who will
	<lb/>not be Blind to his Merit nor Contradict
	<lb/>his Will and Pleaſure, but make it her
	<lb/>Buſineſs, her very Ambition to content
	<lb/>him; whoſe ſoftneſs and gentle Compli­
	<lb/>ance will calm his Paſſions, to whom
	<lb/>he may ſafely diſcloſe his troubleſome
	<lb/>Thoughts, and in her Breaſt diſcharge
	<lb/>his Cares; whoſe Duty, Submiſſion and
	<lb/>Obſervance, will heal thoſe Wounds other
	<lb/>Peoples oppoſition or neglect have given
	<lb/>him. In a word, one whom he can intirely
	<lb/>Govern, and conſequently may form her
	<lb/>to his will and liking, who muſt be his
	<lb/><ref xml:id="er12" type="correction" target="#ec12">of</ref> Life, and therefore cannot 
            quit his Ser­
	<lb/>vice let him treat her how he will.</p>
        <p>And if this be what every Man expects,
	<lb/>the Sum of his violent Love and Court­
	<lb/>ſhip, when it is put into Senſe and ren­
	<lb/>dred Intelligible, to what a fine paſs does
	  <mw rend="align(center)" type="sig">D2</mw>
	  <mw rend="break(no)" type="catch">ſhe</mw>
	  
<pb n="36"/>
<milestone n="D2v" unit="sig"/>
<mw rend="align(left)" type="pageNum">36</mw>
	<lb/>ſhe bring her ſelf who purchaſes a Lord
	<lb/>and Maſter, not only with her Money,
	<lb/>but with what is of greater Value, at the
	<lb/>price of her Diſcretion? Who has not ſo
	<lb/>much as that poor Excuſe, Precedent and
	<lb/>Example; or if ſhe has, they are only
	<lb/>ſuch as all the World condemns? She will
	<lb/>not find him leſs a Governor becauſe ſhe
	<lb/>was once his Superior, on the contrary the
	<lb/>ſcum of the People are moſt Tyrannical
	<lb/>when they get the Power, and treat their
	<lb/>Betters with the greateſt Inſolence. For as
	<lb/>the wiſe Man long ſince obſerv'd, a Ser­
	<lb/>vant when he Reigns is one of thoſe things
	<lb/>for which the <placeName rend="slant(upright)">Earth</placeName> is diſquieted, and
	<lb/>which no body is able to bear.</p>
        <p>It is the hardeſt thing in the World for
	<lb/>a Woman to know that a Man is not Mer­
	<lb/>cenary, that he does not Act on baſe and
	<lb/>ungenerous Principles, even when he is
	<lb/>her Equal, becauſe being abſolute Maſter,
	<lb/>ſhe and all the Grants he makes her are
	<lb/>in his Power, and there have been but
	<lb/>too many inſtances of Huſbands that by
	<lb/>wheedling or threatning their Wives, by
	<lb/>ſeeming Kindneſs or cruel Uſage, have
	<lb/>perſwaded or forc'd them out of what has
	<lb/>been ſettled on them. So that the Wo­
	<lb/>man has in truth no ſecurity but the Man's
	<lb/>Honour and Good-nature, a Security that
	<lb/>in this preſent Age no wiſe Perſon would
	  <mw type="catch">ven-</mw>

	  
<pb n="37"/>
<milestone n="D3r" unit="sig"/>
<mw type="pageNum">37</mw>
	<lb/>venture much upon. A Man enters into
	<lb/>Articles very readily before Marriage,
	<lb/>and ſo he may, for he performs no more
	<lb/>of them afterwards than he thinks fit.
	<lb/>A Wife muſt never diſpute with her Hus­
	<lb/>band, his Reaſons are now no doubt on't
	<lb/>better than hers, whatever they were be­
	<lb/>fore; he is ſure to perſwade her out of
	<lb/>her Agreement, and bring her, it muſt
	<lb/>be ſuppos'd, <mcr>Willingly</mcr>, to give up what ſhe
	<lb/>did vainly hope to obtain, and what ſhe
	<lb/>thought had been made ſure to her. And
	<lb/>if ſhe ſhews any Refractorineſs, there are
	<lb/>ways enough to humble her; ſo that by
	<lb/>right or wrong the Huſband gains his Will.
	<lb/>For Covenants betwixt Huſband and
	<lb/>Wife, like Laws in an Arbitrary Govern­
	<lb/>ment, are of little Force, the Will of the
	<lb/>Sovereign is all in all. Thus it is in Mat­
	<lb/>ter of Fact, I will not anſwer for the
	<lb/>Right of it; for if the Woman's Reaſons
	<lb/>upon which thoſe Agreements are groun­
	<lb/>ded are not Juſt and Good, why did he
	<lb/>conſent to them? Was it becauſe there
	<lb/>was no other way to obtain his Suit, and
	<lb/>with an Intention to Annul them when
	<lb/>it ſhall be in his Power? Where then is
	<lb/>his Sincerity? But if her Reaſons are
	<lb/>good, where is his Juſtice in obliging her
	<lb/>to quit them? He neither way acts like
	<lb/>an equitable or honeſt Man.</p>
        <mw rend="align(center)" type="sig">D3</mw>
        <mw rend="break(no)" type="catch">But</mw>
        <pb n="38"/>
        <milestone n="D3v" unit="sig"/>
        <mw rend="align(left)" type="pageNum">38</mw>
        <p>But when a Woman Marrys unequally
	<lb/>and beneath her ſelf, there is almoſt De­
	<lb/>monſtration that the Man is Sordid and
	<lb/>Unfair, that inſtead of Loving her he
	<lb/>only Loves himſelf, trapans and ruines
	<lb/>her to ſerve his own Ends. For if he had
	<lb/>not a mighty Opinion of himſelf, (which
	<lb/>temper is like to make an admirable Hus­
	<lb/>band,) he cou'd never imagine that his
	<lb/>Perſon and good Qualities ſhould make
	<lb/>compenſation for all the advantages ſhe
	<lb/>quits on his account. If he had a real
	<lb/>Eſteem for her or valu'd her Reputation,
	<lb/>he wou'd not expoſe it, nor have her
	<lb/>Diſcretion call'd in Queſtion for his ſake;
	<lb/>and if he truly Lov'd her he wou'd not
	<lb/>reduce her to Straits and a narrow For­
	<lb/>tune, nor ſo much as leſſen her way of
	<lb/>Living to better his own. For ſince <mcr rend="slant(upright)case(allcaps)">God</mcr>
	<lb/>has plac'd different Ranks in the World,
	<lb/>put ſome in a higher and ſome in a lower
	<lb/>Station, for Order and Beauty's ſake, and
	<lb/>for many good Reaſons; tho' it is both
	<lb/>our Wiſdom and Duty not only to ſub­
	<lb/>mit with Patience, but to be Thankful
	<lb/>and well-ſatisfied when by his Providence
	<lb/>we are brought low, yet there is no man­
	<lb/>ner of Reaſon for us to Degrade our
	<lb/>ſelves; on the contrary, much why we
	<lb/>ought not. The better our Lot is in this
	<lb/>World and the more we have of it, the
	  <mw type="catch">greater</mw>

<pb n="39"/>
<milestone n="D4r" unit="sig"/>
<mw type="pageNum">39</mw>
	<lb/>greater is our leiſure to prepare for the
	<lb/>next; we have the more opportunity to
	<lb/>exerciſe that God-like Quality, to taſt
	<lb/>that Divine Pleaſure, Doing good to the
	<lb/>Bodies and Souls of thoſe beneath us. Is it
	<lb/>not then ill Manners to Heaven, and an
	<lb/>irreligious contempt of its Favours, for a
	<lb/>Woman to ſlight that nobler Employment,
	<lb/>to which it has aſſign'd her, and thruſt
	<lb/>her ſelf down to a meaner Drudgery, to
	<lb/>what is in the very literal Senſe a ca­
	<lb/>ring for the things of the World, a ca­
	<lb/>ring not only to pleaſe, but to maintain
	<lb/>a Huſband?</p>
        <p>And a Huſband ſo choſen will not at
	<lb/>all abate of his Authority and Right to
	<lb/>Govern, whatever fair Promiſes he might
	<lb/>make before. She has made him her Head,
	<lb/>and he thinks himſelf as well qualify'd
	<lb/>as the beſt to Act accordingly, nor has
	<lb/>ſhe given him any ſuch Evidence of her
	<lb/>Prudence as may diſpoſe him to make an
	<lb/>Act of Grace in her Favour. Beſides,
	<lb/>great Obligations are what Superiors can­
	<lb/>not bear, they are more than can be re­
	<lb/>turn'd; to acknowledge, were only to re­
	<lb/>proach themſelves with ingratitude, and
	<lb/>therefore the readieſt way is not to own
	<lb/>but overlook them, or rather, as too ma­
	<lb/>ny do, to repay them with Affronts and
	<lb/>Injuries.</p>
        <mw rend="align(center)" type="sig">D4</mw>
        <mw rend="break(no)" type="catch">What</mw>
        <pb n="40"/>
        <milestone n="D4v" unit="sig"/>
        <mw rend="align(left)" type="pageNum">40</mw>
        <p>What then is to be done? How muſt
	<lb/>a Man chuſe, and what Qualities muſt
	<lb/>encline a Woman to accept, that ſo our
	<lb/>Marry'd couple may be as happy as that 
	<lb/>State can make them? This is no hard
	<lb/>Queſtion; let the Soul be principally con­
	<lb/>ſider'd, and regard had in the firſt Place
	<lb/>to a good Underſtanding, a Vertuous
	<lb/>Mind, and in all other reſpects let there
	<lb/>be as much equality as may be. If they
	<lb/>are good Chriſtians and of ſuitable Tem­
	<lb/>pers all will be well; but I ſhould be
	<lb/>ſhrewdly tempted to ſuſpect their Chri­
	<lb/>ſtianity who Marry after any of thoſe
	<lb/>ways we have been ſpeaking of, I dare
	<lb/>venture to ſay, that they don't Act accor­
	<lb/>ding to the Precepts of the Goſpel, they
	<lb/>neither ſhew the Wiſdom of the Serpent,
	<lb/>nor the Innocency of the Dove, they have
	<lb/>neither ſo much Government of them­
	<lb/>ſelves, nor ſo much Charity for their
	<lb/>Neighbours, they neither take ſuch care
	<lb/>not to Scandalize others, nor to avoid
	<lb/>Temptations themſelves, are neither ſo
	<lb/>much above this World, nor ſo affected
	<lb/>with the next, as they wou'd certainly be
	<lb/>did the Chriſtian Religion operate in their
	<lb/>Hearts, did they rightly underſtand and 
	<lb/>ſincerely Practiſe it, or Acted <emph>indeed</emph> ac­
	<lb/>cording to the Spirit of the Goſpel.</p>
        <mw type="catch">But</mw>
        <pb n="41"/>
        <milestone n="D5r" unit="sig"/>
        <mw type="pageNum">41</mw>
        <p>But it is not enough to enter wiſely into
	<lb/>this State, care muſt be taken of our Con­
	<lb/>duct afterwards. A Woman will not want
	<lb/>being admoniſh'd of her Duty, the cu­
	<lb/>ſtom of the World, Œconomy, every
	<lb/>thing almoſt reminds her of it. Governors
	<lb/>do not often ſuffer their Subjects to forget
	<lb/>Obedience through their want of demand­
	<lb/>ing it, perhaps Huſbands are but too for­
	<lb/>ward on this occaſion, and claim their
	<lb/>Right oftner and more Imperiouſly than
	<lb/>either Diſcretion or good Manners will
	<lb/>juſtifie, and might have both a more chear­
	<lb/>ful and conſtant Obedience paid them if
	<lb/>they were not ſo rigorous in Exacting it.
	<lb/>For there is a mutual Stipulation, and
	<lb/>Love, Honour, and Worſhip, by which
	<lb/>certainly Civility and Reſpect at leaſt are
	<lb/>meant, are as much the Woman's due, as 
	<lb/>Love, Honour, and Obedience are the
	<lb/>Man's, and being the Woman is ſaid to
	<lb/>be the weaker Veſſel, the Man ſhou'd be
	<lb/>more careful not to grieve or offend her.
	<lb/>Since her Reaſon is ſuppos'd to be leſs, and
	<lb/>her Paſſions ſtronger than his, he ſhou'd
	<lb/>not give occaſion to call that ſuppoſition
	<lb/>in Queſtion by his pettiſh Carriage and
	<lb/>needleſs Provocations. Since he is the
	<lb/><mcr>Man</mcr>, by which <choice><sic/><corr>e</corr></choice>very word Cuſtom wou'd
	<lb/>have us underſtand not only greateſt
	<lb/>ſtrength of Body, but even greateſt firm­
	  <mw type="catch">neſs</mw>

<pb n="42"/>
<milestone n="D5v" unit="sig"/>
<mw rend="align(left)" type="pageNum">40</mw>
	<lb/>neſs and force of Mind, he ſhou'd not play
	<lb/>the <mcr>little Maſter</mcr> ſo much as to expect to be
	<lb/>cocker'd, nor run over to that ſide which
	<lb/>the <ref xml:id="er13" type="correction" target="#ec13">Woman</ref> us'd to be rank'd in; for ac­
	<lb/>cording to the Wiſdom of the <name>Italians</name>,
	<lb/><quote source="b:IT99999">Will you? Is ſpoken to ſick Folks.</quote></p>
        <p>Indeed Subjection, according to the com­
	<lb/>mon Notion of it, is not over eaſie, none
	<lb/>of us whether Men or Women but have ſo
	<lb/>good an Opinion of our own Conduct as
	<lb/>to believe we are fit, if not to direct others,
	<lb/>at leaſt to govern our ſelves. Nothing but
	<lb/>a ſound Underſtanding, and Grace the
	<lb/>beſt improver of natural Reaſon, can cor­
	<lb/>rect this Opinion, truly humble us, and
	<lb/>heartily reconcile us to Obedience. This
	<lb/>bitter Cup therefore ought to be ſweetned
	<lb/>as much as may be; for Authority may be
	<lb/>preſerv'd and Government kept inviola­
	<lb/>ble, without that nauſeous Oſtentation of
	<lb/>Power which ſerves to no end or purpoſe,
	<lb/>but to blow up the Pride and Vanity of
	<lb/>thoſe who have it, and to exaſperate the
	<lb/>Spirits of ſuch as muſt truckle under it.</p>
        <p>Inſolence 'tis true is never the effect of
	<lb/>Power but in weak and cowardly Spirits,
	<lb/>who wanting true <mcr>Merit</mcr> and Judgment to
	<lb/>ſupport themſelves in that advantageous
	<lb/>Ground on which they ſtand, are ever ap­
	<lb/>pealing to their Authority, and making a
	<lb/>ſhew of it to maintain their Vanity and
	  <mw type="catch">Pride.</mw>

<pb n="43"/>
<milestone n="D6r" unit="sig"/>
<mw type="pageNum">43</mw>
	<lb/>Pride. A truly great Mind and ſuch as is
	<lb/>fit to Govern, tho' it may ſtand on its Right
	<lb/>with its Equals, and modeſtly expect what 
	<lb/>is due to it even from its Superiors, yet it
	<lb/>never contends with its Inferiors, nor makes
	<lb/>uſe of its Superiority but to do them Good.
	<lb/>So that conſidering the juſt Dignity of
	<lb/>Man, his great Wiſdom ſo conſpicuous on
	<lb/>all occaſions! the goodneſs of his Temper
	<lb/>and Reaſonableneſs of all his Commands,
	<lb/>which make it a Woman's Intereſt as well
	<lb/>as Duty to be obſervant and Obedient in
	<lb/>all things! that his Prerogative is ſettled
	<lb/>by an undoubted Right, and the Preſcri­
	<lb/>ption of many Ages; it cannot be ſuppos'd
	<lb/>that he ſhould make frequent and inſolent
	<lb/>Claims of an Authority ſo well eſtabliſh'd
	<lb/>and us'd with ſuch moderation! nor give
	<lb/>an impartial By-ſtander (cou'd ſuch an one
	<lb/>be found) any occaſion from thence to ſuſ­
	<lb/>pect that he is inwardly conſcious of the
	<lb/>badneſs of his Title; Uſurpers being al­
	<lb/>ways moſt deſirous of Recognitions and
	<lb/>buſie in impoſing Oaths, whereas a Lawful
	<lb/>Prince contents himſelf with the uſual
	<lb/>Methods and Securities.</p>
        <p>And ſince Power does naturally puff up,
	<lb/>and he who finds himſelf exalted, ſeldom
	<lb/>fails to think he <mcr>ought</mcr> to be ſo, it is more
	<lb/>ſuitable to a Man's Wiſdom and Genero­
	<lb/>ſity, to be mindful of his great Obligati­
	  <mw type="catch">ons</mw>

<pb n="44"/>
<milestone n="D6v" unit="sig"/>
<mw rend="align(left)" type="pageNum">44</mw>
	<lb/>ons than to inſiſt on his Rights and Prero­
	<lb/>gatives. Sweetneſs of Temper and an
	<lb/>obliging Carriage are ſo juſtly due to a
	<lb/>Wife, that a Huſband who muſt not be
	<lb/>thought to want either Underſtanding to
	<lb/>know what is fit, nor Goodneſs to perform
	<lb/>it, can't be ſuppos'd not to ſhew them.
	<lb/>For ſetting aſide the hazards of her Perſon
	<lb/>to keep up his Name and Family, with all
	<lb/>the Pains and Trouble that attend it, which
	<lb/>may well be thought great enough to de­
	<lb/>ſerve all the reſpect and kindneſs that may
	<lb/>be, ſetting this aſide, tho' 'tis very conſi­
	<lb/>derable, a Woman has ſo much the diſad­
	<lb/>vantage in <mcr>moſt</mcr>, I was about to ſay in <mcr>all</mcr>
	<lb/>things, that ſhe makes a Man the greateſt
	<lb/>Compliment in the World when ſhe con­
	<lb/>deſcends to take him <mcr>for Better for Worſe</mcr>.
	<lb/>She puts her ſelf intirely in his Power,
	<lb/>leaves all that is dear to her, her Friends
	<lb/>and Family, to eſpouſe his Intereſts and
	<lb/>follow his Fortune, and makes it her Bu­
	<lb/>ſineſs and Duty to pleaſe him! What ac­
	<lb/>knowledgments, what returns can he make?
	<lb/>What Gratitude can be ſufficient for ſuch
	<lb/>Obligations? She ſhews her good Opini­
	<lb/>on of him by the great Truſt ſhe repoſes
	<lb/>in him, and what a Brute muſt he be who
	<lb/>betrays that Truſt, or acts any way un­
	<lb/>worthy of it? Ingratitude is one of the
	<lb/>baſeſt Vices, and if a Man's Soul is ſunk
	<mw type="catch">ſo</mw>

<pb n="45"/>
<milestone n="D7r" unit="sig"/>
<mw type="pageNum">45</mw>
	<lb/>ſo low, as to be guilty of it towards her
	<lb/>who has ſo generouſly oblig'd him, and
	<lb/>who ſo intirely depends on him, if he
	<lb/>can treat her Diſreſpectfully, who has ſo
	<lb/>fully teſtify'd her Eſteem of him, ſhe muſt
	<lb/>have a ſtock of Vertue which he ſhou'd
	<lb/>bluſh to diſcern, if ſhe can pay him that
	<lb/>Obedience of which he is ſo unworthy.</p>
        <p>Superiors indeed are too apt to forget
	<lb/>the common Privileges of Mankind;
	<lb/>that their Inferiors ſhare with them the
	<lb/>greateſt Benefits, and are as capable as
	<lb/>themſelves of enjoying the ſupreme Good;
	<lb/>that tho' the Order of the World requires
	<lb/>an <mcr>Outward</mcr> Reſpect and Obedience from
	<lb/>ſome to others, yet the Mind is free, no­
	<lb/>thing but Reaſon can oblige it, 'tis out of
	<lb/>the reach of the moſt abſolute Tyrant.
	<lb/>Nor will it ever be well either with thoſe
	<lb/>who Rule or thoſe in Subjection, even
	<lb/>from the Throne to every Private Family,
	<lb/>till thoſe in Authority look on themſelves
	<lb/>as plac'd in that Station for the good and
	<lb/>improvement of their Subjects, and not
	<lb/>for their own ſakes; not as the reward of
	<lb/>their Merit, or that they may proſecute
	<lb/>their own Deſires and fulfil all their Plea­
	<lb/>ſure, but as the Repreſentatives of <mcr rend="slant(upright)case(allcaps)">God</mcr>
	<lb/>whom they ought to imitate in the Juſtice
	<lb/>and Equity of their Laws, in doing good
	<lb/>and communicating Bleſſings to all beneath
	  <mw type="catch">them:</mw>

<pb n="46"/>
<milestone n="D7v" unit="sig"/>
<mw rend="align(left)" type="pageNum">46</mw>
	<lb/>them: By which, and not by following the
	<lb/>imperious Dictates of their own will, they
	<lb/>become truly Great and Illuſtrious and
	<lb/>Worthily fill their Place. And the Go­
	<lb/>verned for their part ceaſing to envy the
	<lb/>Pomp and Name of Authority, ſhou'd re­
	<lb/>ſpect their Gover<choice><sic>u</sic><corr>n</corr></choice>ours as plac'd in 
	  <mcr rend="slant(upright)case(allcaps)">God's</mcr>
	<lb/>ſtead, and contribute what they can to eaſe
	<lb/>them of their real Cares, by a chearful,
	<lb/>and ready compliance with their good en­
	<lb/>deavours, and by affording them the Plea­
	<lb/>ſure of ſucceſs in ſuch noble and generous
	<lb/>Deſigns.</p>
        <p>For upon a due eſtimate things are
	<lb/>pretty equally divided; thoſe in Subjecti­
	<lb/>on as they have a leſs Glorious, ſo they
	<lb/>have an eaſier task and a leſs account to
	<lb/>give, whereas he who Commands has in
	<lb/>a great meaſure the Faults of others to
	<lb/>anſwer for as well as his own. 'Tis true
	<lb/>he has the Pleaſure of doing more good
	<lb/>than a Private Perſon can, and ſhall re­
	<lb/>ceive the Reward of it when Time ſhall
	<lb/>be no more, in compenſation for the ha­
	<lb/>zards he runs, the difficulties he at pre­
	<lb/>ſent encounters, and the large Account he
	<lb/>is to make hereafter, which Pleaſure and
	<lb/>Reward are highly deſirable and moſt wor­
	<lb/>thy our purſuit; but they are Motives
	<lb/>which ſuch as uſurp on their Governors,
	<lb/>and make them uneaſie in the due diſcharge
	  <mw type="catch">of</mw>

<pb n="47"/>
<milestone n="D8r" unit="sig"/>
<mw type="pageNum">47</mw>
	<lb/>of their Duty, never propoſe. And for
	<lb/>thoſe other little things that move their
	<lb/>Envy and Ambition, they are of no E­
	<lb/>ſteem with a juſt Conſiderer, nor will
	<lb/>ſuch as violently purſue, find their Ac­
	<lb/>count in them.</p>
        <p>But how can a Man reſpect his Wife
	<lb/>when he has a contemptible Opinion of
	<lb/>her and her Sex? When from his own
	<lb/>Elevation he looks down on them as void
	<lb/>of Underſtanding, and full of Ignorance
	<lb/>and Paſſion, ſo that Folly and a Woman
	<lb/>are equivalent Terms with him? Can he
	<lb/>think there is any Gratitude due to her
	<lb/>whoſe utmoſt ſervices he exacts as ſtrict
	<lb/>Duty? Becauſe ſhe was made to be a Slave
	<lb/>to his Will, and has no higher end than
	<lb/>to Serve and Obey him! Perhaps we ar­
	<lb/>rogate too much to our ſelves when we
	<lb/>ſay this Material World was made for our
	<lb/>ſakes; that its Glorious Maker has given
	<lb/>us the uſe of it is certain, but when we
	<lb/>ſuppoſe a thing to be made purely for our
	<lb/>ſakes, becauſe we have Dominion over it,
	<lb/>we draw a falſe Concluſion, as he who
	<lb/>ſhou'd ſay the People were made for the
	<lb/>Prince who is ſet over them, wou'd be
	<lb/>thought to be out of his Senſes as well as
	<lb/>his Politicks. Yet even allowing that
	<lb/><mcr rend="slant(upright)case(allcaps)">God</mcr> who made every thing in Number,
	<lb/>Weight and Meaſure, who never acts
	  <mw type="catch">but</mw>

<pb n="48"/>
<milestone n="D8v" unit="sig"/>
<mw rend="align(left)" type="pageNum">48</mw>
	<lb/>but for ſome great and glorious End, an
	<lb/>End agreeable to His Majeſty, allowing
	<lb/>that He Created ſuch a Number of Ra­
	<lb/>tional Spirits merely to ſerve their fel­
	<lb/>low Creatures, yet how are theſe Lords
	<lb/>and Maſters helpt by the Contempt they
	<lb/>ſhew of their poor humble Vaſſals? Is it
	<lb/>not rather an hindrance to that Service
	<lb/>they expect, as being an undeniable and
	<lb/>conſtant Proof how unworthy they are to
	<lb/>receive it?</p>
        <p>None of <mcr rend="slant(upright)case(allcaps)">God's</mcr> 
           Creatures abſolutely
	<lb/>conſider'd are in their own Nature Con­
	<lb/>temptible; the meaneſt Fly, the pooreſt
	<lb/>Inſect has its Uſe and Vertue. Contempt
	<lb/>is ſcarce a Human Paſſion, one may ven­
	<lb/>ture to ſay it was not in Innocent Man,
	<lb/>for till Sin came into the World, there
	<lb/>was nothing in it to be contemn'd. But
	<lb/>Pride which makes every thing ſerve its
	<lb/>purpoſes, wreſted this Paſſion from its on­
	<lb/>ly uſe, ſo that inſtead of being an Anti­
	<lb/>dote againſt Sin, it is become a grand pro­
	<lb/>moter of it, nothing making us more wor­
	<lb/>thy of that Contempt we ſhew, than when 
	<lb/>poor, weak, dependent Creatures as we
	<lb/>are! we look down with Scorn and Diſ­
	<lb/>dain on others.</p>
        <p>There is not a ſurer Sign of a noble
	<lb/>Mind, a Mind very far advanc'd towards
	<lb/>Perfection, than the being able to bear
	  <mw type="catch">Con-</mw>
<pb n="49"/>
<milestone n="E1r" unit="sig"/>
<mw type="pageNum">49</mw>
	<lb/>Contempt and an unjuſt Treatment from
	<lb/>ones Superiors evenly and patiently. For
	<lb/>inward Worth and real Excellency are the
	<lb/>true Ground of Superiority, and one Per­
	<lb/>ſon is not in reality better than another,
	<lb/>but as he is more Wiſe and Good. But
	<lb/>this World being a place of Tryal and
	<lb/>govern'd by general Laws, juſt Retribu­
	<lb/>tions being reſerv'd for hereafter, Reſpect
	<lb/>and Obedience many times become due
	<lb/>for Order's ſake to thoſe who don't other­
	<lb/>wiſe deſerve them. Now tho' Humility
	<lb/>keeps us from over-valuing our ſelves or
	<lb/>viewing our Merit thro' a falſe and mag­
	<lb/>nifying <mcr>Medium</mcr>, yet it does not put out
	<lb/>our Eyes, it does not, it ought not to de­
	<lb/>prive us of that pleaſing ſentiment which
	<lb/>attends our Acting as we ought to Act,
	<lb/>which is as it were a foretaſt of Heaven,
	<lb/>our preſent Reward for doing what is Juſt
	<lb/>and Fit. And when a Superior does a Mean
	<lb/>and unjuſt Thing, as all Contempt of one's
	<lb/>Neighbour is, and yet this does not pro­
	<lb/>voke his Inferiors to refuſe that Obſervance
	<lb/>which their Stations in the World require,
	<lb/>they cannot but have an inward Senſe of
	<lb/>their own real Superiority, the other ha­
	<lb/>ving no pretence to it, at the ſame time
	<lb/>that they pay him an outward Reſpect and
	<lb/>Deference, which is ſuch a flagrant Teſti­
	<lb/>mony of the ſincereſt Love of Order as
	  <mw rend="align(center)" type="sig">E</mw>
	  <mw rend="break(no)" type="catch">proves</mw>

<pb n="50"/>
<milestone n="E1v" unit="sig"/>
<mw rend="align(left)" type="pageNum">50</mw>
	<lb/>proves their Souls to be of the higheſt and
	<lb/>nobleſt Rank.</p>
        <p>A Man therefore for his own ſake, and
	<lb/>to give evidence that he has a Right to
	<lb/>thoſe Prerogatives he aſſumes, ſhou'd treat
	<lb/>Women with a little more Humanity
	<lb/>and Regard than is uſually paid them.
	<lb/>Your whiffling Wits may ſcoff at them,
	<lb/>and what then? It matters not, for they
	<lb/>Rally every thing tho' ever ſo Sacred, and
	<lb/>rail at the Women commonly in very good
	<lb/>Company. Religion, its Prieſts, and thoſe
	<lb/>its moſt conſtant and regular Profeſſors, are
	<lb/>the uſual Subjects of their manly, man­
	<lb/>nerly and ſurprizing Jeſts. Surprizing in­
	<lb/>deed! not for the newneſs of the Thought,
	<lb/>the brightneſs of the Fancy, or nobleneſs
	<lb/>of Expreſſion, but for the good Aſſurance
	<lb/>with which ſuch thread-bare Jeſts are a­
	<lb/>gain and again repeated. But that your
	<lb/>grave Dons, you Learned Men, and which
	<lb/>is more, your Men of Senſe as they wou'd
	<lb/>be thought, ſhould ſtoop ſo low as to make
	<lb/>invectives againſt the Women, forget
	<lb/>themſelves ſo much as to Jeſt with their
	<lb/>Slaves, who have neither Liberty nor In­
	<lb/>genuity to make Reprizals! that they ſhou'd
	<lb/>waſte their Time, and debaſe their good
	<lb/>Senſe, which fits them for the moſt weigh­
	<lb/>ty Affairs, ſuch as are ſuitable to their pro­
	<lb/>found Wiſdoms and exalted Underſtand­
	  <mw type="catch">ings!</mw>

<pb n="51"/>
<milestone n="E2r" unit="sig"/>
<mw type="pageNum">51</mw>
	<lb/>ings! to render thoſe poor Wretches more
	<lb/>ridiculous and odious who are already in 
	<lb/>their Opinion ſufficiently contemptible,
	<lb/>and find no better exerciſe of their Wit
	<lb/>and Satyr than ſuch as are not worth their
	<lb/>Pains, tho' it were poſſible to Reform them,
	<lb/>this, this indeed may juſtly be wondred at!</p>
        <p>I know not whether or no Women are
	<lb/>allow'd to have Souls, if they have, perhaps
	<lb/>it is not prudent to provoke them too much,
	<lb/>leſt ſilly as they are, they at laſt recrimi­
	<lb/>nate, and then what polite and well-bred
	<lb/>Gentleman, tho' himſelf is concern'd can
	<lb/>forbear taking that lawful Pleaſure which
	<lb/>all who underſtand Raillery muſt taſt,
	<lb/>when they find his Jeſts who inſolently
	<lb/>began to peck at his Neighbour, return'd
	<lb/>with Intereſt upon his own Head? And
	<lb/>indeed Men are too Humane, too Wiſe to
	<lb/>venture at it did they not hope for this ef­
	<lb/>fect, and expect the Pleaſure of finding
	<lb/>their Wit turn to ſuch account; for if it
	<lb/>be lawful to reveal a Secret, this is with­
	<lb/>out doubt the whole deſign of thoſe fine
	<lb/>Diſcourſes which have been made againſt 
	<lb/>the Women from our great Fore-fathers to
	<lb/>this preſent Time! Generous Man has too
	<lb/>much Bravery, he is too Juſt and too Good
	<lb/>to aſſault a defenceleſs Enemy, and if he
	<lb/>did inveigh againſt the Women it was on­
	<lb/>ly to do them Service! For ſince neither
	  <mw rend="align(center)" type="sig">E2</mw>
	  <mw rend="break(no)" type="catch">his</mw>

<pb n="52"/>
<milestone n="E2v" unit="sig"/>
<mw rend="align(left)" type="pageNum">52</mw>
	<lb/>his Care of their Education, his hearty
	<lb/>endeavours to improve their Minds, his
	<lb/>wholſome Precepts, nor great Example
	<lb/>cou'd do them good, as his laſt and kindeſt
	<lb/>Eſſay, he reſolv'd to try what Contempt
	<lb/>wou'd do, and choſe rather to expoſe him­
	<lb/>ſelf by a ſeeming want of Juſtice, Equity,
	<lb/>Ingenuity and Good-nature, than ſuffer
	<lb/>Women to remain ſuch vain and inſignifi­
	<lb/>cant Creatures as they have hitherto been
	<lb/>reckon'd! And truly Women are ſome de­
	<lb/>grees beneath what I have thus far thought
	<lb/>them, if they do not make the beſt uſe
	<lb/>of his kindneſs, improve themſelves, and
	<lb/>like <name rend="slant(upright)">Christians</name> return it.</p>
        <p>Let us ſee then what is their Part, what
	<lb/>muſt they do to make the Matrimonial
	<lb/>Yoke tolerable to themſelves as well as
	<lb/>pleaſing to their Lords and Maſters? That
	<lb/>the World is an empty and deceitful
	<lb/>Thing, that thoſe Enjoyments which ap­
	<lb/>pear'd ſo deſirable at a diſtance, which
	<lb/>rais'd our Hopes and Expectations to ſuch
	<lb/>a mighty Pitch, which we ſo paſſionately
	<lb/>coveted, and ſo eagerly purſued, vaniſh at
	<lb/>our firſt approach, leaving nothing behind
	<lb/>them but the Folly of Deluſion, and the
	<lb/>pain of diſappointed Hopes, is a common
	<lb/>Outcry; and yet as common as it is, tho'
	<lb/>we complain of being deceiv'd this Inſtant,
	<lb/>we do not fail of contributing to the
	  <mw type="catch">Cheat</mw>

<pb n="53"/>
<milestone n="E3r" unit="sig"/>
<mw type="pageNum">53</mw>
	<lb/>Cheat the very next. Tho' in reality it
	<lb/>is not the World that abuſes us, 'tis we
	<lb/>abuſe our ſelves, it is not the emptineſs of
	<lb/>that, but our own falſe Judgments, our
	<lb/>unreaſonable Deſires and Expectations
	<lb/>that Torment us; for he who exerts his 
	<lb/>whole ſtrength to lift a Straw, ought not
	<lb/>to complain of the Burden, but of his own
	<lb/>diſproportionate endeavour which gives
	<lb/>him the pain he feels. The World affords
	<lb/>us all the Pleaſure a ſound Judgment can
	<lb/>expect from it, and anſwers all thoſe Ends
	<lb/>and Purpoſes for which it was deſign'd,
	<lb/>let us expect no more than is reaſonable, 
	<lb/>and then we ſhall not fail of our Expecta­
	<lb/>tion.</p>
        <p>It is even ſo in the Caſe before us; a
	<lb/>Woman who has been taught to think
	<lb/>Marriage her only Preferment, the Sum-
	<lb/>total of her Endeavours, the completion
	<lb/>of all her hopes, that which muſt ſettle
	<lb/>and make her Happy in this World, and
	<lb/>very few, in their Youth eſpecially, car­
	<lb/>ry a Thought ſteddily to a greater diſtance;
	<lb/>She who has ſeen a Lover dying at her
	<lb/>Feet, and can't therefore imagine that he
	<lb/>who profeſſes to receive all his Happineſs
	<lb/>from her, can have any other Deſign or
	<lb/>Deſire than to pleaſe her; whoſe Eyes
	<lb/>have been dazled with all the Glitter and
	<lb/>Pomp of a Wedding, and who hears of no­
	  <mw rend="align(center)" type="sig">E3</mw>
	  <mw rend="break(no)" type="catch">thing</mw>


<pb n="54"/>
<milestone n="E3v" unit="sig"/>
<mw rend="align(left)" type="pageNum">54</mw>
	<lb/>thing but Joy and Congratulation; who is
	<lb/>tranſported with the Pleaſure of being out
	<lb/>of Pupillage, and Miſtreſs not only of her
	<lb/>ſelf but of a Family too: She who is ei­
	<lb/>ther ſo ſimple or ſo vain, as to take her
	<lb/>Lover at his Word either as to the Praiſes
	<lb/>he gave her, or the Promiſes he made for
	<lb/>himſelf; in ſum, ſhe whoſe Expectation
	<lb/>has been rais'd by Court-ſhip, by all the
	<lb/>fine things that her Lover, her Governeſs,
	<lb/>and Domeſtic Flatterers ſay, will find a
	<lb/>terrible diſappointment when the hurry is
	<lb/>over, and when ſhe comes calmly to conſi­
	<lb/>der her Condition, and views it no more
	<lb/>under a falſe Appearance, but as it truly is.</p>
        <p>I doubt in ſuch a View it will not ap­
	<lb/>pear over-deſirable, if ſhe regards only the
	<lb/>preſent State of Things. Hereafter may
	<lb/>make amends for what ſhe muſt be prepar'd
	<lb/>to ſuffer here, then will be her Reward,
	<lb/>this is her time of Tryal, the Seaſon of
	<lb/>exerciſing and improving her Vertues. A
	<lb/>Woman that is not Miſtreſs of her Paſſions,
	<lb/>that cannot patiently ſubmit even when
	<lb/>Reaſon ſuffers with her, who does not
	<lb/>practiſe Paſſive Obedience to the utmoſt,
	<lb/>will never be acceptable to ſuch an abſo­
	<lb/>lute Sovereign as a Husband. Wiſdom
	<lb/>ought to Govern without Contradiction,
	<lb/>but Strength however will be obey'd.
	<lb/>There are but few of thoſe wiſe Perſons
	  <mw type="catch">who</mw>

<pb n="55"/>
<milestone n="E4r" unit="sig"/>
<mw type="pageNum">55</mw>
	<lb/>who can be content to be made yet wiſer
	<lb/>by Contradiction, the moſt will have their
	<lb/><mcr>Will</mcr>, and it is right becauſe it is their's.
	<lb/>Such is the vanity of Humane Nature that
	<lb/>nothing pleaſes like an intire Subjection;
	<lb/>what Imperfections won't a Man over-look
	<lb/>where this is not wanting! Tho' we live
	<lb/>like Brutes, we wou'd have Incenſe offer'd
	<lb/>us that is only due to Heaven it ſelf, wou'd
	<lb/>have an abſolute and blind Obedience paid
	<lb/>us by all over whom we pretend Authority.
	<lb/>We were not made to Idolize one another,
	<lb/>yet the whole ſtrain of Courtſhip is little
	<lb/>leſs than rank Idolatry: But does a Man
	<lb/>intend to give, and not to receive his ſhare
	<lb/>in this Religious Worſhip? No ſuch mat­
	<lb/>ter; Pride and Vanity and Self-love have
	<lb/>their Deſigns, and if the Lover is ſo con­
	<lb/>deſcending as to ſet a Pattern in the time of
	<lb/>his Addreſſes, he is ſo Juſt as to expect his
	<lb/>Wife ſhou'd ſtrictly Copy after it all the
	<lb/>reſt of her life.</p>
        <p>But how can a Woman ſcruple intire
	<lb/>Subjection, how can ſhe forbear to admire
	<lb/>the worth and excellency of the Superior
	<lb/>Sex, if ſhe at all conſiders it? Have not
	<lb/>all the great Actions that have been per­
	<lb/>form'd in the World been done by Men?
	<lb/>Have not they founded Empires and over­
	<lb/>turn'd them? Do not they make Laws and
	<lb/>continually repeal and amend them? Their
	  <mw rend="align(center)" type="sig">E4</mw>
	  <mw rend="break(no)" type="catch">vaſt</mw>

<pb n="56"/>
<milestone n="E4v" unit="sig"/>
<mw rend="align(left)" type="pageNum">56</mw>
	<lb/>vaſt Minds lay Kingdoms waſt, no bounds
	<lb/>or meaſures can be preſcrib'd to their De­
	<lb/>ſires. War and Peace depend on them, they
	<lb/>form Cabals and have the Wiſdom and
	<lb/>Courage to get over all <ref xml:id="er14" type="correction" target="#ec14">theſe</ref> Rubs which
	<lb/>may lie in the way of their deſired Gran­
	<lb/>deur. What is it they cannot do? They
	<lb/>make Worlds and ruine them, form Sy­
	<lb/>ſtems of univerſal Nature and diſpute e­
	<lb/>ternally about them; their Pen gives
	<lb/>worth to the moſt trifling Controverſie;
	<lb/>nor can a fray be inconſiderable if they
	<lb/>have drawn their Swords in't. All that
	<lb/>the wiſe Man pronounces is an Oracle,
	<lb/>and every Word the Witty ſpeaks a Jeſt.
	<lb/>It is a Woman's Happineſs to hear, admire
	<lb/>and praiſe them, eſpecially if a little Ill-
	<lb/>nature keeps them at any time from be­
	<lb/>ſtowing due Applauſes on each other! And
	<lb/>if ſhe aſpires no further, ſhe is thought to
	<lb/>be in her proper Sphere of Action, ſhe is
	<lb/>as wiſe and as good as can be expected 
	<lb/>from her!</p>
        <p>She then who Marrys ought to lay it
	<lb/>down for an indiſputable Maxim, that
	<lb/>her Huſband muſt govern abſolutely and
	<lb/>intirely, and that ſhe has nothing elſe to
	<lb/>do but to Pleaſe and Obey. She muſt not
	<lb/>attempt to divide his Authority, or ſo
	<lb/>much as diſpute it, to ſtruggle with her
	<lb/>Yoke will only make it gall the more, but
	  <mw type="catch">muſt</mw>

<pb n="57"/>
<milestone n="E5r" unit="sig"/>
<mw type="pageNum">57</mw>
	<lb/>muſt believe him Wiſe and Good and in
	<lb/>all reſpects the beſt, at leaſt he muſt be ſo
	<lb/>to her. She who can't do this is no way fit
	<lb/>to be a Wife, ſhe may ſet up for that pecu­
	<lb/>liar Coronet the ancient Fathers talk'd of,
	<lb/>but is not qualify'd to receive that great
	<lb/>reward, which attends the eminent exer­
	<lb/>ciſe of Humility and Self-denial, Patience
	<lb/>and Reſignation, the Duties that a Wife is
	<lb/>call'd to.</p>
        <p>But ſome refractory Woman perhaps
	<lb/>will ſay, how can this be? Is it poſſible
	<lb/>for her to believe him Wiſe and Good who
	<lb/>by a thouſand Demonſtrations convinces
	<lb/>her and all the World of the contrary?
	<lb/>Did the bare Name of Huſband confer
	<lb/>Senſe on a Man, and the mere being in 
	<lb/>Authority infallibly qualifie him for Go­
	<lb/>vernment, much might be done. But ſince
	<lb/>a wiſe Man and a Huſband are not Terms
	<lb/>convertible, and how loth ſoever one is
	<lb/>to own it, Matter of Fact won't allow us
	<lb/>to deny, that the Head many times ſtands
	<lb/>in need of the Inferior's Brains to manage
	<lb/>it, ſhe muſt beg leave to be excus'd from
	<lb/>ſuch high thoughts of her Sovereign, and
	<lb/>if ſhe ſubmits to his Power, it is not ſo
	<lb/>much Reaſon as Neceſſity that compels her.</p>
        <p>Now of how little force ſoever this
	<lb/>Objection may be in other reſpects, me­
	<lb/>thinks it is ſtrong enough to prove the ne­
	 <mw type="catch">ceſſity</mw>

<pb n="58"/>
<milestone n="E5v" unit="sig"/>
<mw rend="align(left)" type="pageNum">58</mw>
	<lb/>ceſſity of a good Education, and that Men
	<lb/>never miſtake their true Intereſt more than
	<lb/>when they endeavour to keep Women in
	<lb/>Ignorance. Cou'd they indeed deprive them
	<lb/>of their Natural good Senſe at the ſame
	<lb/>time they deny them the due improvement
	<lb/>of it, they might compaſs their End; other­
	<lb/>wiſe Natural Senſe unaſſiſted may run in­
	<lb/>to a falſe Track, and ſerve only to puniſh
	<lb/>him juſtly, who wou'd not allow it to be uſe­
	<lb/>ful to himſelf or others. If Man's Autho­
	<lb/>rity be juſtly eſtabliſh'd, the more Senſe a
	<lb/>Woman has, the more reaſon ſhe will find
	<lb/>to ſubmit to it; if according to the Tradi­
	<lb/>tion of our Father, (who having had
	<lb/><mcr>Poſſeſſion</mcr> of the Pen, thought they had
	<lb/>alſo the beſt <mcr>Right</mcr> to it,) Women's Under­
	<lb/>ſtanding is but ſmall, and Men's Partiality
	<lb/>adds no Weight to the Obſervation, ought
	<lb/>not the more care to be taken to improve
	<lb/>them? How it agrees with the Juſtice of
	<lb/>Men we enquire not, but certainly Heaven
	<lb/>is abundantly more equitable than to enjoyn
	<lb/>Women the hardeſt Task and give them
	<lb/>the leaſt Strength to perform it. And if
	<lb/>Men Learned; Wiſe and Diſcreet as they
	<lb/>are, who have as is ſaid all the advantages
	<lb/>of Nature, and without controverſy have,
	<lb/>or may have all the aſſiſtance of Art, are
	<lb/>ſo far from acquitting themſelves as they
	<lb/>ought, from living according to that Rea­
	  <mw type="catch">ſon</mw>

<pb n="59"/>
<milestone n="E6r" unit="sig"/>
<mw type="pageNum">59</mw> 
	<lb/>ſon and excellent Underſtanding they ſo
	<lb/>much boaſt of, can it be expected that a
	<lb/>Woman who is reckon'd ſilly enough in her
	<lb/>ſelf, at leaſt comparatively, and whom Men
	<lb/>take care to make yet more ſo, can it be ex­
	<lb/>pected that ſhe ſhou'd conſtantly perform ſo
	<lb/>difficult a Duty as intire Subjection, to
	<lb/>which corrupt Nature is ſo averſe?</p>
        <p>If the Great and Wiſe <persName ref="p:mcato.lxb">Cato</persName>, a <mcr>Man</mcr>, a
	<lb/>Man of no ordinary firmneſs and ſtrength
	<lb/>of Mind, a Man who was eſteem'd as an
	<lb/>Oracle, and by the Philoſophers and great
	<lb/>Men of his Nation equall'd even to the
	<lb/>Gods themſelves; If he with all his Stoical
	<lb/>Principles was not able to bear the ſight of
	<lb/>a triumphant Conqueror, (who perhaps
	<lb/>wou'd have Inſulted and perhaps wou'd not,)
	<lb/>but out of a Cowardly fear of an Inſult,
	<lb/>ran to Death to ſecure him from it; can it
	<lb/>be thought that an ignorant weak Woman
	<lb/>ſhou'd have patience to bear a continual
	<lb/>Out-rage and Inſolence all the days of her
	<lb/>Life? Unleſs you will ſuppoſe her a <mcr>very
	<lb/>Aſs</mcr>, but then remember what the <name>Italians</name> 
	<lb/>ſay, to Quote them once more, ſince being
	<lb/><emph>very</emph> Huſbands they may be preſum'd to
	<lb/>have Authority in this Caſe, <quote source="b:IT99999">an Aſs tho'
	<lb/>ſlow if provok'd will kick.</quote></p>
        <p>We never ſee or perhaps make ſport 
	<lb/>with the ill Effects of a bad Education, till
	<lb/>it come to touch us home in the ill conduct
	  <mw type="catch">of</mw>

<pb n="60"/>
<milestone n="E6v" unit="sig"/>
<mw rend="align(left)" type="pageNum">60</mw>
	<lb/>of a Siſter, a Daughter, or Wife. Then
	<lb/>the Women muſt be blam'd, their Folly is
	<lb/>exclaim'd againſt, when all this while it
	<lb/>was the wiſe Man's Fault, who did not ſet
	<lb/>a better Guard on thoſe who according to
	<lb/>him ſtand in ſo much need of one. A young
	<lb/>Gentleman, as a celebrated Author tells
	<lb/>us, ought above all things to be acquaint­
	<lb/>ed with the State of the World, the Ways
	<lb/>and Humours, the Follies, the Cheats, the
	<lb/>Faults of the Age he is fallen into, he
	<lb/>ſhould by degrees be inform'd of the Vice
	<lb/>in Faſhion, and warn'd of the Application
	<lb/>and Deſign of thoſe who will make it their
	<lb/>Buſineſs to corrupt him, ſhou'd be told the
	<lb/>Arts they uſe and the Trains they lay, be
	<lb/>prepar'd to be Shock'd by ſome and careſs'd
	<lb/>by others; warn'd who are like to oppoſe,
	<lb/>who to miſlead, who to undermine, and
	<lb/>who to ſerve him. He ſhou'd be inſtructed
	<lb/>how to know and diſtinguiſh them, where
	<lb/>he ſhou'd let them ſee, and when diſſem­
	<lb/>ble the Knowledge of them and their Aims
	<lb/>and Workings. Our Author is much in the
	<lb/>right, and not to diſparage any other Ac­
	<lb/>compliſhments which are uſeful in their
	<lb/>kind, this will turn to more account than
	<lb/>any Language or Philoſophy, Art or Sci­
	<lb/>ence, or any other piece of Good-breeding
	<lb/>and fine Education that can be taught him,
	<lb/>which are no otherwiſe excellent than as
	  <mw type="catch">they</mw>

<pb n="61"/>
<milestone n="E7r" unit="sig"/>
<mw type="pageNum">61</mw>
	<lb/>they contribute to this, as this does above
	<lb/>all things to the making him a wiſe, a ver­
	<lb/>tuous and uſeful Man.</p>
        <p>And it is not leſs neceſſary that a young
	<lb/>Lady ſhou'd receive the like Inſtructions,
	<lb/>whether or no her Temptations be fewer,
	<lb/>her Reputation and Honour however are
	<lb/>to be more nicely preſerv'd; they may be
	<lb/>ruin'd by a little Ignorance or Indiſcretion,
	<lb/>and then tho' ſhe has kept her Innocence,
	<lb/>and ſo is ſecur'd as to the next World, yet
	<lb/>ſhe is in a great meaſure loſt to this. A Wo­
	<lb/>man cannot be too watchful, too appre­
	<lb/>henſive of her danger, nor keep at too great 
	<lb/>a diſtance from it, ſince Man whoſe Wiſ­
	<lb/>dom and Ingenuity is ſo much Superior to
	<lb/>hers! condeſcends for his Intereſt ſome­
	<lb/>times, and ſometimes by way of Diverſion,
	<lb/>to lay Snares for her. For tho' all Men are
	<lb/><mcr>Virtuoſi</mcr>, Philoſophers and Politicians, in
	<lb/>compariſon of the Ignorant and Illiterate
	<lb/>Women, yet they don't all pretend to be 
	<lb/>Saints, and 'tis no great Matter to them if
	<lb/>Women who were born to be their Slaves,
	<lb/>be now and then ruin'd for their Enter­
	<lb/>tainment.</p>
        <p>But according to the rate that young
	<lb/>Women are Educated, according to the
	<lb/>way their Time is ſpent, they are deſtin'd 
	<lb/>to Folly and Impertinence, to ſay no worſe,
	<lb/>and which is yet more inhuman, they are
	  <mw type="catch">blam'd</mw>

<pb n="62"/>
<milestone n="E7v" unit="sig"/>
<mw rend="align(left)" type="pageNum">62</mw>
	<lb/>blam'd for that ill Conduct they are not
	<lb/>ſuffer'd to avoid, and reproach'd for thoſe
	<lb/>Faults they are in a manner forc'd into;
	<lb/>ſo that if Heaven has beſtowed any Senſe
	<lb/>on them, no other uſe is made of it, than
	<lb/>to leave them without Excuſe. So much
	<lb/>and no more of the World is ſhewn them,
	<lb/>as ſerves to weaken and corrupt their Minds,
	<lb/>to give them wrong Notions, and buſy
	<lb/>them in mean Purſuits; to diſturb, not to
	<lb/>regulate their Paſſions; to make them ti­
	<lb/>morous and dependant, and in a word, fit
	<lb/>for nothing elſe but to act a Farce for the
	<lb/>Diverſion of their Governours.</p>
        <p>Even Men themſelves improve no other­
	<lb/>wiſe than according to the Aim they take,
	<lb/>and the End they propoſe; and he whoſe
	<lb/>Deſigns are but little and mean, will be
	<lb/>the ſame himſelf. Tho' Ambition, as 'tis
	<lb/>uſually underſtood, is a Fooliſh, not to
	<lb/>ſay a Baſe and Pitiful Vice, yet the Aſpi­
	<lb/>rings of the Soul after true Glory are ſo
	<lb/>much its Nature, that it ſeems to have for­
	<lb/>got it ſelf and to degenerate, if it can for­
	<lb/>bear; and perhaps the great Secret of Edu­
	<lb/>cation lies in affecting the Soul with a lively
	<lb/>Senſe of what is truly its Perfection, and
	<lb/>exciting the moſt ardent Deſires after it.</p>
        <p>But, alas! what poor Woman is ever
	<lb/>taught that ſhe ſhould have a higher De­
	<lb/>ſign than to get her a Huſband? Heaven 
	  <mw type="catch">will</mw>

<pb n="63"/>
<milestone n="E8r" unit="sig"/>
<mw type="pageNum">63</mw>
	<lb/>will fall in of courſe; and if ſhe makes but
	<lb/>an Obedient and Dutiful Wife, ſhe cannot
	<lb/>miſs of it. A Huſband indeed is thought
	<lb/>by both Sexes ſo very valuable, that ſcarce
	<lb/>a Man who can keep himſelf clean and
	<lb/>make a Bow, but thinks he is good enough
	<lb/>to pretend to any Woman, no matter for
	<lb/>the Difference of Birth or Fortune, a Huſ­
	<lb/>band is ſuch a Wonder-working Name as
	<lb/>to make an Equality, or ſomething more,
	<lb/>whenever it is pronounc'd.</p>
        <p>And indeed were there no other Proof
	<lb/>of Maſculine Wiſdom, and what a much
	<lb/>greater Portion of Ingenuity falls to the
	<lb/>Men than to the Women's Share, the Ad­
	<lb/>dreſs, the Artifice, and Management of an
	<lb/>humble Servant were a ſufficient Demon­
	<lb/>ſtration. What good Conduct does he ſhew!
	<lb/>what Patience exerciſe! what Subtilty
	<lb/>leave untry'd! what Concealment of his
	<lb/>Faults! what Parade of his Vertues! what
	<lb/>Government of his Paſſions! How deep is
	<lb/>his Policy in laying his deſigns at ſo great
	<lb/>a diſtance, and working them up by ſuch
	<lb/>little Accidents! How indefatigable is his
	<lb/>Induſtry, and how conſtant his Watchful­
	<lb/>neſs, not to ſlip any Opportunity that may
	<lb/>in the leaſt contribute to his Deſign! What
	<lb/>a handſome Set of Diſguiſes and Preten­
	<lb/>ces is he always furniſh'd with! How con­
	<lb/>ceal'd does he lie! how little pretend, till
	  <mw type="catch">he</mw>

<pb n="64"/>
<milestone n="E8v" unit="sig"/>
<mw rend="align(left)" type="pageNum">64</mw>
	<lb/>he is ſure that his Plot will take! And at
	<lb/>the ſame time that he nouriſhes the Hope
	<lb/>of being Lord and Maſter, appears with
	<lb/>all the Modeſty and Submiſſion of an hum­
	<lb/>ble and unpretending Admirer.</p>
        <p>Can a Woman then be too much upon
	<lb/>her Guard? Can her Prudence and Fore­
	<lb/>ſight, her early Caution, be reckon'd un­
	<lb/>neceſſary Suſpicion, or ill-bred Reſerve,
	<lb/>by any but thoſe whoſe Deſigns they pre­
	<lb/>vent, and whoſe Intereſt it is to declaim
	<lb/>againſt them? it being a certain Maxim
	<lb/>with the Men, tho' Policy or Good Breed­
	<lb/>ing won't allow them to avow it always,
	<lb/>that the Women were made for their Sakes
	<lb/>and Service, and are in all reſpects their
	<lb/>Inferiors, eſpecially in Underſtanding; ſo
	<lb/>that all the Compliments they make, all
	<lb/>the Addreſs and Complaiſance they uſe, all
	<lb/>the Kindneſs they profeſs, all the Service
	<lb/>they pretend to pay, has no other Mean­
	<lb/>ing, no other End, than to get the poor
	<lb/>Woman into their Power, to govern her
	<lb/>according to their Diſcretion. This is all
	<lb/>pure Kindneſs indeed, and therefore no
	<lb/>Woman has Reaſon to be offended with it;
	<lb/>for conſidering how much ſhe is expos'd in
	<lb/>her own, and how ſafe in their Keeping,
	<lb/>'tis the wiſeſt thing ſhe can do to put her
	<lb/>ſelf under Protection! And then if they 
	<lb/>have a tolerable Opinion of her Senſe, and
	  <mw type="catch">not</mw>

<pb n="65"/>
<milestone n="F1r" unit="sig"/>
<mw type="pageNum">65</mw>
	<lb/>not their Vanity but ſome better Principle
	<lb/>diſpoſes them to do ſomething out of the
	<lb/>way, and to appear more generous than the
	<lb/>reſt of their Sex, they'll condeſcend to
	<lb/>dictate to her, and impart ſome of their
	<lb/>Prerogative Books and Learning! 'Tis fit
	<lb/>indeed that ſhe ſhould entirely depend on
	<lb/>their Choice, and walk with the Crutches
	<lb/>they are pleas'd to lend her; and if ſhe is
	<lb/>furniſhed out with ſome Notions to ſet her
	<lb/>a prating, I ſhould have ſaid to make her
	<lb/>entertaining and the Fiddle of the Com­
	<lb/>pany, her Tutor's Time was not ill be­
	<lb/>ſtowed: And it were a diverting Scene to
	<lb/>ſee her ſtript like the <mcr>Jay</mcr> of her borrowed
	<lb/>Feathers, but he, good Man, has not ill Na­
	<lb/>ture enough to take Pleaſure in it! You
	<lb/>may accuſe him perhaps for giving ſo much
	<lb/>Encouragement to a Woman's Vanity, but
	<lb/>your Accuſation is groundleſs, Vanity be­
	<lb/>ing a Diſeaſe the Sex will always be
	<lb/>guilty of; nor is it a Reproach to them,
	<lb/>ſince Men of Learning and Senſe are over­
	<lb/>run with it.</p>
        <p>But there are few Women whoſe Un­
	<lb/>derſtandings are worth the Management,
	<lb/>their Eſtates are much more capable of
	<lb/>Improvement. No Woman, much leſs a
	<lb/>Woman of Fortune, is ever fit to be her
	<lb/>own Miſtreſs, and he who has not the
	<lb/>Vanity to think what much finer things
	  <mw rend="align(center)" type="sig">F</mw>
	  <mw rend="break(no)" type="catch">he</mw>

<pb n="66"/>
<milestone n="F1v" unit="sig"/>
<mw rend="align(left)" type="pageNum">66</mw>
	<lb/>he could perform had he the Ma­
	<lb/>nagement of her Fortune; or ſo much
	<lb/>Partiality and Self-love, as to fancy it can't
	<lb/>be better beſtow'd than in making his;
	<lb/>will yet be ſo honeſt and humble as to
	<lb/>think that 'tis fit ſhe ſhould take his Aſſi­
	<lb/>ſtance, as Steward at leaſt. For the Good
	<lb/>Man aſpires no further, he would only take
	<lb/>the Trouble of her Affairs off her hand;
	<lb/>and the Senſe of her Condeſcention and
	<lb/>his great Obligations, will for ever ſecure
	<lb/>him againſt acting like a Lord and Maſter!</p>
        <p>The Steps to Folly as well as Sin are
	<lb/>gradual, and almoſt imperceptible, and
	<lb/>when we are once on the Decline, we go
	<lb/>down without taking notice on't; were it
	<lb/>not for this, one cou'd not account for
	<lb/>thoſe ſtrange unequal Matches we too of­
	<lb/>ten ſee. For there was a time no doubt,
	<lb/>when a Woman could not have bore the
	<lb/>very thought of what ſhe has been after­
	<lb/>wards betray'd into, it would have ap­
	<lb/>pear'd as ſhocking to her as it always does
	<lb/>to other People; and had a Man been ſo
	<lb/>impolitic as to diſcover the leaſt intimation
	<lb/>of ſuch a Deſign, he had given her a ſuffi­
	<lb/>cient Antidote againſt it. This your Wiſe
	<lb/>Men are well ſatisfy'd of, and underſtand
	<lb/>their own Intereſt too well to let their
	<lb/>Deſign go bare-fac'd, for that would effe­
	<lb/>ctually put a barr to their Succeſs. So in­
	  <mw type="catch">nocent</mw>

<pb n="67"/>
<milestone n="F2r" unit="sig"/>
<mw type="pageNum">67</mw>
	<lb/>nocent are they, that they had not the
	<lb/>leaſt Thought at firſt of what their Good
	<lb/>Fortune afterwards leads them to! They
	<lb/>would draw upon him, (if they wear a
	<lb/>Sword) or fly in her Face who ſhould let
	<lb/>fall the leaſt hint that they had ſuch In­
	<lb/>tentions; and this very Eagerneſs to avoid
	<lb/>the Suſpicion, is a ſhrewd Sign that there
	<lb/>is occaſion for't.</p>
        <p>But who ſhall dare to ſhew the Lady her
	<lb/>Danger, when will it be ſeaſonable to give
	<lb/>her friendly Notice? If you do it e're ſhe
	<lb/>is reſolv'd, tho' with all the Friendſhip
	<lb/>and Tenderneſs imaginable, ſhe will hard­
	<lb/>ly forgive the Affront, or bear the Provo­
	<lb/>cation; you offer her an Outrage, by en­
	<lb/>tertaining ſuch a Thought, and 'tis ten to
	<lb/>one if you are not afterwards accus'd for
	<lb/>putting in her Head what otherwiſe ſhe
	<lb/>could ne'er have dreamt of. And when no
	<lb/>direct Proof can be offer'd, when matter
	<lb/>of Prudence is the only thing in Queſtion,
	<lb/>every Body has ſo good an Opinion of their
	<lb/>own Underſtanding as to think their own
	<lb/>way the beſt. And when ſhe has her Inno­
	<lb/>cence and fair Intentions to oppoſe to your
	<lb/>Fears and Surmiſes, and you cannot pre­
	<lb/>tend to wiſh her better than ſhe does her
	<lb/>ſelf, to be more diſintereſs'd and diligent
	<lb/>in your Watchfulneſs, or to ſee farther in
	<lb/>what ſo nearly concerns her, what can be
	  <mw rend="align(center)" type="sig">F2</mw>
	  <mw rend="break(no)" type="catch">done?</mw>

<pb n="68"/>
<milestone n="F2v" unit="sig"/>
<mw rend="align(left)" type="pageNum">68</mw>
	<lb/>done? Her ruin is commonly too far ad­
	<lb/>vanc'd to be prevented, e're you can in
	<lb/>Good-breeding reach out a hand to help
	<lb/>her. For if the Train has took, if ſhe is
	<lb/>entangled in the Snare, if Love, or rather
	<lb/>a Blind unreaſonable Fondneſs, which
	<lb/>uſurps the Name of that noble Paſſion, has
	<lb/>gain'd on her, Reaſon and Perſwaſion may
	<lb/>as properly be urg'd to the Folks in <placeName>Bethlem</placeName>
	<lb/>as to her. Tell her of this World, ſhe is
	<lb/>got above it, and has no regard to its imper­
	<lb/>tinent Cenſures; tell her of the next, ſhe
	<lb/>laughs at you, and will never be convinc'd
	<lb/>that Actions which are not expreſly for­
	<lb/>bid can be Criminal, tho' they proceed
	<lb/>from, and muſt neceſſarily be reduc'd to
	<lb/>ill Principles, tho' they give Offence, are
	<lb/>of ill Example, injure our Reputation,
	<lb/>which next to our Innocence we are obli­
	<lb/>ged as <name rend="slant(upright)">Chriſtians</name> to take the greateſt care
	<lb/>of, and in a word do more miſchief than
	<lb/>we can readily imagine. Tell her of her
	<lb/>own Good, you appear yet more ridiculous,
	<lb/>for who can judge of her Happineſs but her
	<lb/>ſelf? And whilſt our Hearts are violently
	<lb/>ſet upon any thing, there is no convincing
	<lb/>us that we ſhall ever be of another Mind.
	<lb/>Our Paſſions want no Advocates, they are
	<lb/>always furniſh'd with plauſible Pretences,
	<lb/>and thoſe very Prejudices, which gave riſe
	<lb/>to this unreaſonable Paſſion, will for cer­
	  <mw type="catch">tain</mw>

<pb n="69"/>
<milestone n="F3r" unit="sig"/>
<mw type="pageNum">69</mw>
	<lb/>tain give her Obſtinacy enough to juſtifie
	<lb/>and continue in it. Beſides, ſome are ſo
	<lb/>ill advis'd as to think to ſupport one Indiſ­
	<lb/>cretion with another, they wou'd not have
	<lb/>it thought they have made a falſe Step, in
	<lb/>once giving countenance to that which is
	<lb/>not fit to be continued. Or perhaps the
	<lb/>Lady might be willing enough to throw
	<lb/>off the Intruder at firſt, but wanted Cou­
	<lb/>rage to get above the fear of his Calumnies,
	<lb/>and the longer ſhe ſuffers him to buz about
	<lb/>her, ſhe will find it the harder to get rid of 
	<lb/>his Importunities. By all which it appears
	<lb/>that ſhe who really intends to be ſecure,
	<lb/>muſt keep at the greateſt diſtance from
	<lb/>Danger, ſhe muſt not grant the <emph>leaſt</emph> Indul­
	<lb/>gence, where ſuch ill uſes will be made of it.</p>
        <p>And ſince the caſe is ſo, that Woman
	<lb/>can never be in ſafety who allows a Man
	<lb/>opportunity to betray her. Frequent Con­
	<lb/>verſation does for certain produce either
	<lb/>Averſion or Liking, and when 'tis once
	<lb/>come to Liking, it depends on the Man's
	<lb/>Generoſity not to improve it farther, and
	<lb/>where can one find an Inſtance that this
	<lb/>is any ſecurity? There are very many in­
	<lb/>deed which ſhew it is none. How ſenſible
	<lb/>ſoever a Woman may appear of another's
	<lb/>Indiſcretion, if ſhe will tread in the ſame
	<lb/>Steps, tho' but for a little way, ſhe gives
	<lb/>us no aſſurance that ſhe will not fall into
	  <mw rend="align(center)" type="sig">F3</mw>
	  <mw rend="break(no)" type="catch">the</mw>

<pb n="70"/>
<milestone n="F3v" unit="sig"/>
<mw rend="align(left)" type="pageNum">70</mw>
	<lb/>the ſame Folly, ſhe may perhaps intend
	<lb/>very well, but ſhe puts it paſt her Power
	<lb/>to fulfil her good Intentions. Even thoſe
	<lb/>who have forfeited their Diſcretion, the
	<lb/>moſt valuable thing next to their Vertue,
	<lb/>and without which Vertue it ſelf is but
	<lb/>very weak and faint, 'tis like were once
	<lb/>as well reſolv'd as ſhe, they had the very
	<lb/>ſame Thoughts, they made the ſame Apo­
	<lb/>logies, and their Reſentment wou'd have
	<lb/>been every whit as great againſt thoſe
	<lb/>who cou'd have imagin'd they ſhou'd ſo far
	<lb/>forget themſelves.</p>
        <p>It were endleſs to reckon up the divers
	<lb/>Stratagems Men uſe to catch their Prey,
	<lb/>their different ways of inſinuating which
	<lb/>vary with Circumſtances and the Ladies
	<lb/>Temper. But how unfairly, how baſely
	<lb/>ſoever they proceed, when the Prey is once
	<lb/>caught it paſſes for lawful Prize, and o­
	<lb/>ther Men having the ſame hopes and pro­
	<lb/>jects ſee nothing to find fault with, but
	<lb/>that it was not their own Good Fortune.
	<lb/>They may exclaim againſt it perhaps in a
	<lb/>Lady's hearing, but it is only to keep
	<lb/>themſelves from being ſuſpected, and to
	<lb/>give the better Colour to their own De­
	<lb/>ſigns. Sometimes a Woman is cajol'd, and
	<lb/>ſometimes Hector'd, ſhe is ſeduc'd to Love
	<lb/>a Man, or aw'd into a Fear of him: He
	<lb/>defends her Honour againſt another, or
	  <mw type="catch">aſſumes</mw>

<pb n="71"/>
<milestone n="F4r" unit="sig"/>
<mw type="pageNum">71</mw>
	<lb/>aſſumes the Power of blaſting it himſelf;
	<lb/>was willing to paſs for one of no Conſe­
	<lb/>quence till he cou'd make himſelf conſi­
	<lb/>derable at her Coſt. He might be admit­
	<lb/>ted at firſt to be <mcr>her Jeſt</mcr>, but he carries on
	<lb/>the humor ſo far till he makes her <mcr>his;</mcr> he
	<lb/>will either entertain or ſerve her as occa­
	<lb/>ſion offers, and ſome way or other gets
	<lb/>himſelf intruſted with her Fortune, her
	<lb/>Fame, or her Soul. Allow him but a fre­
	<lb/>quent and free Converſation, and there's
	<lb/>no manner of Queſtion but that his Inge­
	<lb/>nuity and Application will at one time or
	<lb/>other get the Aſcendant over her.</p>
        <p>And generally the more humble and un­
	<lb/>deſigning a Man appears, the more impro­
	<lb/>bable it looks that he ſhould dare to pre­
	<lb/>tend, the greater Caution ſhou'd be us'd
	<lb/>againſt him. A bold Addreſs and good
	<lb/>Aſſurance may ſometimes, but does not
	<lb/>always, take. To a Woman of Senſe an
	<lb/>artificial Modeſty and Humility is a thou­
	<lb/>ſand times more dangerous, for he only
	<lb/>draws back to receive the more Encourage­
	<lb/>ment, and ſhe regards not what Advances
	<lb/>ſhe makes towards him, who ſeems to un­
	<lb/>derſtand himſelf and the World ſo well, as
	<lb/>to be incapable of making an ill uſe of
	<lb/>them. Wou'd it not be unreaſonable and a
	<lb/>piece of Ill-breeding to be ſhy of him who
	<lb/>has no Pretentions, or only ſuch as are
	  <mw rend="align(center)" type="sig">F4</mw>
	  <mw rend="break(no)" type="catch">Juſt</mw>

<pb n="72"/>
<milestone n="F4v" unit="sig"/>
<mw rend="align(left)" type="pageNum">72</mw>
	<lb/>Juſt and Modeſt? What hurt in a Viſit?
	<lb/>Or what if Viſits grow a little more fre­
	<lb/>quent? The Man has ſo much diſcern­
	<lb/>ment, as to reliſh her Wit and Humour,
	<lb/>and can ſhe do leſs than be Partial to him
	<lb/>who is ſo Juſt to her? He ſtrives to pleaſe
	<lb/>and to render himſelf agreeable, or neceſ­
	<lb/>ſary perhaps, and whoever will make it
	<lb/>his Buſineſs may find ways enough to do
	<lb/>it. For they know but little of Human
	<lb/>Nature, they never conſulted their own
	<lb/>Hearts, who are not ſenſible what ad­
	<lb/>vances a well-manag'd Flattery makes,
	<lb/>eſpecially from a Perſon of whoſe Wit and
	<lb/>Senſe one has a good Opinion. His Wit at
	<lb/>firſt recommends his Flatteries, and theſe in
	<lb/>requital ſet off his Wit; and ſhe who has
	<lb/>been us'd to this high-ſeaſon'd Diet, will
	<lb/>ſcarce ever reliſh another Converſation.</p>
        <p>Having got thus far to be ſure he is not
	<lb/>wanting to his good Fortune, but drives
	<lb/>on to an Intimacy, or what they are pleas'd
	<lb/>now a-days, tho' very unjuſtly, to call a
	<lb/>Friendſhip; all is ſafe under this ſacred
	<lb/>Character, which ſets them above little
	<lb/>Aims and mean Deſigns. A Character that
	<lb/>muſt be conducted with the niceſt Honour,
	<lb/>allows the greateſt Truſts, leads to the
	<lb/>higheſt Improvements, is attended with
	<lb/>the pureſt Pleaſures and moſt rational Sa­
	<lb/>tisfaction. And what if the malicious
	  <mw type="catch">World,</mw>

<pb n="73"/>
<milestone n="F5r" unit="sig"/>
<mw type="pageNum">73</mw>
	<lb/>World, envious of his Happineſs, ſhou'd
	<lb/>take Offence at it, ſince he has taken all
	<lb/>due Precautions, ſuch unjuſt and ill-na­
	<lb/>tur'd Cenſures are not to be regarded; for
	<lb/>his part the diſtance that is between them
	<lb/>checks all aſpiring deſires, but her Con­
	<lb/>verſation is what he muſt not, cannot
	<lb/>want, Life is inſipid and not to be en­
	<lb/>dur'd without it; and he is too much the 
	<lb/>Lady's Friend, has too juſt a Value for
	<lb/>her to entertain a Thought to her diſad­
	<lb/>vantage!</p>
        <p>Now if once it is come to this, <mcr rend="slant(upright)case(allcaps)">God</mcr>
	<lb/>help the poor Woman, for not much Ser­
	<lb/>vice can be done her by any of her Friends
	<lb/>on Earth. That Pretender to be ſure will
	<lb/>be the Darling, he will worm out every
	<lb/>other Perſon, tho' ever ſo kind and diſin­
	<lb/>tereſted. For tho' true Friends will en­
	<lb/>deavour to pleaſe in order to ſerve, their
	<lb/>Complaiſance never goes ſo far as to prove
	<lb/>injurious; the beloved Fault is what they
	<lb/>chiefly ſtrike at, and this the Flatterer al­
	<lb/>ways ſooths; ſo that at laſt he becomes
	<lb/>the moſt acceptable Company, and they
	<lb/>who are conſcious of their own Integrity
	<lb/>are not apt to bear ſuch an unjuſt Diſtin­
	<lb/>ction, nor is it by this time to any purpoſe
	<lb/>to remonſtrate the Danger of ſuch an In­
	<lb/>timacy. When a Man, and for certain
	<lb/>much more when a Woman, is fallen into
	  <mw type="catch">this</mw>

<pb n="74"/>
<milestone n="F5v" unit="sig"/>
<mw rend="align(left)" type="pageNum">74</mw>
	<lb/>this Toyl, that is, when either have been
	<lb/>ſo unwary and indiſcreet as to let another
	<lb/>find out by what Artifices he may manage
	<lb/>their Self-love, and draw it over to his
	<lb/>Party, 'tis too late for any one who is really
	<lb/>their Friend, to break the Snare and diſ­
	<lb/>abuſe them.</p>
        <p>Neither Sex cares to deny themſelves
	<lb/>that which pleaſes, eſpecially when they
	<lb/>think they may innocently indulge it; and
	<lb/>nothing pleaſes more than the being ad­
	<lb/>mir'd and humour'd. We may be told of
	<lb/>the Danger, and ſhown the Fall of others,
	<lb/>but tho' their Misfortunes are ever ſo of­
	<lb/>ten or ſo lively repreſented to us, we are
	<lb/>all ſo well aſſur'd of our own good Con­
	<lb/>duct, as to believe it will bring us ſafe off
	<lb/>thoſe Rocks on which others have been
	<lb/>Shipwrackt. We ſuppoſe it in our Power
	<lb/>to ſhorten the Line of our Liberty when
	<lb/>ever we think fit, not conſidering that the
	<lb/>farther we run, we ſhall be the more unwil­
	<lb/>ling to Retreat and unable to judge when
	<lb/>a Retreat is neceſſary. A Woman does not
	<lb/>know that ſhe is more than half loſt when
	<lb/>ſhe admits of theſe Suggeſtions; that thoſe
	<lb/>Arguments ſhe brings for continuing a
	<lb/>Man's Converſation, prove only that ſhe
	<lb/>ought to have quitted it ſooner; that Li­
	<lb/>king inſenſibly converts to Love, and that
	<lb/>when ſhe admits a Man to be her Friend,
	  <mw type="catch">'tis</mw>

<pb n="75"/>
<milestone n="F6r" unit="sig"/>
<mw type="pageNum">75</mw>
	<lb/>'tis his Fault if <choice><sic>b</sic><corr>h</corr></choice>e does not make himſelf
	<lb/>her Huſband.</p>
        <p>And if Men even the Modeſteſt and the
	<lb/>Beſt, are only in purſuit of their own De­
	<lb/>ſigns, when they pretend to do the Lady
	<lb/>Service; if the Honour they wou'd ſeem
	<lb/>to do her, tends only to lead her into an
	<lb/>Imprudent and therefore a Diſhonourable
	<lb/>Action; and they have all that good Opi­
	<lb/>nion of themſelves as to take every thing
	<lb/>for Encouragement, ſo that ſhe who goes
	<lb/>beyond a bare Civility tho' ſhe meant no
	<lb/>more than Reſpect, will find it Interpreted
	<lb/>a Favour and made ill Uſe of, (for Favours
	<lb/>how Innocent ſoever, never turn to a La­
	<lb/>dy's advantage;) what ſhadow of a Pre­
	<lb/>tence can a Woman have for admitting an
	<lb/>intimacy with a Man whoſe Principles
	<lb/>are known to be Looſe and his Practices
	<lb/>Licentious? can ſhe expect to be ſafe with
	<lb/>him who has ruin'd others, and by the
	<lb/>very ſame Methods he takes with her? If
	<lb/>an Intimacy with a Man of a fair Character
	<lb/>gives Offence, with a Man of an ill One,
	<lb/>'tis doubly and trebly Scandalous. And
	<lb/>ſuppoſe neither her Fortune nor Beauty
	<lb/>can Tempt him, he has his ill-natur'd
	<lb/>Pleaſure in deſtroying that Vertue he will
	<lb/>not Practiſe, or if that can't be done, in
	<lb/>blaſting the Reputation of it at leaſt, and
	<lb/>in making the World believe he has made
	<lb/>a Conqueſt tho' he has found a Foil.</p>
        <mw rend="break(no)" type="catch">If</mw>
        <pb n="76"/>
        <milestone n="F6v" unit="sig"/>
        <mw rend="align(left)" type="pageNum">76</mw>
        <p>If the Man be the Woman's Inferior,
	<lb/>beſides all the Dangers formerly men­
	<lb/>tion'd, and thoſe juſt now taken notice of,
	<lb/>ſhe gives ſuch a Countenance to his Vices
	<lb/>as renders her in great meaſure partaker
	<lb/>in them, and it can ſcarce be thought in
	<lb/>ſuch Circumſtances, a Woman cou'd Like
	<lb/>the Man if ſhe were not reconcil'd to his
	<lb/>Faults. Is he her Equal and no unſuitable
	<lb/>Match, if his Deſigns are fair, why don't
	<lb/>they Marry, ſince they are ſo well pleas'd
	<lb/>with each other's Converſation, which in
	<lb/>this State only can be frequently and ſafely
	<lb/>allow'd? Is he her Better, and ſhe hopes
	<lb/>by catching him to make her Fortune,
	<lb/>alas! the poor Woman is neither acquaint­
	<lb/>ed with the World nor her ſelf, ſhe nei­
	<lb/>ther knows her own Weakneſs nor his
	<lb/>Treachery, and tho' he gives ever ſo much
	<lb/>Encouragement to this vain Hope, 'tis only
	<lb/>in order to accompliſh her ruin. To be
	<lb/>ſure the more Freedom ſhe allows, the
	<lb/>more ſhe Leſſens his Eſteem, and that's not
	<lb/>likely to encreaſe a real, tho' it may a pre­
	<lb/>tended kindneſs; ſhe ought to fly, if ſhe
	<lb/>wou'd have him purſue, the ſtricteſt Ver­
	<lb/>tue and Reſerve being the only way to
	<lb/>ſecure him.</p>
        <p>Religion and Reputation are ſo ſure a
	<lb/>Guard, ſuch a ſecurity to poor defenceleſs
	<lb/>Woman, that whenever a Man has ill De­
	  <mw type="catch">ſigns</mw>

<pb n="77"/>
<milestone n="F7r" unit="sig"/>
<mw type="pageNum">77</mw>
	<lb/>ſigns on her, he is ſure to make a Breach
	<lb/><ref xml:id="er15" type="correction" target="#ec15">into</ref> one or both of theſe, 
            by endeavour­
	<lb/>ing either to corrupt her Principles to
	<lb/>make her leſs ſtrict in Devotion, or to
	<lb/>leſſen her value of a fair Reputation, and
	<lb/>wou'd perſwade her that leſs than ſhe ima­
	<lb/>gines will ſecure her as to the next World,
	<lb/>and that not much regard is to be given to
	<lb/>the cenſures of this. Or if this be too
	<lb/>bold at firſt, and will not paſs with her,
	<lb/>he has another way to make even her
	<lb/>Love to Vertue contribute to its ruin, by
	<lb/>perſwading her it never Shines as it ought
	<lb/>unleſs it be expos'd, and that ſhe has no
	<lb/>reaſon to Boaſt of her Vertue unleſs ſhe
	<lb/>has try'd it. An Opinion of the worſt
	<lb/>conſequence that may be, and the moſt
	<lb/>miſchievous to a Woman, becauſe it is
	<lb/>calculated to feed her Vanity, and tends
	<lb/>indeed to her utter Ruin. For can it be fit
	<lb/>to ruſh into Temptations when we are
	<lb/>taught every day to pray againſt them? If
	<lb/>the Trials of our Vertue render it Illuſtri­
	<lb/>ous, 'tis ſuch Trials as Heaven is pleas'd
	<lb/>to ſend us, not thoſe of our own ſeeking.
	<lb/>It holds true of both Sexes, that next to
	<lb/>the Divine Grace, a Modeſt Diſtruſt of
	<lb/>themſelves is their beſt Security, none be­
	<lb/>ing ſo often and ſo ſhamefully Foil'd, as
	<lb/>thoſe who depend moſt on their own
	<lb/>Strength and Reſolution.</p>
        <mw type="catch">As</mw>
        <pb n="78"/>
        <milestone n="F7v" unit="sig"/>
        <mw rend="align(left)" type="pageNum">78</mw>
        <p>As to the Opinion of the World, tho'
	<lb/>one cannot ſay it is always juſt, yet ge­
	<lb/>nerally it has a Foundation; great regard
	<lb/>is to be paid to it, and very good uſe to be
	<lb/>made of it. Others <emph>may</emph> be in fault for
	<lb/>paſſing their Cenſures, but we certainly
	<lb/><emph>are</emph> ſo if we give them any the leaſt juſt
	<lb/>occaſion. And ſince Reputation is not only
	<lb/>one of the Rewards of Vertue, that which
	<lb/>always ought, and generally does attend it,
	<lb/>but alſo a Guard againſt Evil, an Induce­
	<lb/>ment to Good, and a great Inſtrument in
	<lb/>the Hand of the Wiſe to promote the
	<lb/>common cauſe of Vertue, the being Pro­
	<lb/>digal of the one, looks as if we ſet no great
	<lb/>value on the other, and ſhe who abandons
	<lb/>her good Name is not like to preſerve her
	<lb/>Innocence.</p>
        <p>A Woman therefore can never have too
	<lb/>nice a Senſe of Honour, provided ſhe does
	<lb/>not prefer it before her Duty; ſhe can
	<lb/>never be too careful to ſecure her Chara­
	<lb/>cter, not only from the ſuſpicion of a
	<lb/>Crime, but even from the ſhadow of an
	<lb/>Indiſcretion. 'Tis well worth her while
	<lb/>to renounce the moſt Entertaining, and
	<lb/>what ſome perhaps will call the moſt Im­
	<lb/>proving Company, rather than give the
	<lb/>World a juſt occaſion of Suſpicion or Cen­
	<lb/>ſure. For beſides the Injury that is done
	<lb/>Religion, which enjoyns us to avoid the
	  <mw type="catch">very</mw>

<pb n="79"/>
<milestone n="F8r" unit="sig"/>
<mw type="pageNum">79</mw>
	<lb/>very Appearance of Evil, and to do no­
	<lb/>thing but what is of good Report, ſhe puts
	<lb/>her ſelf too much in a Man's Power who
	<lb/>will run ſuch a riſque for his Converſati­
	<lb/>on, and expreſſes ſuch a value for him, as
	<lb/>cannot fail of being made uſe of to do her
	<lb/>a miſchief.</p>
        <p>Preſerve your diſtance then, keep out of
	<lb/>the reach of Danger, fly if you wou'd be
	<lb/>ſafe, be ſure to be always on the Reſerve,
	<lb/>not ſuch as is Moroſe and Affected, but
	<lb/>Modeſt and Diſcreet, your Caution can­
	<lb/>not be too great, nor your Foreſight reach
	<lb/>too far; there's nothing, or what is next
	<lb/>to nothing, a little Amuſement and en­
	<lb/>tertaining Converſation loſt by this, but
	<lb/>all is hazarded by the other. A Man un­
	<lb/>derſtands his own Merit too well to loſe
	<lb/>his time in a Woman's Company, were it
	<lb/>not to divert himſelf at her coſt, to turn
	<lb/>her into a Jeſt or ſomething worſe. And
	<lb/>wherever you ſee great Aſſiduities, when
	<lb/>a Man inſinuates into the Diverſions and
	<lb/>Humors of the Lady, Liking and Admi­
	<lb/>ring whatever ſhe does, tho' at the ſame 
	<lb/>time he ſeems to keep a due Diſtance, or
	<lb/>rather exceeds in the profoundeſt Reſpect,
	<lb/>Reſpect being all he dare at preſent pre­
	<lb/>tend to; when a more than ordinary de­
	<lb/>ference is paid; when ſomething particu­
	<lb/>lar appears in the Look <choice><sic>u</sic><corr>a</corr></choice>nd Addreſs, and
	  <mw type="catch">ſuch</mw>

<pb n="80"/>
<milestone n="F8v" unit="sig"/>
<mw rend="align(left)" type="pageNum">80</mw>
	<lb/>ſuch an Obſequiouſneſs in every Action,
	<lb/>as nothing cou'd engage a Man to, who
	<lb/>never forgets the Superiority of his Sex,
	<lb/>but a hope to be Obſerv'd in his turn:
	<lb/>Then, whatever the Inequality be, and how
	<lb/>ſenſible ſoever he ſeems to be of it, the
	<lb/>Man has for certain his Engines at work,
	<lb/>the Mine is ready to ſpring on the firſt
	<lb/>opportunity, and 'tis well if it be not
	<lb/>too late to prevent the poor Lady's Ruin.</p>
        <p>To wind up this matter, if a Woman
	<lb/>were duly Principled and Taught to know
	<lb/>the World, eſpecially the True Sentiments
	<lb/>that Men have of her, and the Traps
	<lb/>they lay for her under ſo many gilded
	<lb/>Compliments, and ſuch a ſeemingly great
	<lb/>Reſpect, that diſgrace wou'd be prevented
	<lb/>which is brought upon too many Fami­
	<lb/>lies, Women would Marry more diſcreet­
	<lb/>ly, and demean themſelves better in a
	<lb/>Married State than ſome People ſay they
	<lb/>do. The foundation indeed ought to be
	<lb/>laid deep and ſtrong, ſhe ſhou'd be made
	<lb/>a good <name rend="slant(upright)">Chriſtian</name>, and underſtand why ſhe
	<lb/>is ſo, and then ſhe well be every thing elſe
	<lb/>that is Good. Men need keep no Spies
	<lb/>on a Woman's Conduct, need have no fear
	<lb/>of her Vertue, or ſo much as of her Pru­
	<lb/>dence and Caution, were but a due ſenſe
	<lb/>of true Honour and Vertue awaken'd in
	<lb/>her, were her Reaſon excited and prepar'd
	  <mw type="catch">to</mw>

<pb n="81"/>
<milestone n="G1r" unit="sig"/>
<mw type="pageNum"><choice><sic type="seq">83</sic><corr>81</corr></choice></mw>
	<lb/>to conſider the Sophiſtry of thoſe Tempta­
	<lb/>tions which wou'd perſwade her from her
	<lb/>Duty; and were ſhe put in a way to know
	<lb/>that it is both her Wiſdom and Intereſt to
	<lb/>obſerve it; She would then duly examine
	<lb/>and weigh all the Circumſtances, the
	<lb/>Good and Evil of a Married State, and not
	<lb/>be ſurpriz'd with unforeſeen Inconveni­
	<lb/>encies, and either never conſent to be a
	<lb/>Wife, or make a good one when ſhe does.
	<lb/>This would ſhew her what Human Na­
	<lb/>ture <mcr>is</mcr>, as well as what it <mcr>ought</mcr> to be, and
	<lb/>teach her not only what ſhe may juſtly ex­
	<lb/>pect, but what ſhe muſt be Content with;
	<lb/>would enable her to cure ſome Faults, and
	<lb/>patiently to ſuffer what ſhe cannot cure.</p>
        <p>Indeed nothing can aſſure Obedience,
	<lb/>and render it what it ought to be, but the
	<lb/>Conſcience of Duty, the paying it for
	<lb/><mcr rend="slant(upright)case(allcaps)">God's</mcr> ſake. Superiors don't rightly un­
	<lb/>derſtand their own Intereſt when they at­
	<lb/>tempt to put out their Subjects Eyes to
	<lb/>keep them Obedient. A Blind Obedience
	<lb/>is what a Rational Creature ſhou'd never
	<lb/>Pay, nor wou'd ſuch an one receive it did
	<lb/>he rightly underſtand its Nature. For
	<lb/>Human Actions are no otherwiſe valua­
	<lb/>ble than as they are conformable to Rea­
	<lb/>ſon, but a blind Obedience is an Obeying
	<lb/><mcr>without Reaſon</mcr>, for ought we know <mcr>againſt
	<lb/>it</mcr>. <mcr rend="slant(upright)case(allcaps)">God</mcr> himſelf does not require our
	  <mw rend="align(center)" type="sig">G</mw>
	  <mw rend="break(no)" type="catch">Obedi-</mw>

<pb n="82"/>
<milestone n="G1v" unit="sig"/>
<mw rend="align(left)" type="pageNum"><choice><sic type="seq">84</sic><corr>82</corr></choice></mw>
	<lb/>Obedience at this rate, he lays before us
	<lb/>the goodneſs and reaſonableneſs of his
	<lb/>Laws, and were there any thing in them
	<lb/>whoſe Equity we could not readily com­
	<lb/>prehend, yet we have this clear and ſuffi­
	<lb/>cient Reaſon on which to found our Obe­
	<lb/>dience, that nothing but what's Juſt and
	<lb/>Fit, can be enjoyn'd by a Juſt, a Wiſe
	<lb/>and Gracious <mcr rend="slant(upright)case(allcaps)">God</mcr>, but this is a Reaſon
	<lb/>will never hold in reſpect of Men's Com­
	<lb/>mands, unleſs they can prove themſelves
	<lb/>Infallible, and conſequently Impeccable
	<lb/>too.</p>
        <p>It is therefore very much a Man's In­
	<lb/>tereſt that Women ſhould be good <name rend="slant(upright)">Chri­
	<lb/>ſtians</name>, in this as in every other In­
	<lb/>ſtance, he who does his Duty, finds his
	<lb/>own account in it. Duty and true Inte­
	<lb/>reſt are one and the ſame thing, and he
	<lb/>who thinks otherwiſe is to be pitied for
	<lb/>being ſo much in the Wrong; but what
	<lb/>can be more the Duty of the Head, than
	<lb/>to Inſtruct and Improve thoſe who are
	<lb/>under Government? She will freely leave
	<lb/>him the quiet Dominion of this World,
	<lb/>whoſe Thoughts and Expectations are
	<lb/>plac'd on the next. A Proſpect of <placeName rend="slant(upright)">Hea­
	<lb/>ven</placeName>, and that only, will cure that Ambi­
	<lb/>tion which all Generous Minds are fill'd
	<lb/>with; not by taking it away, but by pla­
	<lb/>cing it on a right Object. She will di­
	  <mw type="catch">ſcern</mw>

<pb n="83"/>
<milestone n="G2r" unit="sig"/>
<mw type="pageNum"><choice><sic type="seq">85</sic><corr>83</corr></choice></mw>
	<lb/>ſcern a time when her Sex ſhall be no bar
	<lb/>to the beſt Employments, the higheſt
	<lb/>Honour; a time when that diſtinction, now
	<lb/>ſo much us'd to her Prejudice, ſhall be no
	<lb/>more, but provided ſhe is not wanting to
	<lb/>her ſelf, her Soul ſhall ſhine as bright as
	<lb/>the greateſt Heroe's. This is a true, and
	<lb/>indeed the only conſolation, this makes
	<lb/>her a ſufficient compenſation for all the
	<lb/>neglect and contempt the ill-grounded
	<lb/>Cuſtoms of the World throw on her, for
	<lb/>all the Injuries brutal Power may do her,
	<lb/>and is a ſufficient Cordial to ſupport her
	<lb/>Spirits, be her Lot in this World what
	<lb/>it may.</p>
        <p>But ſome ſage Perſons may perhaps ob­
	<lb/>ject, that were Women allow'd to Im­
	<lb/>prove themſelves, and not amongſt other
	<lb/>diſcouragements driven back by thoſe
	<lb/>wiſe Jeſts and Scoffs that are put upon
	<lb/>a Woman of Senſe or Learning, a Phi­
	<lb/>loſophical Lady as ſhe is call'd by way
	<lb/>of Ridicule, they would be too Wiſe
	<lb/>and too Good for the Men; I grant it,
	<lb/>for vicious and fooliſh Men. Nor is it to
	<lb/>be wonder'd, that he is afraid he ſhou'd
	<lb/>not be able to Govern them were their
	<lb/>Underſtandings improv'd, who is reſolv'd
	<lb/>not to take too much Pains with his
	<lb/>own. But theſe 'tis to be hop'd are no
	<lb/>very conſiderable N<choice><sic>m</sic><corr>u</corr></choice>mber, the fooliſh at
	  <mw type="catch">leaſt;</mw>

<pb n="84"/>
<milestone n="G2v" unit="sig"/>
<mw rend="align(left)" type="pageNum"><choice><sic type="seq">86</sic><corr>84</corr></choice></mw>
	<lb/>leaſt; and therefore this is ſo far from
	<lb/>being an Argument againſt Women's
	<lb/>Improvement, that it is a ſtrong one for
	<lb/>it, if we do but ſuppoſe the Men to be
	<lb/>as capable of Improvement as the Wo­
	<lb/>men, but much more if according to
	<lb/>Tradition we believe they have greater
	<lb/>Capacities. This, if any thing, wou'd
	<lb/>ſtir them up to be what they ought, and
	<lb/>not permit them to waſt their Time and
	<lb/>abuſe their Faculties, in the Service of
	<lb/>their irregular Appetites and unreaſon­
	<lb/>able Deſires, and ſo let poor contempti­
	<lb/>ble Women who have been their Slaves,
	<lb/>excel them in all that is truly Excellent.
	<lb/>This wou'd make them Bluſh at employ­
	<lb/>ing an immortal Mind no better than in
	<lb/>making Proviſion for the Fleſh to fulfil
	<lb/>the Luſts thereof, ſince Women by a Wi­
	<lb/>ſer Conduct have brought themſelves to
	<lb/>ſuch a reach of Thought, to ſuch exact­
	<lb/>neſs of Judgment, ſuch clearneſs and
	<lb/>ſtrength of Reaſoning, ſuch purity and
	<lb/>elevation of Mind, ſuch Command of
	<lb/>their Paſſions, ſuch regularity of Will
	<lb/>and Affection, and in a word, to ſuch a
	<lb/>pitch of Perfection, as the Human Soul
	<lb/>is capable of attaining in this Life by
	<lb/>the Grace of <mcr rend="slant(upright)case(allcaps)">God</mcr>, ſuch true Wiſdom,
	<lb/>ſuch real Greatneſs, as tho, it does not
	<lb/>qualifie them to make a Noiſe in this
	  <mw type="catch">World,</mw>

<pb n="85"/>
<milestone n="G3r" unit="sig"/>
<mw type="pageNum"><choice><sic type="seq">78</sic><corr>85</corr></choice></mw>
	<lb/>World, to found or overturn Empires,
	<lb/>yet it qualifies them for what is infinitely
	<lb/>better, a Kingdom that cannot be mov'd,
	<lb/>and incorruptible Crown of Glory.</p>
        <p>Beſides, it were ridiculous to ſuppoſe
	<lb/>that a Woman, were ſhe ever ſo much
	<lb/>improv'd, cou'd come near the topping
	<lb/>Genius of the Men, and therefore why
	<lb/>ſhou'd they envy or diſcourage her?
	<lb/>Strength of Mind goes along with
	<lb/>Strength of Body, and 'tis only for ſome
	<lb/>odd Accidents which Philoſophers have
	<lb/>not yet thought worth while to enquire
	<lb/>into, that the Sturdieſt Porter is not
	<lb/>the Wiſest Man! As therefore the Men
	<lb/>have the Power in their Hands, ſo there's
	<lb/>no diſpute of their having the Brains
	<lb/>to manage it! Can we ſuppoſe there is
	<lb/>ſuch a thing as good Judgment and Senſe
	<lb/>upon <placeName rend="slant(upright)">Earth</placeName>, if it is not be found a­
	<lb/>mong them? Do not they generally
	<lb/>ſpeaking do all the great Actions and con­
	<lb/>ſiderable Buſineſs of this World, and
	<lb/>leave that of the next to the Women?
	<lb/>Their Subtilty in forming Cabals and
	<lb/>laying deep Deſigns, their Courage and
	<lb/>Conduct in breaking through all Tyes
	<lb/>Sacred and Civil to effect them, not only
	<lb/>advances them to the Poſt of Honour, and
	<lb/>keeps them ſecurely in it for twenty or
	<lb/>thirty Years, but gets them a Name, and
	  <mw rend="align(center)" type="sig"><choice><sic type="seq">G4</sic><corr>G3</corr></choice></mw>
	  <mw rend="break(no)" type="catch">conveys</mw>

<pb n="86"/>
<milestone n="G3v" unit="sig"/>
<mw rend="align(left)" type="pageNum"><choice><sic type="seq">88</sic><corr>86</corr></choice></mw>
	<lb/>conveys it down to Poſterity for ſome
	<lb/>Hundreds, and who wou'd look any fur­
	<lb/>ther? Juſtice and injuſtice are admini­
	<lb/>stred by their Hands, Courts and Schools
	<lb/>are fill'd with theſe Sages; 'tis Men who
	<lb/>diſpute for Truth as well as Men who ar­
	<lb/>gue againſt it; Hiſtories are writ by 
	<lb/>them, they recount each others great Ex­
	<lb/>ploits, and have always done ſo. All fa­
	<lb/>mous Arts have their Original from Men,
	<lb/>even from the Invention of Guns to the
	<lb/>Myſtery of good Eating. And to ſhew
	<lb/>that nothing is beneath their Care, any
	<lb/>more than above their Reach, they have
	<lb/>brought <mcr>Gaming</mcr> to an Art and Science,
	<lb/>and a more Profitable and Honourable
	<lb/>one too, than any of thoſe that us'd to be
	<lb/>call'd <mcr>Liberal</mcr>! Indeed what is it they
	<lb/>can't perform, when they attempt it?
	<lb/>The Strength of their Brains ſhall be
	<lb/>every whit as Conſpicuous at their Cups
	<lb/>as in a Senate-Houſe, and when they
	<lb/>pleaſe they can make it paſs for as ſure
	<lb/>a Mark of Wiſdom, to drink deep as to
	<lb/>Reaſon profoundly; a greater proof of
	<lb/>Courage and conſequently of Underſtand­
	<lb/>ing, to dare the Vengeance of Heaven it
	<lb/>ſelf, than to ſtand the Raillery of ſome of
	<lb/>the worſt of their fellow Creatures.</p>
        <p>Again, it may be ſaid, if a Wife's
	<lb/>caſe be as it is here repreſented, it is not
	  <mw type="catch">good</mw>

<pb n="87"/>
<milestone n="G4r" unit="sig"/>
<mw type="pageNum"><choice><sic type="seq">89</sic><corr>87</corr></choice></mw>
	<lb/>good for a Woman to Marry, and ſo
	<lb/>there's an end of Human Race. But this
	<lb/>is no fair Conſequence, for all that can
	<lb/>juſtly be inferr'd from hence, is that a
	<lb/>Woman has no mighty Obligations to the
	<lb/>Man who makes Love to her, ſhe has no
	<lb/>reaſon to be fond of being a Wife, or to
	<lb/>reckon it a piece of Preferment when ſhe
	<lb/>is taken to be a Man's Upper-Servant; it
	<lb/>is no advantage to her in this World, if
	<lb/>rightly manag'd it may prove one as to
	<lb/>the next. For ſhe who Marries purely to
	<lb/>do Good, to Educate Souls for Heaven,
	<lb/>who can be ſo truly mortify'd as to lay
	<lb/>aſide her own Will and Deſires, to pay
	<lb/>ſuch an intire Submiſſion for Life, to one
	<lb/>whom ſhe cannot be ſure will always de­
	<lb/>ſerve it, does certainly perform a more
	<lb/>Heroic Action than all the famous Maſ­
	<lb/>culine Heroes can boaſt of, ſhe ſuffers a
	<lb/>continual Martyrdom to bring Glory to
	<lb/><mcr rend="slant(upright)case(allcaps)">God</mcr> and Benefit to Mankind, which
	<lb/>conſideration indeed may carry her through
	<lb/>all Difficulties, I know not what elſe can,
	<lb/>and engage her to Love him who proves
	<lb/>perhaps ſo much worſe than a Brute, as
	<lb/>to make this Condition yet more grievous
	<lb/>than it needed to be. She has need of a
	<lb/>ſtrong Reaſon, of a truly Chriſtian and
	<lb/>well-temper'd Spirit, of all the Aſſiſtance
	<lb/>the beſt Education can give her, and ought
	  <mw type="catch">to</mw>

<pb n="88"/>
<milestone n="G4v" unit="sig"/>
<mw rend="align(left)" type="pageNum"><choice><sic type="seq">90</sic><corr>88</corr></choice></mw>
	<lb/>to have ſome good aſſurance of her own
	<lb/>Firmneſs and Vertue, who ventures on
	<lb/>ſuch a Trial; and for this Reaſon 'tis leſs
	<lb/>to be wonder'd at that Women Marry off
	<lb/>in haſt, for perhaps if they took time to
	<lb/>conſider and reflect upon it, they ſeldom
	<lb/>wou'd Marry.</p>
        <p>To conclude, perhaps I've ſaid more
	<lb/>than moſt Men will thank me for, I can­
	<lb/>not help it, for how much ſoever I may
	<lb/>be their Friend and humble Servant, I am
	<lb/>more a Friend to Truth. Truth is ſtrong,
	<lb/>and ſometime or other will prevail, nor is
	<lb/>it for their Honour, and therefore one
	<lb/>wou'd think not for their Intereſt, to be
	<lb/>Partial to themſelves and Unjuſt to others.
	<lb/>They may fancy I have made ſome diſ­
	<lb/>coveries which like <foreign xml:lang="la">Arcana Imperii</foreign>, ought
	<lb/>to be kept ſecret, but in good earneſt, I
	<lb/>do them more Honour than to ſuppoſe their
	<lb/>lawful Prerogatives need any mean Arts
	<lb/>to ſupport them. If they have Uſurpt,
	<lb/>I love Juſtice too much to wiſh Succeſs
	<lb/>and continuance to Uſurpations, which
	<lb/>tho' ſubmitted to out of Prudence, and
	<lb/>for Quietneſs ſake, yet leave every Bo­
	<lb/>dy free to regain their lawful Right when­
	<lb/>ever they have Power and Opportunity.
	<lb/>I don't ſay that Tyranny <mcr>ought</mcr>, but we
	<lb/>find in <mcr>Fact</mcr>, that it provokes the Op­
	  <mw type="catch">preſs'd</mw>

<pb n="89"/>
<milestone n="G5r" unit="sig"/>
<mw type="pageNum"><choice><sic type="seq">91</sic><corr>89</corr></choice></mw>
	<lb/>preſs'd to throw off even a Lawful Yoke
	<lb/>that fits too heavy: And if he who is
	<lb/>freely Elected, after all his fair Promiſes
	<lb/>and the fine Hopes he rais'd, proves a Ty­
	<lb/>rant, the conſideration that he was one's
	<lb/>own Choice, will not render more Sub­
	<lb/>miſſive and Patient, but I fear more Refra­
	<lb/>ctory. For tho' it is very unreaſonable,
	<lb/>yet we ſee 'tis the courſe of the World,
	<lb/>not only to return Injury for Injury, but
	<lb/>Crime for Crime; both Parties indeed are
	<lb/>Guilty, but the Aggreſſors have a double
	<lb/>Guilt, they have not only their own,
	<lb/>but their Neighbours ruin to anſwer for.</p>
        <p>As to the Female Reader, I hope ſhe
	<lb/>will allow I've endeavour'd to do her
	<lb/>Juſtice, nor betray'd her Cauſe as her Ad­
	<lb/>vocates uſually do, under pretence of de­
	<lb/>fending it. A Practice too mean for any
	<lb/>to be Guilty of who have the leaſt Senſe
	<lb/>of Honour, and who do any more than
	<lb/>meerly pretend to it. I think I have held
	<lb/>the Ballance even, and not being conſci­
	<lb/>ous of Partiality I ask no Pardon for it.
	<lb/>To plead for the Oppreſs'd and to defend
	<lb/>the Weak ſeem'd to me a generous under­
	<lb/>taking; for tho' it may be ſecure, 'tis
	<lb/>not always Honourable to run over to the
	<lb/>ſtrongeſt Party. And if ſhe infers from
	<lb/>what has been ſaid that Marriage is a
	  <mw type="catch">very</mw>

<pb n="90"/>
<milestone n="G5v" unit="sig"/>
<mw rend="align(left)" type="pageNum"><choice><sic type="seq">92</sic><corr>90</corr></choice></mw>
	<lb/>very Happy State for Men, if they think
	<lb/>fit to make it ſo; that they govern the
	<lb/>World, they have Preſcription on their
	<lb/>ſide, Women are too weak to diſpute it
	<lb/>with them, therefore they, as all other
	<lb/>Governours, are moſt, if not only accoun­
	<lb/>table, for what's amiſs, for whether other
	<lb/>Governments in their Original, were or
	<lb/>were not confer'd according to the Merit
	<lb/>of the Perſon, yet certainly in this caſe,
	<lb/>if Heaven has appointed the Man to Go­
	<lb/>vern, it has qualify'd him for it: So far
	<lb/>I agree with her. But if ſhe goes on to
	<lb/>infer, that therefore if a Man has not
	<lb/>theſe Qualifications where is his Right?
	<lb/>That if he miſemploys, he abuſes it? And
	<lb/>if he abuſes, according to modern Dedu­
	<lb/>ction, he forfeits it, I muſt leave her there.
	<lb/>A peaceable Woman indeed will not carry
	<lb/>it ſo far, ſhe will neither queſtion her
	<lb/>Huſband's Right nor his Fitneſs to Go­
	<lb/>vern; but how? Not as an abſolute Lord
	<lb/>and Maſter, with an Arbitrary and Ty­
	<lb/>rannical ſway, but as Reaſon Governs and
	<lb/>Conducts a Man, by propoſing what is Juſt
	<lb/>and Fit.   And the Man who acts accord­
	<lb/>ing to that Wiſdom he aſſumes, who wou'd
	<lb/>have that Superiority he pretends to, ac­
	<lb/>knowledg'd Juſt, will receive no Injury by
	<lb/>any thing that has been offer'd here. A
	<lb/>Woman will value him the more who is
	  <mw type="catch">ſo</mw>

<pb n="91"/>
<milestone n="G6r" unit="sig"/>
<mw type="pageNum"><choice><sic type="seq">93</sic><corr>91</corr></choice></mw>
	<lb/>ſo Wiſe and Good, when ſhe diſcerns how
	<lb/>much he excels the reſt of his noble Sex;
	<lb/>the leſs he requires, the more will he Me­
	<lb/>rit that Eſteem and Deference, which 
	<lb/>thoſe who are ſo forward to exact, ſeem
	<lb/>conſcious they don't deſerve. So then the
	<lb/>Man's Prerogative is not at all infring'd,
	<lb/>whilſt the Woman's Privileges are ſecur'd;
	<lb/>and if any Woman think her ſelf Injur'd,
	<lb/>ſhe has a Remedy in reſerve which few
	<lb/>Men will Envy or endeavour to Rob her
	<lb/>of, the Exerciſe and Improvement of her
	<lb/>Vertue here, and the Reward of it here­
	<lb/>after.</p>
        <trailer rend="case(allcaps)pre(#rule)post(#rule)">The End.</trailer>
      
    </body>
    <pb n="92"/>
    <milestone n="G6v" unit="sig"/>
    <back>
      <div type="advert">
        <list>
          <head rend="first-indent(0)indent(1)"><hi rend="slant(upright)case(allcaps)">Books</hi> Printed for 
	  <persName ref="p:rwilkin.tox">Richard Wilkin</persName> at
	  <lb/>the <placeName>King's Head</placeName> in 
	    <placeName rend="slant(upright)">St. <hi rend="slant(italic)">Paul</hi>'s Church­
	  <lb/>Yard</placeName>.</head>
          <item>
            <advertisement>
              <p><title ref="b:TR00462"><hi rend="class(#DIC)">A</hi> Serious Propoſal to the Ladies for the Ad­
	<lb/>vancement of their true and greateſt Intereſt</title>, 
	<lb/>Part the Firſt, the fourth Edition.</p>
            </advertisement>
          </item>
          <item>
            <advertisement>
              <p><title ref="b:TR00462">A Serious Propoſal to the Ladies</title>, Part the Se­
	<lb/>cond. Wherein a Method is offered for the Im­
	<lb/>provement of their Minds.</p>
            </advertisement>
          </item>
          <item>
            <advertisement>
              <p><title ref="b:IT02937">Letters concerning the Love of God</title>, between
	<lb/>the Author of the Propoſal to the Ladies, and
	<lb/>M. <persName ref="p:jnorris.ccp">John Norris</persName>: Wherein his late Diſcourſe, ſhew­
	<lb/>ing, that it ought to be intire and excluſive of all
	<lb/>other Loves, is farther cleared and juſtified. 2d Edit.</p>
            </advertisement>
          </item>
          <item>
            <advertisement>
              <p><title ref="b:IT03115">Moderation truly ſtated: Or a Review of a late
	<lb/>Pamphlet, Entitled, <title ref="b:IT03115">Moderation a Vertue</title>. With
	<lb/>a Prefatory Diſcourſe to <persName ref="p:wdavenant.cpc"><hi rend="slant(upright)">Dr.</hi> 
            D'Avenant</persName>, concern­
              	<lb/>ing his late Eſſays on Peace and War.</title> 4 <hi rend="slant(italic)">to</hi>.</p>
            </advertisement>
          </item>
          <item>
            <advertisement>
              <p><title ref="b:IT02562">A Fair Way with the Diſſenters and their Pa­
	<lb/>trons</title>, not writ by <persName ref="p:lindsay.owt">Mr. L.――Y</persName>. or any other furious
	<lb/><name>Jacobite</name>, whether Clergyman or Layman, but by
	<lb/>a very Moderate Perſon and Dutiful Subject to
	<lb/>the Queen. <mcr>Quarto</mcr>.</p>
            </advertisement>
          </item>
          <item>
            <advertisement>
              <p><title ref="b:IT02810">An Impartial Enquiry into the Cauſes of Re­
	<lb/>bellion, and Civil War in this Kingdom</title>. In an 
	<lb/>Examination of <persName ref="p:wkennett.mxo"><hi rend="slant(upright)">Dr.</hi> Kennet's</persName> Sermon, 
            <date when="1704-01-30"><hi rend="slant(italic)">Jan.</hi> 30th
	<lb/>1704</date>. And Vindication of the Royal Martyr.
	<lb/><mcr>Quarto</mcr>.</p>
            </advertisement>
          </item>
          <item>
            <advertisement>
              <p><title ref="b:IT02273">The Chriſtian Religion as profeſſed by a
	<lb/>Daughter of the <name>Church of England</name></title>. Octavo.</p>
            </advertisement>
          </item>
        </list>
      </div>
    </back>
  </text>
</TEI>